<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
    <front>
        <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosntds</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1935-2735</issn><publisher>
                <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
            </publisher></journal-meta>
        <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PNTD-RA-1497R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041</article-id><article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                    <subject>Research Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
                    <subject>Infectious Diseases/Bacterial Infections</subject>
                    <subject>Infectious Diseases/Neglected Tropical Diseases</subject>
                </subj-group>
            </article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Phase Two Randomised Controlled Double Blind Trial of High Dose
                    Intravenous Methylprednisolone and Oral Prednisolone versus Intravenous Normal
                    Saline and Oral Prednisolone in Individuals with Leprosy Type 1 Reactions and/or
                    Nerve Function Impairment</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">RCT Methylprednisolone I in Type 1
                    Reactions</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Walker</surname>
                        <given-names>Stephen L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref>
                    <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
                        <sup>*</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Nicholls</surname>
                        <given-names>Peter G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                        <sup>2</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Dhakal</surname>
                        <given-names>Sushmita</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                        <sup>3</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Hawksworth</surname>
                        <given-names>Rachel A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                        <sup>3</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Macdonald</surname>
                        <given-names>Murdo</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                        <sup>3</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Mahat</surname>
                        <given-names>Kishori</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                        <sup>3</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Ruchal</surname>
                        <given-names>Shudan</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                        <sup>3</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Hamal</surname>
                        <given-names>Sushma</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                        <sup>3</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Hagge</surname>
                        <given-names>Deanna A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                        <sup>3</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Neupane</surname>
                        <given-names>Kapil D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                        <sup>3</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Lockwood</surname>
                        <given-names>Diana N. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
                <label>1</label>
                <addr-line>Department of Clinical Research, Faculty of Infectious and Tropical
                    Diseases, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, United
                    Kingdom</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff2">
                <label>2</label>
                <addr-line>School of Health Sciences, University of Southampton, Southampton, United
                    Kingdom</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff3">
                <label>3</label>
                <addr-line>Anandaban Hospital, Kathmandu, Nepal</addr-line>
            </aff><contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Phillips</surname>
                        <given-names>Richard O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <role>Editor</role>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Kwame Nkrumah University of Science and Technology (KNUST) School of
                Medical Sciences, Ghana</aff><author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">steve.walker@lshtm.ac.uk</email></corresp>
                <fn fn-type="con">
                    <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: SLW PGN RAH MM DNJL. Performed the
                        experiments: SLW SD RAH KM SR SH. Analyzed the data: SLW PGN. Contributed
                        reagents/materials/analysis tools: SLW DNJL. Wrote the paper: SLW DNJL.
                        Coordinated the study: SLW RAH MM DAH KDN.</p>
                </fn>
            <fn fn-type="conflict">
                <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
            </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>12</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e1041</elocation-id><history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>30</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>21</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Walker et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the
                terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
                distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and
                source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
                <sec>
                    <title>Background</title>
                    <p>Leprosy Type 1 reactions are a major cause of nerve damage and the
                        preventable disability that results. Type 1 reactions are treated with oral
                        corticosteroids and there are few data to support the optimal dose and
                        duration of treatment. Type 1 reactions have a Th1 immune profile: cells in
                        cutaneous and neural lesions expressing interferon-γ and interleukin-12.
                        Methylprednisolone has been used in other Th1 mediated diseases such as
                        rheumatoid arthritis in an attempt to switch off the immune response and so
                        we investigated the efficacy of three days of high dose (1 g) intravenous
                        methylprednisolone at the start of prednisolone therapy in leprosy Type 1
                        reactions and nerve function impairment.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                    <title>Results</title>
                    <p>Forty-two individuals were randomised to receive methylprednisolone followed
                        by oral prednisolone (n = 20) or oral prednisolone
                        alone (n = 22). There were no significant differences
                        in the rate of adverse events or clinical improvement at the completion of
                        the study. However individuals treated with methylprednisolone were less
                        likely than those treated with prednisolone alone to experience
                        deterioration in sensory function between day 29 and day 113 of the study.
                        The study also demonstrated that 50% of individuals with Type 1
                        reactions and/or nerve function impairment required additional prednisolone
                        despite treatment with 16 weeks of corticosteroids.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                    <title>Conclusions</title>
                    <p>The study lends further support to the use of more prolonged courses of
                        corticosteroid to treat Type 1 reactions and the investigation of risk
                        factors for the recurrence of Type 1 reaction and nerve function impairment
                        during and after a corticosteroid treatment.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                    <title>Trial Registration</title>
                    <p>Controlled-Trials.com<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.controlled-trials.com/ISRCTN31894035" xlink:type="simple">ISRCTN31894035</ext-link></p>
                </sec>
            </abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary">
                <title>Author Summary</title>
                <p>Leprosy is caused by a bacterium and is curable with a combination of antibiotics
                    known as multi-drug therapy that patients take for six or 12 months. However a
                    significant proportion of leprosy patients experience inflammation in their skin
                    and/or nerves, which may occur even after successful completion of multi-drug
                    therapy. These episodes of inflammation are called leprosy Type 1 reactions.
                    Type 1 reactions are an important complication of leprosy because they may
                    result in nerve damage that leads to disability and deformity. Type 1 reactions
                    require treatment with immunosuppressive agents such as corticosteroids. The
                    optimum dose and duration of corticosteroid therapy remains unclear. We
                    conducted a study to see if it would be safe to use a large dose of a
                    corticosteroid called methylprednisolone for three days at the start of a 16
                    week corticosteroid treatment regime of prednisolone in patients with leprosy
                    Type 1 reactions and leprosy patients with nerve damage present for less than
                    six months. We did this by comparing individuals who were given
                    methylprednisolone followed by prednisolone and those who received just
                    prednisolone. In this small study we did not see any significant difference in
                    the frequency of adverse events due to corticosteroid treatment in the two
                    groups. We did not demonstrate a significant difference in improvement in
                    individuals in the methylprednisolone group (who received a larger dose of
                    corticosteroids) than those in the prednisolone treated group. Overall
                    approximately 50% of individuals required more prednisolone in addition
                    to the 16 week course of treatment to prevent further nerve damage or reactions.
                    This suggests that it would be worthwhile investigating longer treatment courses
                    with corticosteroids and other immunosuppressive drugs.</p>
            </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by grants from LEPRA, the American Leprosy Mission, the
                    Special Trustees of the Hospital for Tropical Diseases, London, and the Geoffrey
                    Dowling Fellowship of the British Association of Dermatologists. The funders had
                    no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or
                    preparation of the manuscript. Anandaban Hospital is operated by The Leprosy
                    Mission Nepal.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
                <page-count count="10"/>
            </counts></article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec id="s1">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Leprosy is a chronic granulomatous infection principally affecting the skin and
                peripheral nerves caused by the obligate intracellular organism
                    <italic>Mycobacterium leprae</italic>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Lockwood1">[2]</xref>. The disease
                causes skin lesions and neuropathy. Complications secondary to the neuropathy can
                result in deformity and disability. 249 007 new cases of leprosy were diagnosed and
                reported to World Health Organization (WHO) in 2008 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-WHO1">[3]</xref>.</p>
            <p>Type 1 reactions (T1Rs) are a major cause of nerve function impairment (NFI) in
                patients with leprosy and affect up to 30% of susceptible individuals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Ranque1">[4]</xref>. T1Rs
                predominantly affect borderline leprosy<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Ranque1">[4]</xref>. They may be a presenting
                feature of leprosy or occur during multi-drug therapy (MDT) or after completion. A
                T1R is characterised by acute inflammation in skin lesions or nerves or both. Skin
                lesions become acutely inflamed and oedematous and may ulcerate. Oedema of the
                hands, feet and face can also be a feature of a T1R.</p>
            <p>Leprosy T1Rs are treated with oral corticosteroids. However treatment with a
                standardised reducing 12 week course of oral prednisolone (total dose 1.68 g) which
                had been used in a previous pilot study in Nepal resulted in 37% of
                individuals requiring additional prednisolone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Marlowe1">[5]</xref>. The randomised controlled
                treatment trials TRIPOD 2 and TRIPOD 3 that were reported during the design of this
                study had both used a 16 week course of oral prednisolone (total dose 2.52 g) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Richardus1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-vanBrakel1">[7]</xref>.</p>
            <p>T1Rs appear to be mediated via Th1 type cells and lesions in reaction express the
                pro-inflammatory IFNγ, IL12 and the oxygen free radical producer iNOS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Little1">[8]</xref>. The expression
                of TNFα protein in the skin and nerves of patients during T1Rs is increased<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-KhanolkarYoung1">[9]</xref>. High
                dose intravenous (IV) methylprednisolone (MP) has been used as a standard treatment
                in the early phase of an exacerbation of Th1 cytokine mediated relapsing chronic
                diseases. These conditions include rheumatoid arthritis (RA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Weusten1">[10]</xref> and multiple sclerosis (MS)
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Filippini1">[11]</xref>. In 18
                patients with MS treated with IV MP 1 g for three days there was a significant
                suppression of mitogen stimulated IFNγ, TNFα and IL2 production by blood
                leucocytes ex vivo after treatment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Wandinger1">[12]</xref>. MP has also been shown to
                reduce serum levels of TNFα in RA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Youssef1">[13]</xref>. Eleven patients given 1 g IV
                showed significantly reduced serum levels of TNFα at 4 and 24 hours. In a
                comparative study of lymphocyte-suppressive potency between prednisolone and MP in
                44 individuals with RA the latter was more effective in those with greater disease
                activity as defined by rheumatoid factor titres <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Hirano1">[14]</xref>.</p>
            <p>We compared three daily infusions of IV high dose MP and oral prednisolone with a 16
                week course of oral prednisolone alone. High dose IV MP had not been used previously
                in a trial of treatment of leprosy T1R so a Phase 2 trial was needed to confirm
                safety before considering whether to proceed to a larger Phase 3 trial of clinical
                efficacy.</p>
            <p>The aims of the trial were as follows:</p>
            <list list-type="order">
                <list-item>
                    <p>To assess the safety and tolerability of high dose MP when given to patients
                        with leprosy T1Rs and patients with leprosy associated acute neuritis with
                        nerve function impairment in Nepal.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                    <p>To assess the effect of high dose MP on the clinical outcome of leprosy T1Rs
                        and leprosy associated acute neuritis with nerve function impairment.</p>
                </list-item>
            </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
            <title>Methods</title>
            <p>A double blind parallel-group randomised controlled trial was designed to compare the
                safety and effect of early high dose IV MP followed by oral prednisolone with IV
                Normal saline and oral prednisolone. The study was approved by the Nepal Health
                Research Council and the Ethics Committee of the London School of Hygiene and
                Tropical Medicine (Number 4022).</p>
            <p>Participants (aged between 16–65 years and weighing more than 30 kg) were
                recruited from the leprosy service of Anandaban Hospital, Kathmandu, Nepal. Two
                groups of individuals were eligible for entry into the trial:</p>
            <list list-type="order">
                <list-item>
                    <p>Individuals diagnosed as having leprosy with clinical evidence of T1R of less
                        than six months duration.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                    <p>Individuals diagnosed with leprosy with new (less than six months duration)
                        NFI without inflammation of skin lesions (if skin lesions were present).</p>
                </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>Participants with any type of leprosy of the Ridley-Jopling Classification <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Ridley1">[15]</xref> were eligible.
                Initially, enrolment into the study required individuals with clinical evidence of a
                T1R to have associated nerve function impairment. This was changed nine months after
                the start of the trial so that individuals with T1Rs involving the skin only would
                also be eligible for enrolment. This was done because only 14 individuals had been
                recruited in this period and recruitment had been optimal as determined by case note
                review of a random selection of clinic attendees. The change to this eligibility
                criterion was approved by the two Ethics committees.</p>
            <p>The following individuals were excluded: those unwilling to give consent or return
                for follow-up or who had taken systemic steroids within three months of enrolment,
                those who had received other immunosuppressant therapy including thalidomide within
                three months of enrolment, those with severe active infection such as tuberculosis
                or severe intercurrent disease, those with a contraindication to high dose
                methylprednisolone such as peptic ulcer disease, diabetes mellitus, glaucoma and
                uncontrolled hypertension or known allergy to methylprednisolone. Pregnant women
                were excluded and females of child bearing capacity were not recruited unless they
                had at least one month of adequate contraception.</p>
            <p>The participants were treated with corticosteroids for 112 days. The total duration
                of the study was 337 days from entry into the trial. The intervention for the MP
                treated individuals was 1 gram MP in Normal saline given as an IV infusion and eight
                dummy tablets (Comprehensive Medical Services India, Chennai India) identical in
                appearance to prednisolone tablets daily for the first three days of the trial. The
                prednisolone treated individuals received 40 mg (eight tablets) of prednisolone and
                an identical appearing IV infusion which contained only Normal saline daily for the
                first three days of the trial. Thereafter individuals in both groups received the
                same reducing course of prednisolone. This course was prednisolone 40 mg daily from
                day 4 to day 14 of the study. The amount of prednisolone was then reduced to 35 mg
                daily for the next 14 days and then by a further 5 mg daily every 14 days to zero.
                An individual allocated to the MP group received a total dose of corticosteroid
                equivalent to 6.15 g of prednisolone. Individuals in the prednisolone alone group
                received 2.52 g of prednisolone in total.</p>
            <p>All individuals enrolled into the study received albendazole 400 mg daily for the
                first three days of the trial and famotidine 40 mg daily whilst they were receiving
                corticosteroids. The albendazole was given to reduce the risk of hyperinfection with
                    <italic>Strongyloides stercoralis</italic>. The famotidine was used to reduce
                the risk of peptic ulceration.</p>
            <p>The primary outcome measure was the frequency of adverse events in the two treatment
                arms. These were assessed by a study physician prior to treatment and then at day 4
                (after the three IV infusions) and then days 8, 15, 29, 57, 85, 113, 141, 169, 197,
                225, 253, 281, 309 and 337. Adverse events were enquired about and examined for at
                each assessment. A standardized form contained a list of adverse events attributable
                to corticosteroids which participants were asked if they had experienced. There was
                also a free text space available where other symptoms mentioned by the study
                participants or identified by the physician could be recorded. Adverse events were
                defined as major or minor in accordance with the classification used in the TRIPOD
                studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Richardus2">[16]</xref>.
                Major adverse events were defined as psychosis, peptic ulcer, glaucoma, cataract,
                diabetes mellitus, severe infections (including tuberculosis), infected neuropathic
                ulcers, hypertension and death. Minor adverse events were defined as moon face,
                dermatophyte fungal or yeast infections, acne and gastric pain requiring an antacid
                (in addition to the famotidine each individual was prescribed whilst on
                corticosteroids). Individuals were questioned about the symptoms of nocturia,
                polyuria and polydipsia as a method of screening for diabetes mellitus in addition
                to urinalysis being performed.</p>
            <p>Secondary outcomes measures were:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                    <p>change in the clinical severity score derived from the validated Clinical
                        Severity Scale <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Walker1">[17]</xref> at days 4, 29, 113 and 337. The Clinical Severity
                        Scale uses a composite score of skin signs and oedema, sensory and motor
                        nerve function<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Walker1">[17]</xref>. We had previously developed the scale and
                        demonstrated that it has a Cronbach's alpha of &gt;0.8 and an
                        Intra-Class Correlation coefficient of 0.994.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                    <p>change in clinical nerve function impairment determined using the validated
                        Clinical Severity Scale at days 4, 29, 113 and 337.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                    <p>time to the next steroid requiring reactional episode or acute nerve function
                        impairment.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                    <p>the amount of supplementary prednisolone required in addition to the reducing
                        16 week regimen.</p>
                </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>Peripheral nerve function was assessed clinically. Sensory testing (ST) was performed
                using two Semmes-Weinstein monofilaments (SWM) (Sorri-Bauru, Bauru, São
                Paulo, Brazil) at designated test sites on the hands and feet as previously reported
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Walker1">[17]</xref>. The
                sensation in the areas of skin supplied by the ulnar and median nerves was tested
                with 2 g and 10 g monofilaments. The area of skin supplied by the posterior tibial
                nerve was tested with the 10 g and 300 g monofilaments. Trigeminal nerve sensation
                was tested using cotton wool. Voluntary muscle testing (VMT) was assessed using the
                modified Medical Research Council grading of power <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Brain1">[18]</xref>. The facial nerve was tested by
                assessing forced eye closure. The median nerve was tested using resisted thumb
                abduction, the ulnar nerve by resisted little finger abduction and the radial nerve
                by resisted wrist extension. The lateral popliteal nerve was tested by resisted foot
                dorsiflexion. ST and VMT assessments were carried out by trained physio-technicians
                and if necessary repeated by the study physicians.</p>
            <p>Patients with deterioration in nerve function or skin signs were treated with further
                prednisolone. This was defined as a sustained deterioration (for a period of at
                least two weeks) of nerve function, the development of nerve pain unresponsive to
                analgesics, palpable swelling of skin patches or new erythematous and raised skin
                patches. Any decline in nerve function which the study doctors believed required
                immediate additional prednisolone was also regarded as deterioration. Individuals
                who experienced deterioration in skin and/or nerve function whilst receiving a dose
                of prednisolone less than 20 mg daily had the dose increased back to 20 mg and
                reduced by 5 mg every 14 days to zero. The exception to this was if they had a T1R
                involving a facial patch in which case the prednisolone was increased to 40 mg
                regardless of the dose of prednisolone the individual was taking. Individuals taking
                a dose of prednisolone greater than 20 mg had their dose increased to 40 mg and
                tapered by 5 mg every 14 days to zero.</p>
            <p>In order to have 80% power to show that MP was not associated with a
                significantly greater (α&lt;0.05) rate of major adverse effects it was
                calculated that the study would need 201 participants in each group based on a
                higher rate of 7%. Using this same assumption but with the TRIPOD data for
                all the Nepali participants (major adverse effect rate of 2.4%) then 64
                individuals would be needed to be enrolled in each arm.</p>
            <p>Eligible individuals were enrolled consecutively. Block randomisation in groups of
                four using a table of random numbers generated by Dr Peter Nicholls was used. A
                standard envelope system was used for allocation concealment. The envelopes were
                pre-packed in London by Dr Claire Watson who had no other involvement with the
                study. The participants were randomly allocated to the MP/prednisolone or the
                prednisolone alone arm and so had an equal chance of being in either arm of the
                study. The allocation procedure was decentralized and operated solely by the chief
                pharmacist at Anandaban Hospital who kept a separate record of the allocation. The
                pharmacist had no contact with the study participants during their inpatient
                stay.</p>
            <p>All study participants, physicians, ward staff and other assessors
                (physio-technicians) were blinded to the allocation. Only Dr Peter Nicholls had
                access to the study data and the randomisation code. The allocation code was
                revealed to the other researchers once recruitment, follow-up and data collection
                had been completed.</p>
            <p>The data were stored in an Access database and analysed using the Statistical Package
                for the Social Sciences (SPSS version 16 SPSS Inc., Chicago, Illinois). An intention
                to treat analysis was used for calculating the effects of treatment on individuals
                in each group.</p>
            <p>The trial was registered with Current Controlled Trials Ltd (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.controlled-trials.com" xlink:type="simple">www.controlled-trials.com</ext-link>) in accordance with the policy of the
                International Committee of Medical Journal Editors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Moher1">[1]</xref> and was assigned the unique
                identifier ISRCTN31894035. The protocol for the trial can be accessed as a
                supplementary file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0001041.s001">Protocol S1</xref> to this publication.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3">
            <title>Results</title>
            <p>Forty-two patients were enrolled into the trial between 7<sup>th</sup> December 2005
                and 31<sup>st</sup> December 2007. The final assessment and data entry was completed
                on 5<sup>th</sup> November 2008. The participants flow through the study is
                illustrated in the CONSORT flow diagram (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0001041-g001">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
            <fig id="pntd-0001041-g001" position="float">
                <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041.g001</object-id>
                <label>Figure 1</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>CONSORT flow diagram for the pilot study of individuals randomized to
                        either intravenous methylprednisolone and oral prednisolone or oral
                        prednisolone alone.</title>
                </caption>
                <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Thirty-three males and nine females were recruited. Twenty-two individuals were
                randomised to receive prednisolone only. There were no statistically significant
                differences between the groups with respect to gender, age, Ridley-Jopling
                classification, or treatment with MDT (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0001041-t001">Table 1</xref>). The two groups did not differ
                significantly in terms of the nature of the reaction, the type of NFI at baseline or
                the pattern of old (&gt; 6 months duration) NFI.</p>
            <table-wrap id="pntd-0001041-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
                    <title>Baseline characteristics of study participants in each arm.</title>
                </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pntd-0001041-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
                    <colgroup span="1">
                        <col align="left" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PREDNISOLONE (n = 22)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">METHYLPREDNISOLONE (n = 20)</td>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median Age [years (Range; min-max)]</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39 (19;35–54)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.5 (25;17–42)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (43;22–65)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.5 (48;16–64)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ridley-Jopling classification</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tuberculoid</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Borderline tuberculoid</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Borderline borderline</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Borderline lepromatous</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lepromatous leprosy</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reaction Type</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Skin Only</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Skin and Nerves</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nerves Only</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MDT Status</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Untreated</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">On treatment</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Treated</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table></alternatives></table-wrap>
            <p>Eight participants (19%) did not complete the full schedule of follow-up. Five
                were randomised to the prednisolone arm and three received MP. Efforts were made to
                get these individuals to attend by telephoning or writing to them but without
                success. Two of these individuals stopped attending whilst on corticosteroids.</p>
            <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0001041-t002">Table 2</xref> shows the number of
                individuals who experienced a particular adverse event. Twenty-three participants
                experienced at least one adverse event, twelve (54.5%) in the prednisolone
                arm and 11 (55%) in the MP arm. Seven individuals experienced more than one
                adverse event. There were no statistically significant differences in the number of
                individuals experiencing a given adverse event between the two groups of the
                study.</p>
            <table-wrap id="pntd-0001041-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
                    <title>Minor and major adverse events.</title>
                </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pntd-0001041-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
                    <colgroup span="1">
                        <col align="left" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Adverse Event</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prednisolone</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Methylprednisolone</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">chi square (Fisher's exact)</td>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Minor</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moon Face</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.123</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acne</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fungal infection</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.476</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gastric pain</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.414</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NPP</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weight gain</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Major</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Glaucoma</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Infected ulcers</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.476</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table></alternatives></table-wrap>
            <p>Two individuals (one from each arm of the study) experienced a major adverse event.
                One was diagnosed with glaucoma and the other with infected neuropathic ulcers. None
                of the participants developed hypertension, tuberculosis or diabetes mellitus. The
                risk ratio of having an adverse event (of any type; major or minor) given that the
                participant received MP was 1.0083 (95% CI: 0.5817 to 1.7480;
                p = 0.9764) compared to prednisolone.</p>
            <p>Individuals were most likely to experience an adverse event whilst taking the first
                course of corticosteroids between days 1 and 112. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0001041-g002">Figure 2</xref> is a Kaplan-Meier survival curve showing
                the cumulative “survival” probability (i.e. not having an adverse event)
                for individuals in each group. There was no significant difference between the two
                groups (Log Rank (Mantel-Cox) 0.945).</p>
            <fig id="pntd-0001041-g002" position="float">
                <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041.g002</object-id>
                <label>Figure 2</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Time to first adverse event.</title>
                    <p>(The vertical broken line is placed at day 113).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Four individuals had their first adverse event after the initial study intervention
                had been completed (post day 112). Two others had a new adverse event after the
                intervention period. Two individuals experienced an adverse event, weight gain and
                infected neuropathic ulcers respectively, whilst not taking corticosteroids.</p>
            <p>The total clinical severity scores, calculated using the validated scale, for each
                arm of the study at day 1 (enrolment) and days 4, 29,113 and 337 are shown using
                boxplots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0001041-g003">fig.3</xref>). There was a
                downward trend in the total clinical severity scores of both groups. There were no
                statistically significant differences between the prednisolone and MP groups at any
                time point.</p>
            <fig id="pntd-0001041-g003" position="float">
                <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041.g003</object-id>
                <label>Figure 3</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Total severity score at days 1, 4, 29, 113, 337 (Circles denote
                        individuals 1.5 times the interquartile range (IQR) outside the box and
                        asterisks denote individuals 3 times the IQR outside the box).</title>
                </caption>
                <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <p>There was no significant difference in the median sensory scores (corrected for
                impairment &gt;6 months) of individuals in the two groups at baseline. Both groups
                showed a downward trend in the sensory scores during treatment but there were no
                significant differences at any of the pre-specified time points. The Kaplan-Meier
                survival analyses of deterioration in sensory score during the study to days 29, 113
                and 337 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0001041-g004">fig.4</xref>) demonstrate that
                there is no difference between the groups at day 29 but at day 113 there was a
                significant difference in the probability of deterioration in sensation between
                individuals in the two arms of the study (p = 0.046). Patients
                in the prednisolone alone group were more likely to experience deterioration in
                sensation between day 30 and day 113. This effect is not maintained at the end of
                the study follow-up period at day 337. The motor scores of the two groups at
                baseline are not significantly different. They showed a downward trend during the
                course of the study. There are no significant differences between the scores of the
                group at any of the time points. There were no significant differences between the
                groups in the probability of an individual experiencing deterioration in motor
                function at days 29, 113 or 337.</p>
            <fig id="pntd-0001041-g004" position="float">
                <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041.g004</object-id>
                <label>Figure 4</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Time to deterioration of sensory function.</title>
                </caption>
                <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0001041-g005">Figure 5</xref> shows events when
                additional steroid was prescribed and censoring individuals who were unavailable for
                further assessment or who received prednisolone either inappropriately or for ENL.
                There was no significant difference in the probability of being prescribed
                additional prednisolone between the two groups (Log Rank (Mantel Cox)
                p = 0.126). The amount of additional prednisolone required by
                individuals randomised to either treatment group did not differ significantly. The
                mean amount of additional prednisolone prescribed during the study was 1252.5 mg
                (SD±1862.0) for the MP group and 1432.7 mg (SD±1245.9) for the
                prednisolone alone group (p = 0.718).</p>
            <fig id="pntd-0001041-g005" position="float">
                <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041.g005</object-id>
                <label>Figure 5</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Time to requiring first course of additional prednisolone.</title>
                </caption>
                <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Twenty individuals (47.6%) required additional prednisolone because they
                experienced a deterioration of nerve function (n = 11) or a
                recurrence of a T1R (n = 6) or both
                (n = 3). Two individuals received additional prednisolone
                inappropriately and two developed ENL requiring prednisolone. Five of the 20
                individuals (appropriately prescribed additional prednisolone for a trial
                indication) required prednisolone before day 112, the last day of the intervention
                period. The median time to requiring additional prednisolone for these individuals
                was 61 days (range = 14–105) after enrolment when
                individuals were receiving prednisolone 20 mg daily. The other 75% had
                finished the prednisolone before experiencing a deterioration requiring further
                treatment. The median number of days between finishing the study intervention (day
                112) and requiring additional prednisolone was 63 days
                (range = 2–224).</p>
            <p>Analysing the additional corticosteroid requirement by Ridley-Jopling classification
                fifty-two percent (12 of 23) of individuals with borderline tuberculoid (BT)
                leprosy, 67% (two of three) of individuals with borderline borderline (BB)
                leprosy, 38% (five of 13) of those with borderline lepromatous leprosy (LL)
                and 50% (one of two) of lepromatous leprosy patients required additional
                prednisolone for a trial indication (those with ENL were excluded). Two of the BT
                patients had positive slit-skin smears. The median time from enrolment to the
                deterioration requiring additional prednisolone was 152 days for BT patients, 138
                days for BB patients, 125 days for BL patients and 313 days for those with LL. There
                were no significant differences in the proportion of individuals with a particular
                Ridley Jopling classification or the time to requiring additional prednisolone.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>In this small, study the occurrence and timing of minor and major adverse events did
                not differ significantly between the prednisolone and the MP treated groups. The
                study was underpowered and limited the ability to detect significant differences of
                less than 30% between the groups. Twenty-one (50%) individuals
                experienced at least one minor adverse event and two (4.8%) a major adverse
                outcome. In the TRIPOD trials 8.4% (14/167) of the prednisolone treated
                Nepali cohorts experienced a minor adverse event<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Richardus2">[16]</xref>. This was not significantly
                different from the placebo treated group. The individuals in these groups were
                treated with either 1.96 g or 2.52 g of prednisolone depending on which of the three
                trials they were enrolled into.</p>
            <p>The two major adverse events that occurred during the study were glaucoma and
                infected neuropathic ulcers but these were probably not due to the trial
                medications. One individual developed glaucoma at day 305. He developed ENL at day
                111. ENL like corticosteroid therapy is a recognised cause of secondary glaucoma. He
                required continuous oral prednisolone (receiving a total additional dose of 2.87 g
                of prednisolone between days 111 and 305) despite treatment of his ENL with high
                dose (300 mg daily) clofazimine. The majority of individuals who develop ENL require
                long term treatment and many become corticosteroid dependent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Pocaterra1">[19]</xref>. There were no cases of
                glaucoma in any of the TRIPOD participants. Infected neuropathic ulcers affected one
                individual treated with MP. This occurred 58 days after this man completed the trial
                intervention. Two individuals in the TRIPOD studies (one from the prednisolone
                treated group) developed infected ulcers. It is not reported whether the
                prednisolone treated person was taking the drug at the time the infection was
                diagnosed.</p>
            <p>The symptoms of nocturia, polyuria and polydipsia were reported by four (9.5%)
                of individuals. The two individuals who had glycosuria did not complain of these
                symptoms. Their glycosuria was not persistent and therefore not considered to be
                clinically significant. The two individuals were both receiving additional
                prednisolone at the time but neither had received MP. There were no individuals in
                the study diagnosed with diabetes mellitus. The TRIPOD 1 study reported one
                individual from the prednisolone treated group who developed glycosuria. This was
                considered a major adverse event in that study but the authors did not comment
                whether this patient was diagnosed with diabetes mellitus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Smith1">[20]</xref>. Three individuals in the
                steroid treated groups of the three TRIPOD studies developed diabetes mellitus
                compared with one in the placebo groups but this difference was not significant
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Richardus2">[16]</xref>.</p>
            <p>The size of the study limited our ability to detect rare adverse events however a
                much higher rate of acne and moon face was recorded than the TRIPOD studies. Another
                factor that might have reduced our estimation of adverse events is the duration of
                follow-up which may have been too short, however most studies have assumed that
                adverse events will occur during the treatment phase predominantly. We were also
                unable to examine the effect of our interventions on bone density which may be
                significantly affected by corticosteroid therapy in the doses and durations commonly
                used to manage leprosy T1R and NFI. The findings would support the view that MP, in
                the doses used in the study, is safe.</p>
            <p>MP did not appear to have a larger therapeutic effect than prednisolone alone on the
                symptoms and signs of leprosy T1Rs and NFI in this study. The use of a validated
                scale to measure leprosy T1Rs and NFI allows the comparison of the two groups in
                this study. There were no significant differences in the total severity score or the
                sensory or motor scores between the prednisolone and MP treated groups at any of the
                pre-defined time points. However there was a trend towards improvement in sensory
                and motor scores during the study. Participants in the prednisolone treated group
                were significantly more likely to have experienced deterioration in sensory function
                than the MP treated group by the end of the intervention (day 113). However this
                difference was not sustained to the end of the study. This effect may have occurred
                by chance as it was not reproduced in the skin or in motor function. The number of
                participants contributing to all of the survival analyses towards the end of the
                study is small and the results therefore less reliable. This phenomenon of
                deterioration after stopping corticosteroids is similar to the results of the TRIPOD
                1 study of prednisolone given to patients as prophylaxis to prevent the occurrence
                of reactions and NFI. It demonstrated a protective effect of prednisolone compared
                with placebo during the 16 weeks of treatment which was lost by 48 weeks. The higher
                dose may have a greater effect whilst an individual is receiving corticosteroids but
                not once they are no longer taking the drug.</p>
            <p>Forty-five per cent of the MP group and 50% of the prednisolone alone group
                were prescribed additional prednisolone. Of the 20 individuals who required
                additional prednisolone 12 (60%) did not do so until at least 28 days after
                completing the trial intervention. The clinical nature of the deterioration (skin or
                nerves or both) did not differ significantly between those who experienced it whilst
                receiving the study intervention and those who experienced deterioration after
                completing it (χ<sup>2</sup> = 0.292). The delay in
                deterioration in the majority of individuals requiring additional prednisolone is
                similar to that seen in the TRIPOD 1 study<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Smith1">[20]</xref>.</p>
            <p>After the start of this trial data suggesting that more prolonged courses of
                prednisolone may be more effective in treating T1Rs were published. The requirement
                for extra prednisolone was used as the outcome measure in the multi-centre double
                blind randomised controlled trial of three different prednisolone regimens conducted
                in India <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Rao1">[21]</xref>. The
                proportion of individuals requiring additional prednisolone in the three groups was
                24%, 31% and 46% respectively. Individuals who received
                prednisolone for 20 weeks were significantly less likely to require additional
                steroid than those treated for 12. However this does not necessarily reflect
                clinical improvement. The decision to use additional prednisolone was left to the
                individual clinician's judgement at each of the six centres. It is not clear
                how consistency was ensured between individual physicians or at different stages of
                the trial. The protocol of the MP study was stringent in treating NFI.
                “Mild” deterioration in NFI and NFI of short duration were both treated.
                Any sustained (as little as one week) deterioration in monofilament testing at even
                a single test site was an indication for additional prednisolone and so a lower
                threshold for defining deterioration is likely to have been employed in the current
                study. This may in part account for the high proportion of individuals who received
                additional prednisolone. It is likely that some of the change labelled as
                deterioration was due to test response variability. In the TRIPOD 2 cohort
                27% of prednisolone treated individuals with mild sensory impairment
                experienced deterioration necessitating additional prednisolone. A group with mild
                isolated sensory impairment would be expected to require less additional
                prednisolone than a group that included severe nerve impairment both sensory and
                motor and marked skin involvement.</p>
            <p>The results of this small study should be interpreted with caution but it would
                appear that given the available data MP does not result in an increase in the number
                or severity of adverse events in individuals with leprosy in Nepal. However close
                detailed adverse event recording would still be required in any future studies of MP
                in this setting. The establishment of registries of corticosteroid treated patients
                at specialised centres could facilitate the collection of reliable adverse event
                data without the need to resort to more costly randomised controlled trials.</p>
            <p>The clinical outcome of patients in the two arms of this study was not significantly
                different in terms of the validated clinical severity scale. The MP treated group
                had significantly less deterioration in sensory function during the 112 days of
                corticosteroid therapy but this was not maintained to the end of the 337 day
                follow-up period. This may be a reflection of the small numbers in the study,
                particularly towards the end of follow-up. A much larger study would be required to
                examine this potential effect further. However given the high proportion of
                individuals (who received MP) requiring additional prednisolone and the data
                published by Rao and colleagues<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Rao1">[21]</xref> we do not think further clinical trials of high dose IV
                MP are warranted at present. Any future studies must also take into account the
                greater cost of giving intravenous treatment and its acceptability to patients.</p>
            <p>This study has highlighted that corticosteroid treatment for T1R and NFI is
                sub-optimal even when given in large doses for 16 weeks. The majority of patients
                who experienced a “re-reaction” required additional prednisolone after
                the 16 week corticosteroid intervention had ended. It adds further support to the
                argument that treatment should be given for longer durations. Investigating risk
                factors for requiring additional prednisolone and the differences between those who
                have deterioration in symptoms whilst taking corticosteroids and those whose
                deterioration occurs later (or not at all) might enable clinicians to identify those
                individuals who might benefit from prolonged corticosteroid treatment at the outset.
                At present there is convincing evidence for corticosteroid regimes of at least 20
                weeks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Rao1">[21]</xref> but some
                would argue for 24 weeks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Walker2">[22]</xref> and others even longer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001041-Naafs1">[23]</xref>. The development of more
                prolonged treatment protocols would require further monitoring of adverse events and
                in particular the long term sequelae of corticosteroid therapy. However studies with
                adequate power using improvement in nerve function as the primary outcome of the
                effect of corticosteroids and other agents need to be conducted.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s5">
            <title>Supporting Information</title>
            <supplementary-material id="pntd.0001041.s001" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041.s001" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Protocol S1</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>(0.16 MB DOC)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pntd.0001041.s002" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0001041.s002" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Checklist S1</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Consort checklist</p>
                    <p>(0.22 MB DOC)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <p>We would like to thank the participants who gave up their time to be enrolled in this
                study. We are grateful to the staff of Anandaban Hospital for all their hard work.
                In particular Drs Tim and Julie Lewis, Ram Kumar Maharjan, Bijay Pandey, Mahesh
                Shah, Ravi Kumar Singh, Sudhir Suman KC and Min Bahadur Thapa who helped with data
                collection. The physiotechnicians: Ram Babu Bista, Arjun Karki, Jaganath Maharjan
                and Krishna Godar Thapa who performed the bulk of the motor and sensory
                examinations. Mohan Khadka, the pharmacist, who mixed the study infusions and
                dispensed the prednisolone.</p>
            <p>The trial monitors were Dr P S S Sundar Rao and Dr K V Krishna Moorthy and we thank
                them for their support.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Moher1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Moher</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Schulz</surname>
                            <given-names>KF</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Altman</surname>
                            <given-names>DG</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>The CONSORT statement: revised recommendations for improving the
                        quality of reports of parallel-group randomised trials.</article-title>
                    <source>Lancet</source>
                    <volume>357</volume>
                    <fpage>1191</fpage>
                    <lpage>1194</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Lockwood1">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lockwood</surname>
                            <given-names>DNJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Leprosy.</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Burns</surname>
                            <given-names>DA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Breathnach</surname>
                            <given-names>SM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Cox</surname>
                            <given-names>NH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Griffiths</surname>
                            <given-names>CEM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <source>Rook's Textbook of Dermatology 7th ed</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing</publisher-name>
                    <fpage>29.21</fpage>
                    <lpage>29.21</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-WHO1">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>WHO</surname>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>Global leprosy situation, 2009.</article-title>
                    <source>Wkly Epidemiol Rec</source>
                    <volume>84</volume>
                    <fpage>333</fpage>
                    <lpage>340</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Ranque1">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ranque</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nguyen</surname>
                            <given-names>VT</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Vu</surname>
                            <given-names>HT</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nguyen</surname>
                            <given-names>TH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nguyen</surname>
                            <given-names>NB</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Age is an important risk factor for onset and sequelae of
                        reversal reactions in Vietnamese patients with leprosy.</article-title>
                    <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
                    <volume>44</volume>
                    <fpage>33</fpage>
                    <lpage>40</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Marlowe1">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Marlowe</surname>
                            <given-names>SN</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hawksworth</surname>
                            <given-names>RA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Butlin</surname>
                            <given-names>CR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nicholls</surname>
                            <given-names>PG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lockwood</surname>
                            <given-names>DN</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Clinical outcomes in a randomized controlled study comparing
                        azathioprine and prednisolone versus prednisolone alone in the treatment of
                        severe leprosy type 1 reactions in Nepal.</article-title>
                    <source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source>
                    <volume>98</volume>
                    <fpage>602</fpage>
                    <lpage>609</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Richardus1">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Richardus</surname>
                            <given-names>JH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Withington</surname>
                            <given-names>SG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Anderson</surname>
                            <given-names>AM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Croft</surname>
                            <given-names>RP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nicholls</surname>
                            <given-names>PG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Treatment with corticosteroids of long-standing nerve function
                        impairment in leprosy: a randomized controlled trial (TRIPOD
                        3).</article-title>
                    <source>Lepr Rev</source>
                    <volume>74</volume>
                    <fpage>311</fpage>
                    <lpage>318</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-vanBrakel1">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>van Brakel</surname>
                            <given-names>WH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Anderson</surname>
                            <given-names>AM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Withington</surname>
                            <given-names>SG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Croft</surname>
                            <given-names>RP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nicholls</surname>
                            <given-names>PG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>The prognostic importance of detecting mild sensory impairment in
                        leprosy: a randomized controlled trial (TRIPOD 2).</article-title>
                    <source>Lepr Rev</source>
                    <volume>74</volume>
                    <fpage>300</fpage>
                    <lpage>310</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Little1">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Little</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Khanolkar-Young</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Coulthart</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Suneetha</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lockwood</surname>
                            <given-names>DN</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Immunohistochemical analysis of cellular infiltrate and gamma
                        interferon, interleukin-12, and inducible nitric oxide synthase expression
                        in leprosy type 1 (reversal) reactions before and during prednisolone
                        treatment.</article-title>
                    <source>Infect Immun</source>
                    <volume>69</volume>
                    <fpage>3413</fpage>
                    <lpage>3417</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-KhanolkarYoung1">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Khanolkar-Young</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Rayment</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Brickell</surname>
                            <given-names>PM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Katz</surname>
                            <given-names>DR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Vinayakumar</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1995</year>
                    <article-title>Tumour necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-alpha) synthesis is associated
                        with the skin and peripheral nerve pathology of leprosy reversal
                        reactions.</article-title>
                    <source>Clin Exp Immunol</source>
                    <volume>99</volume>
                    <fpage>196</fpage>
                    <lpage>202</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Weusten1">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Weusten</surname>
                            <given-names>BL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Jacobs</surname>
                            <given-names>JW</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bijlsma</surname>
                            <given-names>JW</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1993</year>
                    <article-title>Corticosteroid pulse therapy in active rheumatoid
                        arthritis.</article-title>
                    <source>Semin Arthritis Rheum</source>
                    <volume>23</volume>
                    <fpage>183</fpage>
                    <lpage>192</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Filippini1">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Filippini</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Brusaferri</surname>
                            <given-names>F</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sibley</surname>
                            <given-names>WA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Citterio</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ciucci</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>Corticosteroids or ACTH for acute exacerbations in multiple
                        sclerosis.</article-title>
                    <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>
                    <fpage>CD001331</fpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Wandinger1">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wandinger</surname>
                            <given-names>KP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wessel</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Trillenberg</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Heindl</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kirchner</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <article-title>Effect of high-dose methylprednisolone administration on immune
                        functions in multiple sclerosis patients.</article-title>
                    <source>Acta Neurol Scand</source>
                    <volume>97</volume>
                    <fpage>359</fpage>
                    <lpage>365</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Youssef1">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Youssef</surname>
                            <given-names>PP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Haynes</surname>
                            <given-names>DR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Triantafillou</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Parker</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gamble</surname>
                            <given-names>JR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1997</year>
                    <article-title>Effects of pulse methylprednisolone on inflammatory mediators in
                        peripheral blood, synovial fluid, and synovial membrane in rheumatoid
                        arthritis.</article-title>
                    <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>
                    <volume>40</volume>
                    <fpage>1400</fpage>
                    <lpage>1408</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Hirano1">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hirano</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Tsuboi</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Homma</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Oka</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Takekoshi</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>Comparative study of lymphocyte-suppressive potency between
                        prednisolone and methylprednisolone in rheumatoid arthritis.</article-title>
                    <source>Immunopharmacology</source>
                    <volume>49</volume>
                    <fpage>411</fpage>
                    <lpage>417</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Ridley1">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ridley</surname>
                            <given-names>DS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Jopling</surname>
                            <given-names>WH</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1966</year>
                    <article-title>Classification of Leprosy according to immunity.</article-title>
                    <source>Int J Lepr Other Mycobact Dis</source>
                    <volume>34</volume>
                    <fpage>255</fpage>
                    <lpage>273</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Richardus2">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Richardus</surname>
                            <given-names>JH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Withington</surname>
                            <given-names>SG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Anderson</surname>
                            <given-names>AM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Croft</surname>
                            <given-names>RP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nicholls</surname>
                            <given-names>PG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Adverse events of standardized regimens of corticosteroids for
                        prophylaxis and treatment of nerve function impairment in leprosy: results
                        from the ‘TRIPOD' trials.</article-title>
                    <source>Lepr Rev</source>
                    <volume>74</volume>
                    <fpage>319</fpage>
                    <lpage>327</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Walker1">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Walker</surname>
                            <given-names>SL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nicholls</surname>
                            <given-names>PG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Butlin</surname>
                            <given-names>CR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nery</surname>
                            <given-names>JA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Roy</surname>
                            <given-names>HK</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Development and validation of a severity scale for leprosy type 1
                        reactions.</article-title>
                    <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>
                    <volume>2</volume>
                    <fpage>e351</fpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Brain1">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Brain</surname>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>Aids to the examination of the peripheral nervous
                        system.</article-title>
                    <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>W.B. Saunders</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Pocaterra1">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pocaterra</surname>
                            <given-names>L</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Jain</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Reddy</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Muzaffarullah</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Torres</surname>
                            <given-names>O</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Clinical course of erythema nodosum leprosum: an 11-year cohort
                        study in Hyderabad, India.</article-title>
                    <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
                    <volume>74</volume>
                    <fpage>868</fpage>
                    <lpage>879</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Smith1">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Smith</surname>
                            <given-names>WC</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Anderson</surname>
                            <given-names>AM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Withington</surname>
                            <given-names>SG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>van Brakel</surname>
                            <given-names>WH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Croft</surname>
                            <given-names>RP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Steroid prophylaxis for prevention of nerve function impairment
                        in leprosy: randomised placebo controlled trial (TRIPOD 1).</article-title>
                    <source>BMJ</source>
                    <volume>328</volume>
                    <fpage>1459</fpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Rao1">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Rao</surname>
                            <given-names>PS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sugamaran</surname>
                            <given-names>DS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Richard</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Smith</surname>
                            <given-names>WC</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Multi-centre, double blind, randomized trial of three steroid
                        regimens in the treatment of type-1 reactions in leprosy.</article-title>
                    <source>Lepr Rev</source>
                    <volume>77</volume>
                    <fpage>25</fpage>
                    <lpage>33</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Walker2">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Walker</surname>
                            <given-names>SL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lockwood</surname>
                            <given-names>DN</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Leprosy type 1 (reversal) reactions and their
                        management.</article-title>
                    <source>Lepr Rev</source>
                    <volume>79</volume>
                    <fpage>372</fpage>
                    <lpage>386</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pntd.0001041-Naafs1">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Naafs</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Treatment duration of reversal reaction: a reappraisal. Back to
                        the past.</article-title>
                    <source>Lepr Rev</source>
                    <volume>74</volume>
                    <fpage>328</fpage>
                    <lpage>336</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
        
    </back>
</article>