<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-43994</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Glowing Seashells: Diversity of Fossilized Coloration Patterns on Coral Reef-Associated Cone Snail (Gastropoda: Conidae) Shells from the Neogene of the Dominican Republic</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Fossilized Coloration Patterns on Dominican Cone Snail Shells</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Hendricks</surname>
<given-names>Jonathan R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><addr-line>Department of Geology, San José State University, California, United States of America and Paleontological Research Institution, Ithaca, New York, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Vermeij</surname>
<given-names>Geerat J.</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of California, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The author has declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JRH. Performed the experiments: JRH. Analyzed the data: JRH. Wrote the paper: JRH.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">jonathan.hendricks@sjsu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>1</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<elocation-id>e0120924</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>30</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2014</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>22</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Jonathan R. Hendricks</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924" xlink:type="simple"/>
<abstract>
<p>The biology of modern Conidae (cone snails)—which includes the hyperdiverse genus <italic>Conus</italic>—has been intensively studied, but the fossil record of the clade remains poorly understood, particularly within an evolutionary framework. Here, ultraviolet light is used to reveal and characterize the original shell coloration patterns of 28 species of cone snails from three Neogene coral reef-associated deposits from the Cibao Valley, northern Dominican Republic. These fossils come from the upper Miocene Cercado Fm. and lower Pliocene Gurabo Fm., and range in age from about 6.6-4.8 Ma. Comparison of the revealed coloration patterns with those of extant species allow the taxa to be assigned to three genera of cone snails (<italic>Profundiconus</italic>, <italic>Conasprella</italic>, and <italic>Conus</italic>) and at least nine subgenera. Thirteen members of these phylogenetically diverse reef faunas are described as new species. These include: <italic>Profundiconus</italic>? <italic>hennigi</italic>, <italic>Conasprella (Ximeniconus) ageri</italic>, <italic>Conus anningae</italic>, <italic>Conus lyelli</italic>, <italic>Conus (Atlanticonus</italic>?) <italic>franklinae</italic>, <italic>Conus (Stephanoconus) gouldi</italic>, <italic>Conus (Stephanoconus) bellacoensis</italic>, <italic>Conus (Ductoconus) cashi</italic>, <italic>Conus (Dauciconus) garrisoni</italic>, <italic>Conus (Dauciconus</italic>?) <italic>zambaensis</italic>, <italic>Conus (Spuriconus</italic>?) <italic>kaesleri</italic>, <italic>Conus (Spuriconus</italic>?) <italic>lombardii</italic>, <italic>and Conus (Lautoconus</italic>?) <italic>carlottae</italic>. Each of the three reef deposits contain a minimum of 14–16 cone snail species, levels of diversity that are similar to modern Indo-Pacific reef systems. Finally, most of the 28 species can be assigned to modern clades and thus have important implications for understanding the biogeographic and temporal histories of these clades in tropical America.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>A California State University Research Fund grant (no grant number or website is available) supported travel to the Natural History Museum, London and and Naturhistorisches Museum Basel in 2009. The funder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. Otherwise, the author received no specific funding for this work.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="31"/>
<table-count count="2"/>
<page-count count="59"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>Unaltered, original digital images of specimens photographed under UV light and figured herein are freely available for inspection and download at DataDryad.org (doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.n36n6" xlink:type="simple">10.5061/dryad.n36n6</ext-link>). These include uncompressed raw .CR2 (Canon) and .NEF (Nikon) files, as well as corresponding .JPEG files; each of the raw files retains information about the camera settings (e.g., F numbers and exposure times) used to produce the photograph.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Cone snails—which include three small genera, <italic>Profundiconus</italic>, <italic>Californiconus</italic>, and <italic>Conasprella</italic>, and one large genus, <italic>Conus</italic>—are one of the most well-studied and species-rich clades of marine animals, and are represented by over 700 extant species [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The diverse and often intricate shell coloration patterns of cone snails (e.g., <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>), which all belong to the venomous neogastropod family Conidae [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], have caused them to be coveted by shell collectors for centuries, and these patterns have even been the subjects of studies by computer modelers (e.g., [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]). Besides being appealing to look at, the coloration patterns of cone snail shells are taxonomically useful for distinguishing extant species. While species exhibit intraspecific variation in the finer details of their coloration patterns (e.g., [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]), the major elements that make up a given pattern—for example, presence of spiral rows of dots (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A,B</xref>) or unpigmented tents (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1G,H</xref>)—do not tend to vary substantially within species. Furthermore, cone snail shell coloration patterns seem to contain phylogenetic signal because closely related species often show subtle variations on the same general themes of patterning (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Variation in shell coloration patterns between pairs of closely related cone snail species.</title>
<p>Members of selected pairs belong to the same subgenus (based on phylogeny and classification of Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]). (A) <italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Ximeniconus</italic>) <italic>mahogani</italic> (CASIZ 184267); (B) <italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Ximeniconus</italic>) <italic>ximenes</italic> (CASIZ 184268); (C) <italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Rhizoconus</italic>) <italic>capitaneus</italic> (CASIZ 178062); (D) <italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Rhizoconus</italic>) <italic>miles</italic> (CASIZ 178070); (E) <italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>archon</italic> (UF 26040); (F) <italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>mappa</italic> (UF 238779); (G) <italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Darioconus</italic>) <italic>auricomus</italic> (CASIZ 178034); (H) <italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Darioconus</italic>) <italic>episcopatus</italic> (CASIZ 180453). All scale bars are 1 cm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>In addition to being remarkably diverse today, cone snails have a substantial fossil record that extends back to the early Eocene [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Over 1,000 species have been described from the fossil record [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], though many of these are likely synonymous (e.g., [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]). This is at least in part because cone snail species are relatively conservative in shell morphology and fossils seemingly lack the rich suite of coloration patterns that are often helpful for distinguishing extant species. In the 1960’s, however, Axel Olsson [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] discovered that original coloration patterns—if not the actual colors themselves—sometimes become visible when fossil shells are illuminated with ultraviolet (UV) light, which causes formerly pigmented regions of the shell to fluoresce (also see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]). Many authors have employed this approach as an aid for characterizing Cenozoic mollusk fossils (e.g., [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]), including cone snails (e.g., [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]). Once a specimen has been photographed under UV light, it is possible to use photoediting software to reconstruct the original shell coloration pattern. This is done by creating a reversed, negative image, which causes bright, fluorescing markings to become darkened, corresponding with regions that were once pigmented (e.g., <xref rid="pone.0120924.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>; also see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]).</p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Examples of ancient coloration patterns revealed by UV light.</title>
<p>Top row: three fossil shells (PRI 66199, PRI 66166, and PRI 66158) from the Neogene of the Dominican Republic photographed under regular light; all scale bars are 1 cm. Middle row: the same specimens photographed under longwave UV light. Bottom row: reversed images that show how fluorescing regions correspond to parts of the shell that were once darkly pigmented.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>While the use of UV light to reveal ancient shell coloration patterns has proved to be a useful technique for understanding the systematics of some fossil mollusks, we still do not have a clear understanding of exactly what compounds are responsible for pigmentation in modern shells [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], much less what matter is actually fluorescing in the fossil shells. Hedegaard et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] recently used resonance Raman microspectrometry to study the shell pigments of a variety of mollusks—including the cone snail <italic>Conus marmoreus</italic>—and demonstrated that “[t]he colour of a given shell is possibly due to several compounds, at least one of which is often a polyene” (p. 161). These authors cautioned, however, that “there is no trivial relationship between colour, pigment and taxon” (p. 157). Clearly much more work needs to be done to better understand the compounds responsible for shell coloration.</p>
<p>That said, it seems that oxidation—caused either naturally by exposure of shells to sunlight over prolonged periods of time, or artificially by soaking in bleach for several days—plays a role in causing formerly pigmented regions of fossil shells to fluoresce under UV light [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], though the reason is not currently understood. A fossil specimen of <italic>Conus humerosus</italic> Pilsbry, 1921 (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) provides a useful demonstration of the relationship between pigmented parts of the shell and fluorescence induced by UV light. Under regular light (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref>), the right side of the ventral surface of the last whorl shows five spiral rows of orange-colored, square-shaped spots; these are not visible on the left side. Under UV light (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3B</xref>), however, the same spiral rows of spots fluoresce, becoming visible on the left side (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3C</xref> shows a reversed version of <xref rid="pone.0120924.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3B</xref>). This implies that prior to collection, the right side of the specimen remained buried in the sediment, while the left side was exposed to the light of the sun and consequently oxidized. It should be noted that most fossil cone snail shells show little or no evidence of their original coloration patterns under regular light; <italic>Conus humerosus</italic> is one of the few known species that typically does, suggesting that its shell was heavily pigmented in life.</p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Correspondence between oxidation of the shell, fluorescence under UV light, and effects of digitally reversing the image of the fluorescing shell using photoediting software.</title>
<p>Shell is a specimen of <italic>Conus humerosus</italic> (PRI 67550); scale bar is 1 cm. See text for explanation.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>UV light is used here to reveal and characterize the great diversity of shell coloration patterns exhibited by fossil cone snails from three Neogene-aged, coral reef-associated assemblages from the Cibao Valley of the northern Dominican Republic (DR), the geology and paleontology of which has been intensively studied (e.g., [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]). These three assemblages were selected for their diversity of species and quality of preserved coloration patterns, which permit 13 new species to be recognized and described. The coloration patterns of 15 previously described species are also characterized here, but comprehensive taxonomic treatments (including complete re-descriptions) of these will be published in a future work. Finally, the preserved coloration patterns documented here allow many of the newly and previously studied species to be assigned to modern clades, providing insight on the phylogenetic and biogeographic history of cone snails in tropical America.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Collection Localities</title>
<p>The study specimens were collected in the 1970’s by Harold and Emily Vokes of Tulane University (TU) and are from three TU collecting stations—TU 1422, TU 1354, and TU 1215—that were characterized by E. Vokes [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] as "true [coral] reef localities" (p. 16). This is true for TU 1422 and TU 1354, but see remarks below for TU 1215, which may represent a mixed assemblage.</p>
<p>The first locality, TU 1422, is located at Arroyo Bellaco, “which is a tributary of Río Cana from the east, [a] coral reef that is exposed for approximately 1 km below the ford at Las Caobas Adentro, 3 km southwest of Las Caobas” ([<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], p. 67). Klaus and Budd [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] intensively studied the coral reef at this locality, which was described by Vokes [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] as “the most spectacular reef of all” (p. 16). Based on the map of Klaus and Budd ([<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>), the east end of the locality is at ca. 19.483065°, -71.246228° and the west end at 19.485386°, -71.250524° (this locality was georeferenced using Google Earth, as were TU 1354 and TU 1215). TU 1422 is positioned in the upper Miocene Cercado Fm. and thus formed sometime between 6.0–6.6 Ma [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Klaus and Budd [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] reported 35 coral species from this locality, five of which are extant.</p>
<p>Locality 1354 is located along “Cañada de Zamba, a tributary on the west side of the Río Cana, approximately 2.5 km east of the village of Zamba, which is 7 km north of Cruz de Santiago (Santiago Rodriguez), on road to Guayubin; or 4.5 km (airline) below the ford at Caimito” ([<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], p. 66). The boundaries of the locality are shown in Saunders et al. ([<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], text-<xref rid="pone.0120924.g015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 15</xref>); the east end of the locality is at ca. 19.542518°, -71.300043° and the west end at 19.540455°, -71.303286°. According to Waller [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], TU 1354 is positioned in the lower Pliocene Gurabo Fm. at about 335–345 m in the section of Saunders et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Based on the age-depth model of McNeill et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], this locality is ca. 4.9 Ma. Nearly 60 coral species have been reported from NMB localities equivalent to TU 1354 (based on data available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nmita.geology.uiowa.edu" xlink:type="simple">http://nmita.geology.uiowa.edu</ext-link>). Waller ([<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], p. 124) characterized the paleoenvironment of TU 1354 as “apparently a shallow but clear-water phase of the Gurabo with calcareous silts and corals.”</p>
<p>Finally, locality TU 1215 is exposed at bluffs on both sides of Río Gurabo, “from the ford on Los Quemados-Sabaneta road, upstream to approximately 1 km above the ford” ([<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], p. 64). The boundaries of the locality are shown in Sanders et al. ([<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], text-<xref rid="pone.0120924.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>); the north end of the locality is at ca. 19.506678°, -71.182946°, and the south end at 19.498825°, -71.179809°. According to Waller [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], TU 1215 is positioned in the lower Pliocene Gurabo Fm., between about 275–384 m in the section of Saunders et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. This is a large collecting locality and—according to the Río Gurabo age-depth model of McNeill et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]—ranges from ca. 4.8–5.4 Ma. Over 60 coral species have been reported from NMB localities equivalent to TU 1215 (based on data available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nmita.geology.uiowa.edu" xlink:type="simple">http://nmita.geology.uiowa.edu</ext-link>). There is debate about whether the corals are preserved <italic>in situ</italic>, as suggested by Vokes [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], or if they “tumbled downslope into fine sediments” (Waller [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], p. 29). Based on the fauna of pectinids at TU 1215, Waller [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] argued that the locality likely represents water depths of around 50 m or more. Given this, it is possible that the cone snail fauna at this locality represents more than one paleoenvironmental setting (deeper water species with transported reef-associated species) and—given the ca. 0.6 My duration of the locality—potentially taxa that did not co-exist in time.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Museum Collections</title>
<p>All of the 359 specimens reported on here from TU stations 1215, 1354, and 1422 are reposted at the Paleontological Research Institution (PRI) in Ithaca, New York and listed in <xref rid="pone.0120924.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>. Additional specimens—figured and/or referred to—are from the: Invertebrate Paleontology Collection at the Academy of Natural Sciences of Drexel University (ANSP) in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; Department of Invertebrate Zoology and Geology, California Academy of Sciences (CASIZ) in San Francisco; Division of Invertebrate Zoology, Florida Museum of Natural History at the University of Florida (UF) in Gainesville; Fossil Invertebrate Collections, Natural History Museum, London (NHMUK PI); and Geosciences Collection, Naturhistorisches Museum Basel (NMB), Switzerland. As other workers collected all of the fossil specimens considered here several decades ago, no permits were required for the described study, which complied with all relevant regulations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Specimen Preparation</title>
<p>Because the specimens come from unconsolidated deposits, removal from rock matrix was not necessary. All but the most fragile specimens were gently scrubbed under water to remove attached sand and silt particles and were then soaked overnight in a solution of diluted (50%) Clorox bleach. The shells were then rinsed again in water and allowed to dry. Next, the shells were inspected for preserved coloration patterns using a Raytech LS-7CB UV lamp in a dark room. Most of the shells studied show no indication of their coloration patterns under regular light, but approximately 60% showed well-preserved evidence of their ancient coloration patterns when viewed under UV light. A majority of the specimens exhibiting fluorescing coloration patterns were selected for digital photography.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Digital Photography and Image Processing</title>
<p>Most specimens were photographed using either a Canon 50D or Nikon 7100D digital camera attached to a copy stand. Black sand was used as a mounting medium in order to ensure that specimens were photographed in standardized positions (most often as views of the ventral or dorsal surface, with the axis of coiling oriented perpendicular to the optical axis of the camera lens; in apical views, the axis of coiling is parallel to the optical axis of the lens). Two Raytech LS-7CB lamps were used for UV photography; they were set to emit longwave UV light (365 nm) and were positioned on either side of the specimen being photographed. In order to block out background light during UV photography, photographs were either taken in a dark room, or a large box was used to cover the entire photography apparatus. Figures were prepared using Adobe Photoshop CS6. Adjustments were made to the white balance and levels of individual images, and some images were also treated using the auto tone, auto contrast, and/or auto color functions of Photoshop. Images of most specimens photographed under UV light were digitally reversed (using Photoshop’s invert function) to reconstruct shell coloration patterns (see above). Importantly, these reversed images do not show the actual shell colors of the animal when it was alive. Showing these reversed images in color (as opposed to grayscale) is useful, however, because differences in color—especially between different elements of pigmentation—on the same shell may correspond with variability in the underlying organic molecules that are fluorescing under UV light and/or the taphonomic (i.e., postmortem) history of the individual specimen. Unaltered, original digital images of specimens photographed under UV light and figured herein are freely available for inspection and download at DataDryad.org (doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.n36n6" xlink:type="simple">10.5061/dryad.n36n6</ext-link>). These include uncompressed raw .CR2 (Canon) and .NEF (Nikon) files, as well as corresponding .JPEG files; each of the raw files retains information about the camera settings (e.g., F numbers and exposure times) used to produce the photograph.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Recognition, Characterization, and Treatment of Species</title>
<p>The taxonomic monographs of Röckel et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] have quantitatively and qualitatively demonstrated the ranges of variability that extant cone snail species exhibit in the different features of their shells and thus serve as useful benchmarks for differentiating intra- from interspecific variation in fossil species, which is always a challenge in paleontology [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Although morphological features of the shell may not allow recognition of cryptic species of cone snails [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], all attempts were made here to circumscribe species in a manner consistent with the treatments of Röckel et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], which accepted substantial amounts of variability in certain aspects of shell morphology (e.g., shape and minor details of coloration patterning). These authors defined species broadly, resulting in many previously described forms—many based on a very small number of specimens—being synonymized. This work follows such a non-typological approach to the circumscription of cone snail species (also see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]).</p>
<p>Prior to beginning this project, all available type specimens of previously described species from the Neogene of the Dominican Republic were observed in person and photographed. The new species described herein were compared with these to ensure that they had not previously been described. Species were only formally described as new if at least three specimens were available. This is an admittedly arbitrary cutoff, but ensures at least a minimal characterization of intraspecific variability (including ontogenetic changes in form, which may be taxonomically important and cannot usually be characterized with only two specimens); a higher threshold would prevent description of some species that were naturally rare. Some distinctive morphologies were observed that do not meet this threshold; while some of these likely represent additional new species, they are not formally described at this time (some are figured here, however). Importantly, many of these are small specimens and may thus represent juveniles of species that have already been described, an issue recently also encountered by Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Nomenclatural Acts</title>
<p>The electronic edition of this article conforms to the requirements of the amended International Code of Zoological Nomenclature, and hence the new names contained herein are available under that Code from the electronic edition of this article. This published work and the nomenclatural acts it contains have been registered in ZooBank, the online registration system for the ICZN. The ZooBank LSIDs (Life Science Identifiers) can be resolved and the associated information viewed through any standard web browser by appending the LSID to the prefix "<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zoobank.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://zoobank.org/</ext-link>". The LSID for this publication is: urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:1B73A54D-BF92-4BB2-98DE-F3FC9D80E753. The electronic edition of this work was published in a journal with an ISSN, and has been archived and is available from the following digital repositories: PubMed Central and LOCKSS.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Morphological Terminology</title>
<p>Morphological terminology generally follows Röckel et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], Hendricks [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], and Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. An exception is the treatment of coloration patterning. Cone snail shell coloration patterns often show multiple pigmentation elements (e.g., dots, blotches, or bands) that <italic>appear</italic> to be positioned in different layers—that is, in superimposition—relative to each other. For example, a shell may have a base of pigmented blotches that appears to be covered by numerous spiral rows of dots (e.g., <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>). Another example is a shell that has a base of axial streaks that appears to be overprinted by solid spiral bands (e.g., <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1D</xref>). This study found that treating pigmentation elements as though they occur in separate (but sometimes interacting) layers was useful for their characterization and description. While covered layers are described here as “basal” or “primary” relative to the “secondary” layers that cover them, this is not meant to imply anything about the actual ordering of pigment deposition into the shell. Furthermore, it is important to note that experimental work on modern cone snail shells will be required to determine whether different pattern elements on the same shell actually exist in separate layers relative to each other, as is the case in at least one species of <italic>Littorina</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The terminology for individual pigmentation elements follows that of Röckel et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In some cases, shell coloration patterns revealed by UV fluorescence exhibit more than one color of emitted light. Such cases are noted here, as these variations may correspond with differences in the pigments that once colored the unfossilized shell; confirmation of this, however, will also require experimental work.</p>
<p>Abbreviations used in reference to shell measurements are from Röckel et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and include: SL, shell length; MD, maximum diameter; HMD, height of maximum diameter; and AH, aperture height (also see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]). From these, the following ratios were calculated to characterize different aspects of shell shape: RD, relative diameter (= MD/AH); PMD, position of maximum diameter (= HMD/AH); and RSH, relative spire height (= [SL-AH]/SL). See Röckel et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] for qualitative descriptions of these metrics, which are also used here. Qualitative descriptions of shell size—based on maximum observed SL—follow Röckel et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]: small, 15–25 mm; moderately small, 25–35 mm; medium, 35–55 mm; moderately large, 55–80 mm; and large, &gt;80 mm. Measurement values for specimens belonging to newly described species are given in <xref rid="pone.0120924.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Classification</title>
<p>This study follows the recent cone snail classification published by Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], which is based upon molecular phylogenetic evidence [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. This classification divides extant cone snails among four genera (<italic>Profundiconus</italic>, <italic>Californiconus</italic>, <italic>Conasprella</italic>, and <italic>Conus</italic>) and numerous subgenera (most of which were recognized as genera by Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]). While taxonomic classifications above the species level are largely arbitrary (e.g., [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]), the decision by Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] to split cone snails into four genera is based on their identification of several deep, ancient phylogenetic divergences that divide cone snails into four main clades [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Although debate may continue about whether a given cone snail clade should be recognized at the Linnaean rank of subgenus, genus, or family, such discussions are largely irrelevant to study of evolution in a phylogenetic context [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], unless one presumes (or requires) that equally-ranked taxa should be directly comparable in some way that is biologically meaningful. The rankings employed are very important, however, as tools for communication and in this respect the four-genus system of Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] is appealing from the perspective of nomenclatural stability, as cone snails have long been treated by many workers as belonging to one genus, <italic>Conus</italic> (see overview in [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]), and most extant species retain this generic assignment in the new classification [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p>
<p>The fossil species considered here are not placed in an explicit phylogenetic context at this time. Nevertheless, combinations of shell features shared between extant species of known phylogenetic position and the fossil species allow predictions to be made about the relationships of many of the extinct species to members of the modern fauna. Where possible, the fossil species have been assigned to both a genus and subgenus of cone snails. When this has not been possible, species have been assigned to the genus <italic>Conus</italic>. Unidentified fossils are referred to as Conidae sp., though most of these likely belong to <italic>Conus</italic>.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Systematics</title>
<p>In total, the cone snail fauna comprising TU stations 1422, 1215, and 1354 includes at least 28 species (<xref rid="pone.0120924.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), 13 of which are newly described below. Information about the type species for each higher taxon comes from Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] or Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. See Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] for information about the fossil record and morphological characteristics of these higher taxa. Abbreviated synonymy lists are provided for previously described species.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0120924.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Occurrence data.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0120924.t001g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TU 1422</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TU 1215</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TU 1354</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Dalliconus</italic>) cf. <italic>sauros</italic> (Garcia, 2006)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Ximeniconus</italic>) <italic>ageri</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Ximeniconus</italic>) <italic>cercadensis</italic> (Maury, 1917)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Ximeniconus</italic>) <italic>kitteredgei</italic> (Maury, 1917)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conasprella stenostoma</italic> (Sowerby I, 1850)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> ("<italic>Pyruconus</italic>") <italic>haytensis</italic> Sowerby I, 1850</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Atlanticonus</italic>?) <italic>franklinae</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Atlanticonus</italic>?) <italic>olssoni</italic> Maury, 1917</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>?) <italic>zambaensis</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>furvoides</italic> Gabb, 1873</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>garrisoni</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>karlschmidti</italic>? Maury, 1917</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>multiliratus</italic> Böse, 1906</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>planiliratus</italic> Sowerby I, 1850</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Ductoconus</italic>) <italic>cashi</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Lautoconus</italic>?) <italic>carlottae</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Pyruconus</italic>) <italic>recognitus</italic> Guppy, 1866</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Spuriconus</italic>?) <italic>kaesleri</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Spuriconus</italic>?) <italic>lombardii</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Spuriconus</italic>) <italic>humerosus</italic> Pilsbry, 1921</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Spuriconus</italic>) <italic>spurius</italic> Gmelin, 1791</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>bellacoensis</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>gouldi</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>sewalli</italic> Maury, 1917</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus anningae</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus lyelli</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus symmetricus</italic> Sowerby I, 1850</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Profundiconus</italic>? <italic>hennigi</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conidae spp.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No. Specimens</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>85</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>129</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>145</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>359</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No. Species</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>Number of specimens of each species observed at locality stations TU 1422, 1215, and 1354. Counts include specimens questionably assigned to a given taxon. Total numbers of species observed at each station are minimal estimates because they do not include specimens that have not been identified (i.e., Conidae spp.). (Note: two specimens of <italic>Conus symmetricus</italic> [PRI 66175, TU 1354 and PRI 67707, TU 1215] that are included in the counts above are currently missing.)</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p><bold>Genus <italic>Profundiconus</italic> Kuroda, 1956</bold></p>
<p>Type species: <italic>Chelyconus profundorum</italic> Kuroda, 1956.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Profundiconus</italic>? <italic>hennigi</italic> Hendricks sp. nov</bold>.</p>
<p>urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9B5C69B8-01EF-474E-88D1-F70584C3FDA8</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Profundiconus</italic>? <italic>hennigi</italic> Hendricks sp. nov.</title>
<p>Specimens are from locality station TU 1422 (Cercado Fm.). (A-E) PRI 66164 (holotype), SL 25.5 mm; (F) PRI 67168 (paratype), SL 17.6 mm; (G) PRI 67167 (paratype), SL 24.9 mm. (D-E) are reversed images of the holotype photographed under UV light. Scale bar to the left of (A) is 1 cm and pertains to (A, C-G); (B) scale bar is 1 mm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Holotype</bold>: PRI 66164. <bold>Paratypes</bold>: PRI 67167 and PRI 67168. All type specimens are from TU station 1422.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Type locality and horizon</title>
<p>TU 1422: Arroyo Bellaco, Dominican Republic; upper Miocene Cercado Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Description</title>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Shell size</title>
<p>Shell moderately small (largest observed specimen, PRI 66164, is 25.6 mm).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>Last whorl</title>
<p>Ventricosely conical (RD 0.60–0.62, μ = 0.61; PMD 0.82–0.84, μ = 0.83; n = 2); outline slightly convex. Shoulder subangulate, smooth. Widest part of shell below shoulder. Aperture uniform in width from base to shoulder. Siphonal notch absent. Widely spaced spiral threads on anterior half that are sometimes beaded.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>Spire whorls</title>
<p>Spire height high (RSH 0.27–0.30, μ = 0.29; n = 2); outline straight. Protoconch unknown. Early postnuclear whorls unknown; tubercles absent from preserved whorls. Sutural ramp convex, with at least 3 spiral threads. Subsutural flexure nearly symmetrical, depth approximately 0.9x width.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>One pattern present. Pattern consists of wavy to nearly straight, typically non-branching thin axial streaks that in many cases extend from the base to the shoulder. Axial streaks on the last whorl appear to extend onto the sutural ramp.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec019">
<title>Etymology</title>
<p>Named for Willi Hennig (1913–1976), developer of cladistics.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec020">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p>The only co-occurring fossil species with an overall shell shape—particularly a high spire—that is similar to <italic>Profundiconus</italic>? <italic>hennigi</italic> is <italic>Conus bellacoensis</italic> sp. nov., but that species has a very different coloration pattern, has tubercles on most of the spire whorls, and also lacks spiral threads on its sutural ramp. There are no extant western Atlantic cone snails that have a shell morphology similar to <italic>P</italic>.? <italic>hennigi</italic>. Interestingly, however, <italic>P</italic>.? <italic>hennigi</italic> does bear some resemblance in shell form to a living Indo-Pacific cone species that Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] assigned to the genus <italic>Profundiconus</italic> Kuroda, 1956: <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lani</italic> Crandall, 1979, which was illustrated by Röckel et al. ([<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], pl. 27, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g010" ref-type="fig">10</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g012" ref-type="fig">12</xref>). Given the strong similarity in shell form between this new fossil species and <italic>Profundiconus lani</italic>, the same genus-level assignment is tentatively followed here (Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] also recognized <italic>Profundiconus</italic> as a distinct clade of cone snails and demonstrated that it is basal to all other cone snail clades). <italic>Profundiconus</italic>? <italic>hennigi</italic> is the only known representative of the genus in the Neogene of the Dominican Republic.</p>
<p><bold>Genus <italic>Conasprella</italic> Thiele, 1929</bold></p>
<p>Type species: <italic>Conus pagoda</italic> Kiener, 1847.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conasprella stenostoma</italic> (Sowerby I, 1850)</bold> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g005</object-id>
<label>Fig 5</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conasprella stenostoma</italic> Sowerby I, 1850.</title>
<p>Both specimens are from locality station TU 1215 (Gurabo Fm.). (A-B) PRI 66148, SL 28.1 mm; (C-D) PRI 67549, SL 16.0 mm. All are reversed images of specimens photographed under UV light. Scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to all images.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><italic>Conus stenostoma</italic> Sowerby I, 1850 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], p. 44; Guppy, 1866 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], p. 287, pl. 16, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>; Pilsbry, 1921 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], p. 327–328, pl. 21, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Conus stenostomus</italic> Sowerby I, Maury, 1917 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], p. 203, pl. 6, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Kohniconus stenostoma</italic> (Sowerby I), Tucker and Tenorio, 2009 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], p. 146.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec021">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p>PRI 66148, PRI 67549 (TU station 1215).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec022">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Two noninteracting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern consists of 3 discontinuous spiral bands that sometimes form blotches. The secondary pattern (observed here in PRI 67549) consists of about 20 spiral rows of dots; these sometimes coalesce near the shoulder to form short diagonal lines. The two patterns differ in the color of emitted light. Sutural ramp with blotches.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec023">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p>The distinctive shell shape and coloration pattern of <italic>Conasprella stenostoma</italic> allows it to be easily distinguished from co-occurring fossil species. Among extant western Atlantic species, it is most similar to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>delessertii</italic> Récluz, 1843, which was recently characterized by Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The coloration patterns of the two species are similar (e.g., see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], pl. 24, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). One notable difference is that spiral groves cover the last whorl of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>stenostoma</italic>, but these are restricted to the anterior third in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>delessertii</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. While Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] assigned both <italic>C</italic>. <italic>stenostoma</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>delessertii</italic> to the genus <italic>Kohniconus</italic> Tucker and Tenorio, 2009, Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] found that <italic>C</italic>. <italic>delessertii</italic> did not group with other species that had been assigned to <italic>Kohniconus</italic>, which was treated as a subgenus of <italic>Conasprella</italic> Thiele, 1929 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Given its strong resemblance to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>delessertii</italic> and the taxonomic decision by Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] to characterize the taxonomic status of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>delessertii</italic> as “incertae sedis” within <italic>Conasprella</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>stenostoma</italic> is not assigned to a subgenus at this time.</p>
<p><bold>Subgenus <italic>Dalliconus</italic> Tucker and Tenorio, 2009</bold></p>
<p>Type species: <italic>Conus mcgintyi</italic> Pilsbry, 1955.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Dalliconus</italic>) cf. <italic>sauros</italic> (Garcia, 2006)</bold> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g006" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g006</object-id>
<label>Fig 6</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Dalliconus</italic>) cf. <italic>sauros</italic> Garcia, 2006.</title>
<p>All specimens are from locality station TU 1215 (Gurabo Fm.). (A-C) PRI 67585, SL 17.8 mm; (D) PRI 67581, SL 17.9 mm; (E-F) PRI 67580, SL 18.9 mm. All are reversed images of specimens photographed under UV light. Scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to all images.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><italic>Conus sauros</italic> Garcia, 2006 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], p. 71–74, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g009" ref-type="fig">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g016" ref-type="fig">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g018" ref-type="fig">18</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g021" ref-type="fig">21</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g022" ref-type="fig">22</xref>; Kohn, 2014 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], p. 126–128, pl. 22, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g018" ref-type="fig">18</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Dalliconus</italic>) <italic>sauros</italic> (Garcia), Puillandre et al., 2015 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], p. 5.</p>
<p><italic>Conus tortuosostriatus</italic> Maury, 1917 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], p. 205, pl. 6, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>; not Toula, 1911.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec024">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p>PRI 66136, PRI 67578–67591 (TU station 1215).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec025">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Probably one pattern present. Pattern consists of irregularly-spaced spiral dashes that often coalesce to form axial streaks, blotches, or discontinuous spiral bands; spaces between shoulder tubercles heavily pigmented. Sutural ramp with occasional blotches.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec026">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p>This small, high-spired species is common in some Dominican fossil localities, but the name that should be applied to it is not clear. Maury [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] figured a specimen of this species (PRI 28606) and called it <italic>Conus tortuosostriatus</italic> Toula, 1911, a species likely described from the Miocene Gatun Formation of the Canal Zone, Panama [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Woodring [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] showed that <italic>C</italic>. <italic>tortuosostriatus</italic> is a different species and referred Maury’s [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] specimen to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>gabbi</italic> Pilsbry and Johnson, 1917. The type of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>gabbi</italic> (ANSP 2553) was observed (see Pilsbry, 1921 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], pl. 21, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>) and it appears to be a different species: it is much larger (SL 42.5 mm) and the posterior half of its last whorl is convex in profile, while it is nearly straight in this species. The type of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>gracilissimus</italic> Guppy, 1866—a taxon originally described from Jamaica—is similar to this species, but bears tubercles on all of its spire whorls, which is not a characteristic of the species treated here, which has weak tubercles on the first postnuclear whorl and on the final spire whorls, but not in-between. This species is similar to the extant western Atlantic species <italic>C</italic>. <italic>sauros</italic> (Garcia, 2006)—which was recently characterized by Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]—and placed in the genus <italic>Conasprella</italic> and subgenus <italic>Dalliconus</italic> Tucker and Tenorio, 2009 by Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Once again, however, the fossil species differs by not having tubercles on all of its spire whorls, which is a feature of <italic>Conasprella sauros</italic>. Determination of whether this fossil form, which has been known at least since Maury [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], requires a new name will require additional research; until then, it is simply compared to the modern species as <italic>Conasprella</italic> cf. <italic>sauros</italic>.</p>
<p><bold>Subgenus <italic>Ximeniconus</italic> Emerson and Old, 1962</bold></p>
<p>Type species: <italic>Conus ximenes</italic> Gray, 1839.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Ximeniconus</italic>) <italic>cercadensis</italic> (Maury, 1917)</bold> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7A-E</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g007" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g007</object-id>
<label>Fig 7</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Ximeniconus</italic>) <italic>cercadensis</italic> Maury, 1917 (A-E), <italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Ximeniconus</italic>) <italic>kitteredgei</italic> Maury, 1917 (F-H), and <italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Ximeniconus</italic>) <italic>puncticulata</italic> (Hwass in Bruguière, 1792) (I-J).</title>
<p>Fossil specimens are from locality stations TU 1422 (Cercado Fm.), TU 1215 (Gurabo Fm.), and TU 1354 (Gurabo Fm.); modern <italic>C</italic>. <italic>puncticulata</italic> is from Bateau Bay, Trinidad and Tabago. (A-B) PRI 66153, TU 1422, SL 27.3 mm; (C) PRI 66150, TU 1215, SL 18.8 mm; (D-E) PRI 67185, TU 1422, SL 23.6 mm; (F) PRI 67546, TU 1354, SL 22.9 mm; (G-H) PRI 66183, TU 1354, SL 23.5 mm; (I-J) UF 281140, SL 25.5 mm. (A-H) are reversed images photographed under UV light. Scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to all images.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><italic>Conus cercadensis</italic> Maury, 1917 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], p. 207–208, pl. 7, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>; Pilsbry, 1921 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], p. 332, pl. 20, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Perplexiconus cercadensis</italic> (Maury), Tucker and Tenorio, 2009 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], p. 149.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec027">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Holotype</bold>: PRI 28613. <bold>Other specimens</bold>: PRI 66153, PRI 67185, PRI 67235, and PRI 67237 (TU station 1422); PRI 66150 (TU station 1215).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec028">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>One pattern present. Pattern consists of about 30–40 spiral lines, extending from base to shoulder; these coincide with the raised posterior edges of spiral ribs on the anterior half of the last whorl. Sutural ramp unpigmented.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec029">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p><italic>Conasprella cercadensis</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>kitteredgei</italic> (Maury, 1917) have similar overall shell morphologies, but their preserved coloration patterns exhibit subtle differences: <italic>C</italic>. <italic>kitteredgei</italic> shows evidence of axial streaks and spiral dashes on the last whorl, in addition to dots on the sutural ramp, none of which are observed in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cercadensis</italic>. Both taxa appear to be closely related to the Recent western Atlantic species <italic>C</italic>. <italic>puncticulata</italic> (Hwass in Bruguière, 1792) (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7I,J</xref>), which—with its axial streaks and rows of discontinuous spiral lines—has a coloration pattern that is most similar to that of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>kitteredgei</italic>. <italic>Conasprella puncticulata</italic> is the sister species of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>perplexa</italic> (Sowerby II, 1857) [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], a Recent eastern Pacific taxon. Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] assigned both <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cercadensis</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>kitteredgei</italic> to the genus <italic>Perplexiconus</italic> Tucker and Tenorio, 2009, which was considered by Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] a synonym of <italic>Ximeniconus</italic> Emerson and Old, 1962, a name that they applied at the subgeneric level and which is followed here.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Ximeniconus</italic>) <italic>kitteredgei</italic> (Maury, 1917)</bold> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7F-H</xref></p>
<p><italic>Conus kitteredgei</italic> Maury, 1917 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], pl. 7, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Perplexiconus kitteredgei</italic> (Maury), Tucker and Tenorio, 2009 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], p. 149.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec030">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Syntype</bold>: PRI 28615. <bold>Other specimens</bold>: PRI 66183, PRI 66187, PRI 67545, and PRI 67546 (TU station 1354).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec031">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Two weakly interacting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern consists of axial streaks that extend across much of the last whorl. Secondary pattern consists of about 20–22 discontinuous spiral lines (forming dashes) that extend from base to shoulder; these coincide with the raised posterior edges of spiral ribs on the entirety of the last whorl. The secondary pattern appears to be more intense in areas where it intersects the primary pattern. The two patterns differ slightly in the color of emitted light. Sutural ramp with dots on the abaxial margin.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec032">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p>See remarks for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cercadensis</italic> for a discussion of how its coloration pattern differs from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>kitteredgei</italic>, as well as a comparison with modern taxa.</p>
<p><italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Ximeniconus</italic>) <italic>ageri</italic> Hendricks sp. nov.</p>
<p>urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:5AEE94B0-AC55-4F8F-80EF-E5462E70BC4A</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8A-P</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g008" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g008</object-id>
<label>Fig 8</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Ximeniconus</italic>) <italic>ageri</italic> sp. nov. (A-P) and <italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Ximeniconus</italic>) <italic>tornata</italic> (Sowerby II, 1833) (Q-R).</title>
<p>Fossil specimens are from locality stations TU 1422 (Cercado Fm.) and TU 1354 (Gurabo Fm.); modern <italic>C</italic>. <italic>tornata</italic> is from Tortola Island, Bay of Panama. (A-E) PRI 67515, TU 1354, SL 30.8 mm; (F-G) PRI 67520, TU 1354, SL 26.9 mm; (H-I) PRI 67510, TU 1354, SL 24.1 mm; (J) PRI 67532, TU 1354, SL 19.4 mm; (K) PRI 67512, TU 1354, SL 25.1 mm; (L) PRI 66171, TU 1354, SL 28.0 mm; (M) PRI 67523, TU 1354, SL 26.8 mm; (N) PRI 67527, TU 1354, SL 23.2 mm; (O-P) PRI 67231, TU 1422, SL 16.4 mm; (Q-R) UF 355879, SL 28.4 mm. Scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to all images.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec033">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Holotype</bold>: PRI 67515. <bold>Paratypes</bold>: PRI 66171, PRI 67510–67514, PRI 67516–67536. All type specimens are from TU station 1354. <bold>Other specimens</bold>: PRI 67231–67232 (TU station 1422).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec034">
<title>Type locality and horizon</title>
<p>TU 1354: Cañada de Zamba, Dominican Republic; lower Pliocene Gurabo Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec035">
<title>Description</title>
<sec id="sec036">
<title>Shell size</title>
<p>Shell moderately small (largest observed specimen, PRI 67514, is 32.5 mm).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec037">
<title>Last whorl</title>
<p>Typically conical, sometimes ventricosely conical (RD 0.54–0.61, μ = 0.57; PMD 0.83–0.89, μ = 0.86; n = 17); outline slightly convex, except at anterior quarter, which is slightly concave. Shoulder sharply angulate, smooth. Widest part of shell just below shoulder. Aperture slightly wider at base than near shoulder. Siphonal notch absent; anterior-most end of lip sometimes extends slightly beyond columella. Incised spiral grooves on anterior half that diminish towards the shoulder; pustules sometimes present on adapical surfaces of intervening ribs (e.g., PRI 67510).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec038">
<title>Spire whorls</title>
<p>Spire height moderate (RSH 0.18–0.23, μ = 0.20; n = 17); outline slightly concave. Protoconch diameter 0.7–0.8 mm (based on PRI 67510, PRI 67511, and PRI 67518), number of whorls unknown. Tubercles absent from all spire whorls. Sutural ramp flat to concave on early whorls, concave in later whorls; spiral ornamentation absent, but growth lines prominent across sutural ramp. Subsutural flexure symmetrical and square-shaped to slightly curved abaxially; depth 1.5–2.3x width.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec039">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Two noninteracting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern consists of axially-arranged, irregularly-shaped blotches of variable width. The secondary pattern typically consists of about 20–30 spiral rows of dots or dashes. The two patterns differ in the color of emitted light. Sutural ramp with blotches.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec040">
<title>Etymology</title>
<p>Named in honor of paleontologist Derek V. Ager, author of “The Nature of the Stratigraphical Record” [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec041">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p>A specimen of cone snail (NHMUK PI BM 64050) remarkably similar to <italic>Conasprella ageri</italic> is present in collections at the NHMUK associated with Guppy’s [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] report on fossil mollusks from Jamaica (photographs of the specimen may be viewed online through the NHMUK Palaeontology Collection Database: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nhm.ac.uk/research-curation/scientific-resources/collections/palaeontological-collections/palaeontology-specimen-database/index.php" xlink:type="simple">http://www.nhm.ac.uk/research-curation/scientific-resources/collections/palaeontological-collections/palaeontology-specimen-database/index.php</ext-link>). NHMUK PI BM 64050 is labeled as “<italic>Conus solidus</italic>,” a very differently shaped species that is synonymous with <italic>Conus recognitus</italic> Guppy, 1867 (this was recognized by Maury [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], Pilsbry [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], and Woodring [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]). It does not appear that the distinctive morphology of NHMUK PI BM 64050 was ever formally described by Guppy or other workers. It is likely a specimen of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>ageri</italic>, as its shell characteristics are consistent with the new species (it is not known at the present time, however, whether it bears a preserved coloration pattern visible under UV light). Two poorly preserved shells—PRI 67231 and PRI 67232—are from TU station 1422 and may be additional specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>ageri</italic>. PRI 67231 has a well-preserved coloration pattern that is consistent with <italic>C</italic>. <italic>ageri</italic>, except that the primary pattern consists of two nearly continuous spiral bands that separate an unpigmented region in the middle of the last whorl (see <xref rid="pone.0120924.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8O,P</xref>). The specimens of <italic>Conus granozonatus</italic> Guppy, 1866 figured by Woodring [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] (from Jamaica) and holotype of <italic>Conus trisculptus</italic> Pilsbry and Johnson, 1917 (ANSP 2567) (from the Dominican Republic) are very similar in shell form to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>ageri</italic>, but both species show evidence of tubercles on the shoulder, which are not present on <italic>C</italic>. <italic>ageri</italic>.</p>
<p>Among extant species, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>ageri</italic> is most similar in shell morphology and coloration pattern to the eastern Pacific species <italic>Conasprella tornata</italic> (Sowerby II, 1833) (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8Q,R</xref>). <italic>Conasprella tornata</italic> was assigned by Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] to the subgenus <italic>Ximeniconus</italic> and this assignment is also followed here for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>ageri</italic>.</p>
<p><bold>Genus <italic>Conus</italic> Linnaeus, 1758</bold></p>
<p>Type species: <italic>Conus marmoreus</italic> Linnaeus, 1758.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus symmetricus</italic> Sowerby I, 1850</bold> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g009" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g009</object-id>
<label>Fig 9</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus symmetricus</italic> Sowerby I, 1850.</title>
<p>Specimens are from locality stations TU 1422 (Cercado Fm.), TU 1215 (Gurabo Fm.), and TU 1354 (Gurabo Fm.). (A-B) PRI 67665, TU 1215, SL 27.3 mm; (C) PRI 67190, TU 1422, SL 17.1 mm; (D) PRI 67192, TU 1422, SL 19.5 mm; (E) PRI 67191, TU 1422, SL 27.4 mm; (F) PRI 67675, TU 1354, SL 26.2 mm; (G) PRI 66155, TU 1422, SL 46.1 mm. All are reversed images of specimens photographed under UV light. Scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to all images.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><italic>Conus symmetricus</italic> Sowerby I, 1850 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], p. 44, pl. 9, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>; Maury, 1917 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], pl. 7, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7, 7A</xref>; Pilsbry, 1921 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], pl. 20, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2, 2A, 2B</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Leptoconus</italic>) <italic>symmetricus</italic> Sowerby I, Pflug, 1961 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], p. 63–64, pl. 18, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g011" ref-type="fig">11</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Purpuriconus symmetricus</italic> (Sowerby I), Tucker and Tenorio, 2009 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], p. 116.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec042">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Lectotype</bold>: NHMUK PI BM G 83969 (designated by Pflug [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]). <bold>Other specimens</bold>. PRI 66155, PRI 67187–67188, PRI 67190–67192, PRI 67228–67229 (TU station 1422); PRI 66135, PRI 67665, PRI 67701–67741 (TU station 1215); PRI 66170, PRI 66175, PRI 67672–67699 (TU station 1354).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec043">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>While otherwise consistent in shell morphology, specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>symmetricus</italic> show a wide range of variability in coloration pattern. Two general types of observed coloration pattern are described here.</p>
<p>Type 1 (see <xref rid="pone.0120924.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9A,B,F,G</xref>). Two noninteracting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern consists of irregularly-shaped axial streaks or spots that cover most of the last whorl. The secondary pattern consists of about 17–20 spiral rows of dots that correspond with beaded spiral ribs on the basal two-thirds of the last whorl. The two patterns differ slightly in the color of emitted light. Sutural ramp with radial streaks.</p>
<p>Type 2 (see <xref rid="pone.0120924.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9C,D</xref>, questionably E). Two noninteracting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern consists of three weakly-pigmented, discontinuous spiral bands. The secondary pattern consists of about 20 spiral rows of dots, which sometimes coalesce near the shoulder to form axial streaks. The two patterns differ slightly in the color of emitted light. Sutural ramp with radial streaks.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec044">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p><italic>Conus symmetricus</italic>—which is a common species, especially in the Gurabo Fm.—has a very distinctive shell shape that is not easily confused with co-occurring species. Its relationship to extant species is not clear. Petuch [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] stated that <italic>C</italic>. <italic>tristensis</italic> Petuch, 1987 “probably represents the last living member of the <italic>C</italic>. <italic>symmetricus-dominguensis</italic> species complex” ([<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], p. 113) (also see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], p. 272). Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] considered <italic>C</italic>. <italic>tristensis</italic> a synonym, albeit somewhat tentatively, of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cancellatus</italic> Hwass in Bruguière, 1792, which was assigned to the subgenus <italic>Dauciconus</italic> by Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. While many specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>symmetricus</italic> have an overall shell shape that is somewhat similar to that of the holotype of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>tristensis</italic> (see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], pl. 69, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>), specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>symmetricus</italic> always have beaded ribs on the last whorl, which were not reported by Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] in his recent description of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cancellatus</italic>. Additionally, shells of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>symmetricus</italic> are widest below the shoulder, but specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cancellatus</italic> are usually widest at the shoulder. Finally, coloration patterns similar to those described above for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>symmetricus</italic> are not present in any known specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cancellatus</italic>, which are often—though not always (see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>])—unpigmented. Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] assigned <italic>C</italic>. <italic>symmetricus</italic> to the genus <italic>Purpuriconus</italic> da Motta, 1991, which they defined in part as having “only 1 cord that may not persist on the whorl tops” (p. 115); <italic>C</italic>. <italic>symmetricus</italic>, however, has several spiral threads on the sutural ramp (e.g., <xref rid="pone.0120924.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9B</xref>; Pflug [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], pl. 18, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g010" ref-type="fig">10</xref>). Because its phylogenetic position cannot be resolved at this time, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>symmetricus</italic> is not assigned to a subgenus.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus anningae</italic> Hendricks sp. nov</bold>.</p>
<p>urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FC37256A-4348-4916-A241-F4BDBB4F4552</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g010" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g010</object-id>
<label>Fig 10</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus anningae</italic> Hendricks sp. nov.</title>
<p>All specimens are from locality station TU 1215 (Gurabo Fm.). (A-E) PRI 66141 (holotype), SL 30.3 mm; (F-G) PRI 67567 (paratype), SL 19.2 mm; (H-J) PRI 67569 (paratype), SL 25.2 mm. (B, F-J) are reversed images of specimens photographed under UV light. Scale bar to left of (A) is 1 cm and pertains to images (A-D and F-J); scale bar below (E) is 1 mm and pertains to that image. (E) is a focal stacked image constructed from 10 separate images using Helicon Focus software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.heliconsoft.com/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.heliconsoft.com/</ext-link>).</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g010" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec045">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Holotype</bold>: PRI 66141. <bold>Paratypes</bold>: PRI 67567, PRI 67569. All type specimens are from TU station 1215.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec046">
<title>Type locality and horizon</title>
<p>TU 1215: Río Gurabo, Dominican Republic; lower Pliocene Gurabo Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec047">
<title>Description</title>
<sec id="sec048">
<title>Shell size</title>
<p>Shell moderately small (largest observed specimen, PRI 66141, is 30.3 mm).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec049">
<title>Last whorl</title>
<p>Conoid-cylindrical (RD 0.50–0.53, μ = 0.52; PMD 0.82–0.85, μ = 0.84; n = 3); outline slightly convex, except at anterior quarter, which is slightly concave. Shoulder subangulate; smooth. Widest part of shell below shoulder. Aperture slightly wider at base than near shoulder. Siphonal notch absent. Spiral threads on anterior third.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec050">
<title>Spire whorls</title>
<p>Spire height low (RSH 0.10–0.11, μ = 0.10; n = 3); outline sigmoidal. Protoconch with &gt;3 whorls (based on PRI 66141), diameter 0.7–0.8 mm (based on all three known specimens); protrudes above subsequent whorls. Tubercles present on first 0.5–2 postnuclear whorls, becoming weakly undulate on following several whorls before diminishing. Sutural ramp concave on early whorls, convex on later whorls, with multiple spiral threads. Subsutural flexure asymmetrical, depth about equal to width.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec051">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Two weakly interacting patterns present. PRI 66141 (holotype; <xref rid="pone.0120924.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10A-E</xref>) and PRI 67567 (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10F,G</xref>) appear to have a solidly pigmented primary (base) pattern that extends from the anterior end to the shoulder; in PRI 67569 (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10H-J</xref>), this primary pattern is restricted to two pigmented bands that each cover about one-fifth of the last whorl. The secondary pattern consists of 5 or at least 6 (PRI 67567 and PRI 66141, respectively) to as many as 19 (PRI 67569) spiral rows of square-shaped dots. Interaction between the two patterns occurs when the spiral dots intersect the base pattern, resulting in unpigmented spaces between the spiral dots (e.g., see anterior band on <xref rid="pone.0120924.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10H</xref>). The two patterns differ in the color of emitted light. Sutural ramp with radial streaks that correspond with the shape of the subsutural flexure.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec052">
<title>Etymology</title>
<p>Named for Mary Anning (1799–1847) in honor of the important fossil discoveries that she made at Lyme Regis, England. Anning is the person referred to in Terry Sullivan’s famous tongue-twister “she sells seashells on the seashore.”</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec053">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p>The preserved coloration pattern of paratype PRI 67569 (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10H-J</xref>) differs significantly from that of the other two known specimens in the number of spiral rows of dots (see above), but this shell is otherwise consistent in other aspects of shell form. It is assumed, therefore, that these differences in coloration pattern amount to intraspecific variation and that all three specimens belong to the same species. Comparison with Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] reveals that <italic>Conus anningae</italic> is not similar in shell morphology to any extant western Atlantic cone snail species, nor is it similar to any other known extant or fossil species. It may therefore represent an extinct lineage of Conidae.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus lyelli</italic> Hendricks sp. nov</bold>.</p>
<p>urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8D6708E0-9262-4CA2-B03D-39A4EFB5081B</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g011" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11A-L</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g011" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g011</object-id>
<label>Fig 11</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus lyelli</italic> Hendricks sp. nov. (A-L) and <italic>Conus xenicus</italic> Pilsbry and Johnson, 1917 (M-N).</title>
<p>Specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>lyelli</italic> are from locality stations TU 1422 (Cercado Fm.), TU 1278 (Gurabo Fm.), and TU 1354 (Gurabo Fm.); the specimen label associated with the holotype of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>xenicus</italic> (M-N) reports the locality as “S. Domingo.” (A-C) PRI 66156 (holotype), TU 1422, SL 23.7 mm; (D-F) PRI 67165 (paratype), TU 1354, SL 21.2 mm; (G-I) PRI 66189 (paratype), TU 1422, SL 20.3 mm; (J) PRI 66184 (paratype), TU 1354, SL 22.3 mm; (K-L) PRI 66115 (paratype), TU 1278, SL 29.4 mm (estimated from digital image); (M-N) ANSP 2575 (holotype), SL 28.3 mm (estimated from digital image). (C-D, J) are reversed images of specimens photographed under UV light. (I) is a focal stacked image constructed from 9 separate images using Helicon Focus software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.heliconsoft.com/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.heliconsoft.com/</ext-link>). Scale bar to the left of (A) is 1 cm and pertains to (A-D, G, J-N); (E, H) scale bars are 5 mm; (F) scale bar is 2 mm; (I) scale bar is 1 mm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g011" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec054">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Holotype</bold>: PRI 66156 (TU station 1422). <bold>Paratypes</bold>: PRI 66189–66192 (TU station 1422); PRI 66184 and 67165 (TU station 1354); PRI 66115 (TU station 1278).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec055">
<title>Type locality and horizon</title>
<p>TU 1422: Arroyo Bellaco, Dominican Republic; upper Miocene Cercado Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec056">
<title>Other localities and horizons</title>
<p>TU 1354: Cañada de Zamba, Dominican Republic; lower Pliocene Gurabo Formation. TU 1278: Río Gurabo, Dominican Republic; lower Pliocene Gurabo Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec057">
<title>Description</title>
<sec id="sec058">
<title>Shell size</title>
<p>Shell moderately small (largest observed complete specimen, PRI 66156, is 23.7 mm; a fragment of a larger specimen, PRI 66192, with MD 22.8 mm is also known, suggesting a complete shell size of about 35 mm).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec059">
<title>Last whorl</title>
<p>Broadly conical (RD 0.70–0.75, μ = 0.73; PMD 0.89–0.93, μ = 0.91; n = 3); outline slightly sigmoidal. Shoulder subangulate, with undulations. Widest point of shell at shoulder. Aperture uniform in width from base to shoulder. Siphonal notch absent. Spiral threads on anterior half, diminishing towards shoulder.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec060">
<title>Spire whorls</title>
<p>Spire height low to moderate (RSH 0.09–0.17, μ = 0.15; n = 3), with later whorls depressed beneath shoulder in some specimens; outline concave. Protoconch with 2.2 whorls, diameter 0.8 mm (based on PRI 66189). Tubercles present on first several postnuclear whorls, becoming posterior-pointing shoulder undulations in later whorls. Sutural ramp slightly concave to flat, with 3–6 fine spiral threads. Subsutural flexure symmetrical, depth about 0.6–0.8x width.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec061">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>One pattern present. Pattern consists of slightly jagged to saw-toothed, non-branching thin axial streaks that in many cases extend from the base to the shoulder. There is no evidence of a coloration pattern on the spire whorls.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec062">
<title>Etymology</title>
<p>Named for the great geologist Charles Lyell (1797–1875), who popularized the concepts of uniformitarianism and the antiquity of the earth.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec063">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p><italic>Conus lyelli</italic> is most similar in shell shape to <italic>Conus xenicus</italic> Pilsbry and Johnson, 1917 (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g011" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11M,N</xref>), which is also known from the Neogene of the Dominican Republic. An important difference is that <italic>C</italic>. <italic>lyelli</italic> possesses tubercles or shoulder undulations on all postnuclear whorls, while these features are absent in the holotype of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>xenicus</italic> (ANSP 2575). Additionally, the shoulder in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>xenicus</italic> is angulate and this species also has much more prominent spiral threads on its sutural ramp. As detailed locality information is not available for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>xenicus</italic>, it is not known whether it was contemporaneous with <italic>C</italic>. <italic>lyelli</italic>. Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] assigned <italic>C</italic>. <italic>xenicus</italic> to the genus <italic>Jaspidiconus</italic> Petuch, 2003, but it does not have a shell like extant species that have been assigned to that clade (note that Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] recognized <italic>Jaspidiconus</italic> as synonym of <italic>Conasprella</italic>, subgenus <italic>Ximeniconus</italic>). <italic>Conus ornatus</italic> of Maury, 1917 (not of Röding, which in turn is a junior synonym of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>generalis</italic> Linnaeus, 1767; see Röckel et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]) and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>williamgabbi</italic> Maury, 1917 are also somewhat similar to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>lyelli</italic>, both having broad shells with low spires. Like <italic>C</italic>. <italic>xenicus</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>ornatus</italic> differs from the new species in its lack of tuberculate postnuclear whorls. <italic>Conus williamgabbi</italic> has an asymmetrical, deep subsutural flexure and is much larger than the new species. <italic>Conus lyelli</italic> is not similar to any known extant species, suggesting that it, along with <italic>C</italic>. <italic>xenicus</italic>, may be members of an extinct clade of cone snails.</p>
<p><bold>Subgenus <italic>Atlanticonus</italic> Petuch and Sargent, 2012</bold></p>
<p>Type species: <italic>Conus granulatus</italic> Linnaeus, 1758.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Atlanticonus</italic>?) <italic>olssoni</italic> (Maury, 1917)</bold> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g012" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12A-I</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g012" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g012</object-id>
<label>Fig 12</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus olssoni</italic> Maury, 1917 (A-I) and <italic>Conus granulatus</italic> Linnaeus, 1758 (J).</title>
<p>Fossil specimens are from locality stations TU 1422 (Cercado Fm.), TU 1215 (Gurabo Fm.), and TU 1354 (Gurabo Fm.); modern <italic>C</italic>. <italic>granulatus</italic> is from Isla Payardi, Bahia las Minas, Panama. (A) PRI 67198, TU 1422, SL 46.4 mm; (B) PRI 67203, TU 1422, SL 22.4 mm; (C) PRI 67199, TU 1422, SL 25.3 mm; (D) PRI 66137, TU 1215, SL 36.8 mm; (E) PRI 67204, TU 1422, SL 25.4 mm; (F-G) PRI 67200, TU 1422, SL 27.4 mm; (H) PRI 67245, TU 1354, SL 36.7 mm; (I) PRI 67598, TU 1215, SL 21.1 mm; (J) UF 329263–1, SL 35.0 mm. (A-I) are reversed images photographed under UV light. Scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to all images.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g012" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><italic>Conus olssoni</italic> Maury, 1917 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], p. 207, pl. 7, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Dauciconus olssoni</italic> (Maury), Tucker and Tenorio, 2009 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], p. 89.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec064">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Holotype</bold>: PRI 28612. <bold>Other specimens</bold>: PRI 66157, PRI 67198–67206 (TU station 1422); PRI 66137, PRI 67592–67604 (TU station 1215); PRI 66180, PRI 67242, PRI 67244–67251 (TU station 1354).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec065">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>One pattern present. Pattern consists of slightly wavy to nearly straight, sometimes branching axial streaks that often extend from the base to the shoulder; these become finer in width as shell size increases. In some specimens (e.g., PRI 66137, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g012" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12D</xref> and PRI 67598, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g012" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12I</xref>), pigmented blotches occur at the shoulder; it is not clear how these relate to the principle pattern. The last whorl pattern extends over the shoulder onto the sutural ramp.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec066">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p><italic>Conus olssoni</italic> has a distinctive shell shape that is not easily confused with co-occurring species. It does, however, bear some similarity in shell form to <italic>Conus granulatus</italic> Linnaeus, 1758 (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g012" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12J</xref>), an extant western Atlantic species recently characterized by Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In particular, both species have similarly shaped last whorls and stepped spire whorls. While some specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>granulatus</italic> have faint axial streaks on the last whorl (e.g., [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], pl. 2, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g010" ref-type="fig">10</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g011" ref-type="fig">11</xref>), these are much more pronounced in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>olssoni</italic>. Additionally, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>granulatus</italic> possesses spiral rows of ribs and pigmented dots on the last whorl; these were not observed in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>olssoni</italic>.</p>
<p>Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] placed <italic>C</italic>. <italic>olssoni</italic> in the genus <italic>Dauciconus</italic> Cotton, 1945. Given the similarities in shell shape that it shares with <italic>C</italic>. <italic>granulatus</italic>, however, it is instead tentatively placed in the subgenus <italic>Atlanticonus</italic> Petuch and Sargent, 2012, following the designation for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>granulatus</italic> by Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. It is worth mentioning that none of the four extant species assigned to the subgenus <italic>Atlanticonus</italic> by Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] have been subjected to phylogenetic analysis; thus, this clade still requires verification.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Atlanticonus</italic>?) <italic>franklinae</italic> Hendricks sp. nov</bold>.</p>
<p>urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:3E38EC90-8C86-45AB-8DEC-20927DB90FFE</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g013" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g013" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g013</object-id>
<label>Fig 13</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Atlanticonus</italic>?) <italic>franklinae</italic> Hendricks sp. nov.</title>
<p>Specimens are from locality stations TU 1422 (Cercado Fm.) and TU 1215 (Gurabo Fm.). (A-E) PRI 66142 (holotype), TU 1215, SL 32.7 mm; (F) PRI 67227 (paratype), TU 1422, SL 18.8 mm; (G-H) PRI 67226 (paratype), TU 1422, SL 14.7 mm; (I-M) PRI 67230 (paratype), TU 1422, SL 10.5 mm. (C-J) are reversed images of specimens photographed under UV light. Scale bar to the left of (A) is 1 cm and pertains to (A-J); (K, M) scale bars are 1 mm; (L) scale bar is 2 mm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g013" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec067">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Holotype</bold>: PRI 66142 (TU station 1215). <bold>Paratypes</bold>: PRI 67226, PRI 67227, and PRI 67230 (TU station 1422).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec068">
<title>Type locality and horizon</title>
<p>TU 1215: Río Gurabo, Dominican Republic; lower Pliocene Gurabo Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec069">
<title>Other locality and horizon</title>
<p>TU 1422: Arroyo Bellaco, Dominican Republic; upper Miocene Cercado Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec070">
<title>Description</title>
<sec id="sec071">
<title>Shell size</title>
<p>Shell moderately small (largest observed specimen, PRI 66142, is 32.7 mm).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec072">
<title>Last whorl</title>
<p>Ventricosely conical (RD 0.58–0.59, μ = 0.58; PMD 0.79–0.83, μ = 0.81; n = 3); outline convex, except at anterior quarter, which is slightly concave. Shoulder subangulate, smooth. Widest part of shell below shoulder. Aperture uniform in width from base to shoulder. Siphonal notch present. Fine spiral threads on anterior half of juvenile specimens, extending to shoulder in mature specimens.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec073">
<title>Spire whorls</title>
<p>Spire height moderate (RSH 0.13–0.19, μ = 0.16; n = 3); outline sigmoidal. Protoconch multispiral, diameter 0.8 mm (based on partial remains on PRI 67230). Tubercles present on first 2 postnuclear whorls. Sutural ramp slightly concave to flat on early whorls, convex on later whorls, with several spiral threads. Subsutural flexure asymmetrical, depth approximately 0.5–0.9x width.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec074">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Two noninteracting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern consists of a solid to blotchy ground pattern that is interrupted by 2–4 spiral rows of inconsistently arranged, unpigmented dots. The secondary pattern consists—at least in juvenile specimens—of at least 10 spiral rows of dots. The two patterns differ slightly in the color of emitted light. Sutural ramp with blotches that appear to be extensions of the primary last whorl pattern.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec075">
<title>Etymology</title>
<p>Named in honor of Rosalind Franklin (1920–1958) for the important role that she played in discovering the structure of DNA.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec076">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p>The shell morphology and coloration pattern of <italic>Conus franklinae</italic> is somewhat similar to that of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>zambaensis</italic> sp. nov. (see below). The two species do not overlap, however, in their positions of maximum diameter (PMD 0.79–0.83 in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>franklinae</italic>, 0.84–0.88 in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>zambaensis</italic>) or relative spire heights (RSH 0.13–0.19 in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>franklinae</italic>, 0.06–0.09 in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>zambaensis</italic>). Additionally, the subsutural flexure in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>franklinae</italic> is asymmetrical, while that of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>zambaensis</italic> is nearly symmetrical and deeper. <italic>Conus franklinae</italic> bears strong similarity to the extant western Atlantic species <italic>Conus ritae</italic> Petuch, 1995, which is only known from a few specimens [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Besides having an overall shape that is similar to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>ritae</italic>, the coloration patterning of both species closely match (see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], pl. 4). Specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>franklinae</italic>, however, have narrower last whorls than specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>ritae</italic> (Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] reported RD values for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>ritae</italic> that range from 0.61–0.68). Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] assigned <italic>C</italic>. <italic>ritae</italic> to the subgenus <italic>Atlanticonus</italic>, along with three other species: <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cuna</italic> Petuch, 1998, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>granulatus</italic> Linnaeus, 1758, and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>glenni</italic> Petuch, 1993 (none of these four extant species of <italic>Atlanticonus</italic> have yet been placed in an explicit phylogenetic context). This subgeneric assignment is tentatively also followed here for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>franklinae</italic>.</p>
<p><bold>Subgenus <italic>Stephanoconus</italic> Mörch, 1852</bold></p>
<p>Type species: <italic>Conus regius</italic> Gmelin, 1791.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>gouldi</italic> Hendricks sp. nov</bold>.</p>
<p>urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:0436FD65-9526-44F9-8FA3-E2AAA537101A</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g014" ref-type="fig">Fig. 14A-J</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g014" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g014</object-id>
<label>Fig 14</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>gouldi</italic> Hendricks sp. nov. (A-J) and <italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>regius</italic> Gmelin, 1791 (K).</title>
<p>Fossil specimens are from locality station TU 1422 (Cercado Fm.); modern <italic>C</italic>. <italic>regius</italic> is from the West Indies. (A-C) PRI 66168 (holotype), SL 24.3 mm; (D-F) PRI 66193 (paratype), SL 22.3 mm; (G-H) PRI 66194 (paratype), SL 19.8 mm; (I-J) PRI 66197 (paratype), SL 12.0 mm; (K) CASIZ 178046, 53.1 mm. (D-F, I-J) are reversed images of specimens photographed under UV light. Scale bar to the left of (A) is 1 cm and pertains to (A-D, F-G, I-J); (E) is a magnified view of the shoulder region of (D), illustrating pigmentation between tubercles; (H) scale bar is 5 mm; (K) scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to that image.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g014" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec077">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Holotype</bold>: PRI 66168. <bold>Paratypes</bold>: PRI 66193–66197. All type specimens are from TU station 1422.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec078">
<title>Type locality and horizon</title>
<p>TU 1422: Arroyo Bellaco, Dominican Republic; upper Miocene Cercado Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec079">
<title>Description</title>
<sec id="sec080">
<title>Shell size</title>
<p>Shell moderately small (largest observed specimen, PRI 66196, is 26.7 mm; this specimen is missing a small portion of its spire and anterior end).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec081">
<title>Last whorl</title>
<p>Broadly and ventricosely conical or broadly conical (RD 0.70–0.75, μ = 0.72; PMD 0.81–0.88, μ = 0.84; n = 5); outline convex to sigmoidal. Shoulder subangulate, tuberculate. Most shells widest below shoulder. Aperture uniform in width from base to shoulder. Siphonal notch absent. Fine spiral threads restricted to the basal half; some specimens exhibit a fine spiral groove that cuts across shoulder tubercles.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec082">
<title>Spire whorls</title>
<p>Spire height low to moderate (RSH 0.10–0.23, μ = 0.18; n = 5); outline straight to slightly convex. Protoconch unknown. All postnuclear whorls tuberculate. Sutural ramp concave to sigmoidal, with multiple spiral threads. Subsutural flexure asymmetrical, depth about 1.7x width.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec083">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Description based on mature specimen PRI 66193 (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g014" ref-type="fig">Fig. 14D-F</xref>). Two noninteracting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern consists of two irregular spiral bands on the last whorl; occasional axial blotches extend toward the shoulder from the posterior band. Regions between the shoulder tubercles are also pigmented. The secondary pattern consists of many (&gt;30; poor preservation prevents an accurate count) spiral rows of fine dots that extend from the base to just below the shoulder; at the shoulder, these appear to coalesce into fine axial streaks. The two patterns differ slightly in the color of emitted light. Pattern on sutural ramp unknown. Immature specimen PRI 66197 (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g014" ref-type="fig">Fig. 14I,J</xref>) has irregular blotches on the last whorl and lacks the secondary pattern.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec084">
<title>Etymology</title>
<p>Named for Stephen J. Gould (1941–2002) in recognition of his important contributions to paleontology.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec085">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p><italic>Conus gouldi</italic> is unlike co-occurring fossil species, but is very similar in shell morphology to the extant western Atlantic species <italic>Conus regius</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g014" ref-type="fig">Fig. 14K</xref>), as recently circumscribed by Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Coloration patterns are not well preserved in the known specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>gouldi</italic>, but PRI 66193 does show last whorl patterning similar to some adult specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>regius</italic> (e.g., [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], pl. 40, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g008" ref-type="fig">8</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g009" ref-type="fig">9</xref>). Furthermore, juvenile specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>regius</italic> (e.g., [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], pl. 42, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g009" ref-type="fig">9</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g011" ref-type="fig">11</xref>) sometimes lack the spiral rows of dots that are present in mature specimens, something also observed here in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>gouldi</italic> (PRI 66197). An important difference between the fossil and extant species, however, is adult shell size; <italic>C</italic>. <italic>regius</italic> reaches a “[t]ypical” shell length of 43 mm ([<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], p. 179; the largest known specimen is over 80 mm), but the largest specimen of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>gouldi</italic> is only 26.7 mm (it is missing a small portion of its spire and anterior end, however).</p>
<p>Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] demonstrated a close relationship between <italic>C</italic>. <italic>regius</italic> and the sister taxa <italic>C</italic>. <italic>bartschi</italic> Hanna and Strong, 1949 and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>brunneus</italic> Wood, 1828, all three of which they assigned to the subgenus <italic>Stephanoconus</italic> Mörch, 1852 (along with seven additional species). This subgeneric assignment is followed here for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>gouldi</italic>.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>sewalli</italic> Maury, 1917</bold> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 15A-I</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g015" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g015</object-id>
<label>Fig 15</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>sewalli</italic> (Maury, 1917) (A-I) and <italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>mappa</italic> [Lightfoot, 1786] (J).</title>
<p>Fossil specimens are from locality stations TU 1422 (Cercado Fm.) and TU 1215 (Gurabo Fm.); modern <italic>C</italic>. <italic>mappa</italic> is from Pigeon Point, Tobago. (A-B) PRI 67183, TU 1422, SL 30.6 mm; (C) PRI 66160, TU 1422, SL 44.1 mm; (D-E) PRI 67193, TU 1422, SL 23.5 mm; (F) PRI 67184, TU 1422, SL 33.3 mm; (G) PRI 67565, TU 1215, SL 17.3 mm; (H) PRI 67564, TU 1215, SL 25.2 mm; (I) PRI 66152, TU 1215, SL 24.1 mm; (J) UF 281116–1, SL 64.4 mm. (A-I) are reversed images photographed under UV light. Scale bar to left of (A) is 1 cm and pertains to (A-I). Scale bar to right of (J) is 1 cm and pertains to that image.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g015" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><italic>Conus sewalli</italic> Maury, 1917 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], p. 201–202, pl. 5, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, pl. 6, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Purpuriconus sewalli</italic> (Maury), Tucker and Tenorio, 2009 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], p. 116.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec086">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Syntype</bold>: PRI 28599. <bold>Other specimens</bold>: PRI 66160, PRI 66163, PRI 67183, PRI 67184, PRI 67193 (TU station 1422); PRI 66152, PRI 67564–67565 (TU 1215); PRI 66182 (TU 1354).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec087">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Two weakly interacting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern consists of two elements: 1) both large and small irregularly shaped blotches concentrated into two regions on the last whorl—near the anterior end of the shell and below the PMD of the last whorl, leaving an unpigmented region just below the center; 2) small sub-triangular markings concentrated on the posterior third of the last whorl. The secondary pattern consists of 17–23 spiral rows of dots and dashes extending from the base to shoulder; spaces between dashes are sometimes unpigmented in instances where the secondary pattern overlies the primary pattern. The secondary pattern coincides with spiral ornamentation features on the anterior end of the shell. The two patterns differ in the color of emitted light. The axial blotches associated with the primary pattern sometimes extend over the shoulder onto the sutural ramp.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec088">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p><italic>Conus sewalli</italic> is similar in shell form to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>haytensis</italic> Sowerby I, 1850 (see below), another Dominican Neogene species, and the two taxa can be challenging to differentiate without observation of their coloration patterns. Most significantly, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>sewalli</italic> has sub-triangular markings on the last whorl, but these are absent in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>haytensis</italic>. Furthermore, the last whorl shape of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>sewalli</italic> tends to be more convex than that of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>haytensis</italic>, which is often slightly sigmoidal in profile. The coloration pattern of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>sewalli</italic> is similar to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>bellacoensis</italic> sp. nov. (see below), as well as extant species such as <italic>C</italic>. <italic>mappa</italic> (Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g015" ref-type="fig">15J</xref>) and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>curassaviensis</italic> (see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], pl. 39, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g018" ref-type="fig">Fig. 18</xref>) that are members of the western Atlantic “<italic>Conus cedonulli</italic> Species Group” (see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], p. 144). For additional discussion of this association, see remarks below for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>bellacoensis</italic> sp. nov. Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] placed <italic>C</italic>. <italic>sewalli</italic> in the genus <italic>Purpuriconus</italic> da Motta, 1991, but the strong similarity between <italic>C</italic>. <italic>sewalli</italic> and extant species like <italic>C</italic>. <italic>mappa</italic> instead suggest that it belongs in the subgenus <italic>Stephanoconus</italic> (see additional remarks below for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>bellacoensis</italic> sp. nov.).</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>bellacoensis</italic> Hendricks sp. nov</bold>.</p>
<p>urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:DEAA465A-EED2-4DE4-9185-6D7DD41F8C7F</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g016" ref-type="fig">Fig. 16A-H</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g016" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g016</object-id>
<label>Fig 16</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>bellacoensis</italic> Hendricks sp. nov. (A-H), <italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>mappa</italic> [Lightfoot, 1786] (I), and <italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>archon</italic> Broderip, 1833 (J).</title>
<p>Fossil specimens are from locality stations TU 1422 (Cercado Fm.) and TU 1354 (Gurabo Fm.); modern <italic>C</italic>. <italic>mappa is</italic> from Pigeon Point, Tobago; modern <italic>C</italic>. <italic>archon</italic> is from the Gulf of California, Mexico. (A-E) PRI 66158 (holotype), TU 1422, SL 59.7 mm; (F) PRI 67252 (paratype), TU 1354, SL 76.0 mm; (G-H) PRI 67186 (paratype), TU 1422, SL 12.4 mm; (I) UF 241414, SL 45.5 mm; (J) UF 26040, SL 58.7 mm. (B-D, F-H) are reversed images photographed under UV light. Scale bar to left of (A) is 1 cm and pertains to (A-F, I-J). Scale bar to right of (H) is 1 cm and pertains to (G-H).</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g016" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec089">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Holotype</bold>: PRI 66158 (TU station 1422). <bold>Paratypes</bold>: PRI 67186 (TU station 1422); PRI 67252 (TU station 1354).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec090">
<title>Type locality and horizon</title>
<p>TU 1422: Arroyo Bellaco, Dominican Republic; upper Miocene Cercado Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec091">
<title>Other locality and horizon</title>
<p>TU 1354: Cañada de Zamba, Dominican Republic; lower Pliocene Gurabo Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec092">
<title>Description</title>
<sec id="sec093">
<title>Shell size</title>
<p>Shell moderately large (largest observed specimen, PRI 67252, is 76.0 mm).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec094">
<title>Last whorl</title>
<p>Conical (RD 0.53–0.66, μ = 0.57; PMD 0.88–0.93, μ = 0.91; n = 3); outline slightly convex. Shoulder angulate; smooth in mature specimens. Widest part of shell at shoulder in juvenile specimens, below shoulder in mature specimens. Aperture slightly wider at base than near shoulder. Siphonal notch absent. Weakly beaded spiral threads on anterior half.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec095">
<title>Spire whorls</title>
<p>Spire height high (RSH 0.25–0.31, μ = 0.28; n = 3); outline straight, whorls stepped. Protoconch unknown. Most spire whorls tuberculate (information unavailable on earliest post nuclear whorls; 5 tuberculate whorls preserved on PRI 67252, 7 on PRI 66158), though later whorls are not. Sutural ramp concave, unornamented. Subsutural flexure symmetrical, depth about 3x width.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec096">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Two interacting patterns (one complex, one simple) present; it is not clear which pattern is primary. The more complex pattern consists of an irregular spiral band on the anterior end of the last whorl and a complex posterior pigmentation region composed of diamond-shaped blotches that are linked along their edges or corners to form axial or oblique-axial streaks. The simpler pattern consists of about 20 rows of spiral dots; spaces between dots sometimes appear to be unpigmented. The spiral dots are more closely spaced in regions where they intersect the complex pattern. The two patterns differ in the color of emitted light. Axial streaks on the last whorl sometimes extend onto the sutural ramp.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec097">
<title>Etymology</title>
<p>Named for the type locality, Arroyo Bellaco.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec098">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p><italic>Conus bellacoensis</italic> is similar in shell form—and especially in its complex coloration pattern—to members of the “<italic>Conus cedonulli</italic> Species Group” ([<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], p. 144), which includes the western Atlantic species <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cedonulli</italic> Linnaeus, 1767, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>pseudaurantius</italic> Vink and von Cosel, 1985, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>aurantius</italic> Hwass in Bruguière, 1792, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>mappa</italic> [Lightfoot, 1786] (Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">1F</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g015" ref-type="fig">15J</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g016" ref-type="fig">16I</xref>), and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>curassaviensis</italic> Bruguière, 1792 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The phylogenetic analysis of Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] also recognized the eastern Pacific species <italic>C</italic>. <italic>archon</italic> (Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">1E</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g016" ref-type="fig">16J</xref>) as closely related to three of these species: (<italic>C</italic>. <italic>archon</italic>(<italic>C</italic>. <italic>cedunolli</italic>(<italic>C</italic>. <italic>curassaviensis</italic>,<italic>C</italic>. <italic>mappa</italic>))). Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] assigned these extant species to the subgenus <italic>Stephanoconus</italic>, a designation that is followed here for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>bellacoensis</italic>, based on the hypothesis that it is also a member of this group. A key difference that separates the new species from extant members of this group is its narrower last whorl: the two known adult shells (PRI 66158 and PRI 67252) have relative diameters of 0.53, while other species in the group all have wider last whorls (mean values range from 0.60 to 0.66; [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]). Among Neogene fossils from the Dominican Republic, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>bellacoensis</italic> is most similar to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>sewalli</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 15A-I</xref>), a species that is also hypothesized to be a member of the <italic>Stephanoconus</italic> clade. <italic>Conus bellacoensis</italic> can be differentiated from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>sewalli</italic> by its narrower last whorl and higher spire.</p>
<p><bold>Subgenus <italic>Pyruconus</italic> Olsson, 1967</bold></p>
<p>Type species: <italic>Conus patricius</italic> Hinds, 1843.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Pyruconus</italic>) <italic>recognitus</italic> Guppy, 1867</bold> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g017" ref-type="fig">Fig. 17A-D</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g017" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g017</object-id>
<label>Fig 17</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Pyruconus</italic>) <italic>recognitus</italic> Guppy, 1866 (A-D) and <italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Pyruconus</italic>) <italic>patricius</italic> Hinds, 1843 (E).</title>
<p>Fossil specimens are from locality station TU 1354 (Gurabo Fm.); modern <italic>C</italic>. <italic>patricius</italic> is from Palo Seco, Panama. (A) PRI 67539, SL 33.8 mm; (B) PRI 67538, SL 33.4 mm; (C) PRI 67537, SL 33.4 mm; (D) PRI 66181, SL 32.4 mm; (E) UF 321278–1, SL 60.8 mm. (A-D) are reversed images of specimens photographed under UV light. Scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to all images.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g017" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><italic>Conus solidus</italic> of Sowerby I, 1850 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], p. 45; Guppy, 1866 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], p. 287, pl. 16, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>; not Gmelin, 1791, not Sowerby I, 1841.</p>
<p><italic>Conus recognitus</italic> Guppy, 1867 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], p. 171; Maury, 1917 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], p. 209, pl. 7, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>; Pilsbry, 1921 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], pl. 19, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Lithoconus</italic>) <italic>recognitus</italic> Guppy, Pflug, 1961 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], pl. 18, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g012" ref-type="fig">12</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g015" ref-type="fig">15</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Pyruconus recognitus</italic> (Guppy), Tucker and Tenorio, 2009 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], p. 117.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec099">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Syntype</bold>: NHMUK PI BM G 83970. <bold>Other specimens</bold>: PRI 66181, PRI 67537–67541 (TU station 1354).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec100">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>One pattern present. Pattern consists of a solid, undifferentiated ground pattern that extends over the entire last whorl. The last whorl pattern extends over the shoulder onto the sutural ramp.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec101">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p>The specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>recognitus</italic> illustrated here (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g017" ref-type="fig">Fig. 17A-D</xref>) do fluoresce, but do not show evidence of a distinctive pattern, supporting the description provided above of a solidly pigmented ground pattern. The distinctive shell shape of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>recognitus</italic> separates the species from co-occurring fossil species. <italic>Conus recognitus</italic> is very similar in shell form to the extant eastern Pacific species <italic>C</italic>. <italic>patricius</italic> Hinds, 1843, an association also recognized by Woodring [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. The coloration pattern of <italic>Conus patricius</italic> (e.g., <xref rid="pone.0120924.g017" ref-type="fig">Fig. 17E</xref>) consists of a solid, cream-colored base pattern that sometimes also exhibits subtle spiral and/or axial bands of slightly different color. The patterning of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>patricius</italic> explains the undifferentiated regions of fluorescence shown here in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>recognitus</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g017" ref-type="fig">Fig. 17A-D</xref>).</p>
<p>Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] assigned <italic>C</italic>. <italic>recognitus</italic> to the genus <italic>Pyruconus</italic> Olsson, 1967, which Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] recognized as a subgeneric ranking. This assignment is followed here for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>recognitus</italic> (see remarks for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>haytensis</italic>, which discuss the paraphyletic nature of <italic>Pyruconus</italic> as a genus-level name when applied to the extant species <italic>C</italic>. <italic>fergusoni</italic> Sowerby III, 1873).</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (“<italic>Pyruconus</italic>”) <italic>haytensis</italic> Sowerby I, 1850</bold> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g018" ref-type="fig">Fig. 18</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g018" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g018</object-id>
<label>Fig 18</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (“<italic>Pyruconus</italic>”) <italic>haytensis</italic> Sowerby I, 1850.</title>
<p>All specimens are from locality station TU 1215 (Gurabo Fm.). (A-C) PRI 67552, SL 30.2 mm; (D) PRI 67551, SL 27.9 mm; (E) PRI 67554, SL 21.2 mm; (F) <italic>Conus haytensis</italic>?, PRI 67555, fragment is 33.6 mm in length. All are reversed images of specimens photographed under UV light. Scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to all images.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g018" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><italic>Conus haytensis</italic> Sowerby I, 1850 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], p. 44; Pilsbry, 1921 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], p. 326, pl. 19, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dendroconus</italic>) <italic>haytensis</italic> Sowerby I, Pflug, 1961 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], pl. 16, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec102">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Lectotype</bold>: NHMUK PI BM G83961. <bold>Other specimens</bold>: PRI 66139, PRI 67551–67554, questionably PRI 67555 (TU station 1215).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec103">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Two noninteracting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern consists of 2–3 discontinuous (forming broad axial streaks) or continuous spiral bands. The secondary pattern consists of 14–27 (number increases with shell size) spiral rows of lines. The two patterns differ in the color of emitted light. Sutural ramp with radial blotches that sometimes appear to be extensions of the primary pattern over the shoulder.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec104">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p>In terms of shell characters, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>haytensis</italic> may be easily confused with the fossil species <italic>C</italic>. <italic>sewalli</italic>, but these two species have very different coloration patterns (compare Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g015" ref-type="fig">15</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0120924.g018" ref-type="fig">18</xref>). Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] assigned <italic>C</italic>. <italic>haytensis</italic> to the genus <italic>Pyruconus</italic> Olsson, 1967. Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], however, showed that “<italic>Pyruconus</italic>” is paraphyletic (also see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]), as the two extant species—<italic>C</italic>. <italic>patricius</italic> Hinds, 1843 and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>fergusoni</italic> Sowerby III, 1873, both of which are from the eastern Pacific—assigned to this genus-level grouping by Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] nest in different clades. Nevertheless, Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] assigned both species to <italic>Pyruconus</italic> (ranked at the subgeneric-level) “to avoid the creation of a new subgeneric name” (p. 12). <italic>Conus haytensis</italic> is more similar to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>fergusoni</italic> (e.g., <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.coneshell.net/pages/c_fergusoni.htm" xlink:type="simple">http://www.coneshell.net/pages/c_fergusoni.htm</ext-link>) than to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>patricius</italic> (see the above description of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>recognitus</italic>, a species similar to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>patricius</italic>, as well as the photograph of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>patricius</italic> in <xref rid="pone.0120924.g017" ref-type="fig">Fig. 17A-D</xref>). As <italic>C</italic>. <italic>patricius</italic> is the type species of <italic>Pyruconus</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], <italic>C</italic>. <italic>fergusoni</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>haytensis</italic> should probably be assigned to a different subgenus of cone snails; nevertheless, the paraphyletic subgenus name “<italic>Pyruconus</italic>” is used here for consistency with Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] and Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] until this taxonomic matter can be formally resolved.</p>
<p>Specimen PRI 67555 (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g018" ref-type="fig">Fig. 18F</xref>) may be a fragment of a much larger specimen of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>haytensis</italic> than the other specimens shown here (<italic>C</italic>. <italic>haytensis</italic> is one of the largest species of fossil cone snails known from the Dominican Republic). If so, its secondary coloration pattern shows variation not exhibited by the other, smaller specimens: rows of spiral dots and dashes, with unpigmented regions in-between.</p>
<p><bold>Subgenus <italic>Ductoconus</italic> da Motta, 1991</bold></p>
<p>Type species: <italic>Conus princeps</italic> Linnaeus, 1758.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Ductoconus</italic>) <italic>cashi</italic> Hendricks sp. nov</bold>.</p>
<p>urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:4E5E81F2-9F92-4BD7-AA62-200499FCB5AE</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g019" ref-type="fig">Fig. 19A-J</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g019" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g019</object-id>
<label>Fig 19</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Ductoconus</italic>) <italic>cashi</italic> Hendricks sp. nov. (A-J) and <italic>Conus princeps</italic> Linnaeus, 1758 (K).</title>
<p>Fossil specimens are from locality stations TU 1422 (Cercado Fm.), TU 1215 (Gurabo Fm.), TU 1278 (Gurabo Fm.), and NMB 15848 (Gurabo Fm.); modern <italic>C</italic>. <italic>princeps</italic> is from the Perlas Islands, Panama. (A-F) PRI 66144, TU 1215, SL 22.5 mm; (G) PRI 67166, TU 1422, SL 23.8 mm; (H) PRI 66162, TU 1422, SL 26.2 mm; (I) NMB H18381, NMB 15848, SL 25.0 mm; (J) PRI 66116, TU 1278, SL 18.1 mm; (K) UF 169052–1, SL 52.2 mm. (F-H) are reversed images photographed under UV light. Scale bar to the left of (A) is 1 cm and pertains to (A-B, F-J); (C, E) scale bars are 2 mm; (D) scale bar is 5 mm; (K) scale bar is 1 cm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g019" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec105">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Holotype</bold>: PRI 66144 (TU station 1215). <bold>Paratypes</bold>: PRI 66162 and PRI 67166 (TU station 1422); PRI 66116 (TU station 1278); NMB H18381 (NMB locality 15848).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec106">
<title>Type locality and horizon</title>
<p>TU 1215: Río Gurabo, Dominican Republic; lower Pliocene Gurabo Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec107">
<title>Other localities and horizons</title>
<p>TU 1422: Arroyo Bellaco, Dominican Republic; upper Miocene Cercado Formation. TU1278: “Large arroyo on east side of Río Gurabo just at the ford on Los Quemados-Sabaneta road” (Saunders et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], p. 65); lower Pliocene Gurabo Formation. NMB 15848: Río Gurabo, lower Pliocene Gurabo Formation (see text-<xref rid="pone.0120924.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> in [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]); locality represents a subset of TU 1215.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec108">
<title>Description</title>
<sec id="sec109">
<title>Shell size</title>
<p>Shell moderately small (largest complete observed specimen, PRI 66162, is 26.2 mm; PRI 67166, which is missing its anterior third, is larger).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec110">
<title>Last whorl</title>
<p>Narrowly conical to conical (RD 0.49–0.50, μ = 0.49; PMD 0.85–0.86, μ = 0.86; n = 2); outline convex on posterior half, slightly concave on anterior half, resulting in slightly sigmoidal profile. Shoulder angulate to subangulate; tuberculate. Widest part of shell below shoulder. Aperture uniform in width from base to shoulder. Siphonal notch absent. Spiral threads on anterior third.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec111">
<title>Spire whorls</title>
<p>Spire height moderate (RSH 0.14; n = 2); outline concave to sigmoidal. Protoconch with ca. 2 whorls, diameter 0.9 mm (based on PRI 66144). All postnuclear whorls tuberculate. Sutural ramp sigmoidal, with 2–3 spiral threads. Subsutural flexure slightly asymmetrical, depth about 0.5x width.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec112">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Two noninteracting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern consists of two wide spiral bands that cover most of the anterior and posterior ends of the last whorl, leaving a narrow, unpigmented band in the center. The secondary pattern consists of jagged, non-branching (but sometimes touching) thin axial streaks that in many cases extend from the base to the shoulder. The two patterns differ slightly in the color of emitted light. Sutural ramp with radial streaks that roughly correspond with the shape of the subsutural flexure.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec113">
<title>Etymology</title>
<p>Named in honor of American musician John “Johnny” Cash (1932–2003), otherwise known as “The Man in Black.”</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec114">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p><italic>Conus cashi</italic> is not similar to other DR fossil species, but is similar in shell morphology and especially coloration pattern to the extant eastern Pacific species <italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Ductoconus</italic>) <italic>princeps</italic> Linnaeus, 1758 (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g019" ref-type="fig">Fig. 19K</xref>), suggesting that <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cashi</italic> should also be included with <italic>C</italic>. <italic>princeps</italic> in the subgenus <italic>Ductoconus</italic> da Motta, 1991, which was accepted by Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] found molecular support for the western Atlantic species <italic>C</italic>. <italic>hieroglyphus</italic> Duclos, 1833 being the sister taxon of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>princeps</italic>, but it has a very different shell morphology than <italic>C</italic>. <italic>princeps</italic>.</p>
<p><bold>Subgenus <italic>Dauciconus</italic> Cotton, 1945</bold></p>
<p>Type species: <italic>Conus daucus</italic> Hwass, 1792.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>furvoides</italic> Gabb, 1873</bold> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 20</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g020" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g020</object-id>
<label>Fig 20</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>furvoides</italic> Gabb, 1873.</title>
<p>All specimens are from locality station TU 1354 (Gurabo Fm.). (A-B) PRI 67239, SL 40.8 mm; (C) PRI 67238, SL 36.6 mm; (D-E) PRI 67240, SL 42.3 mm. All are reversed images photographed under UV light. Scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to all images.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g020" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><italic>Conus furvoides</italic> Gabb, 1873 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], p. 232; Maury, 1917 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], p. 206–207, pl. 7, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>; Pilsbry, 1921 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], p. 328, pl. 20, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Dauciconus furvoides</italic> (Gabb), Tucker and Tenorio, 2009 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], p. 89.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec115">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Lectotype</bold>: ANSP 2576. <bold>Other specimens</bold>: PRI 66188, PRI 67238–67241 (TU station 1354).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec116">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Two weakly interacting patterns (one complex, one simple) present; it is not clear which pattern is primary. The more complex pattern consists of axially arranged markings that extend from the base to shoulder and onto the sutural ramp. These markings may also cover broader areas of the last whorl, forming unpigmented axial or diagonal blotches. PRI 67240 (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 20D</xref>) shows evidence of the temporary cessation of the complex pigmentation field (though not necessarily cessation of shell production) in the direction of growth, followed by its later resumption, resulting in oppositely-patterned regions that appear like puzzle pieces that might fit together. The simpler pattern consists of at least 12–17 spiral rows of dots (the extent of this pattern on the anterior third of the last whorl is not known). Interaction between the two coloration patterns occurs when the spiral dots intersect the margins of the axial patterns; this results in the formation of small, triangular shaped blotches. The two patterns do not differ in the color of emitted light. The complex last whorl pattern extends over the shoulder onto the sutural ramp.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec117">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p><italic>Conus furvoides</italic> has cannot be easily confused with co-occurring fossil species. It does, however, shares similarities in shell form with some extant members of the subgenus <italic>Dauciconus</italic> Cotton, 1945 (sensu [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]) (Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] assigned <italic>C</italic>. <italic>furvoides</italic> to <italic>Dauciconus</italic>, although at the genus level). Some specimens of <italic>C</italic>. (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>virgatus</italic> Reeve, 1849, an eastern Pacific species, exhibit the puzzle-piece like arrangement of axial streaks described above (e.g., <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gastropods.com/9/Shell_769.shtml" xlink:type="simple">http://www.gastropods.com/9/Shell_769.shtml</ext-link>), while some specimens of <italic>C</italic>. (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>recurvus</italic> Broderip and Sowerby, 1833—an eastern Pacific species that is the sister taxon of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>virgatus</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]—show evidence of diagonal blotches (e.g., <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.coneshell.net/pages/c_recurvus.htm" xlink:type="simple">http://www.coneshell.net/pages/c_recurvus.htm</ext-link>). Neither <italic>C</italic>. <italic>virgatus</italic>, nor <italic>C</italic>. <italic>recurvus</italic>, however, show evidence of rows of spiral dots on the last whorl, which are observed in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>furvoides</italic>. <italic>Conus furvoides</italic> is also similar in shell shape to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>villepinii</italic> Fischer and Bernardi, 1857, an extant western Atlantic species also assigned by Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] to the subgenus <italic>Dauciconus</italic>. The coloration pattern of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>furvoides</italic>, however, differs substantially from the specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>villepinii</italic> figured by Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]; in particular, the last whorl coloration pattern of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>villepinii</italic>—which consists of two discontinuous spiral bands, resulting in axial streaks—is not present in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>furvoides</italic>.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>planiliratus</italic> Sowerby I, 1850</bold> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g021" ref-type="fig">Fig. 21</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g021" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g021</object-id>
<label>Fig 21</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>planiliratus</italic> Sowerby I, 1850.</title>
<p>Specimens are from locality stations TU 1215 and TU 1354 (both Gurabo Fm.). (A) PRI 67502, TU 1354, SL 24.0 mm; (B-C) PRI 66179, TU 1354, SL 23.4 mm; (D-E) PRI 67504, TU 1354, SL 23.2 mm; (F) PRI 67508, TU 1354, SL 18.9 mm; (G) PRI 67505, TU 1354, SL 22.4 mm; (H) PRI 67503, TU 1354, SL 21.3 mm; (I-J) PRI 67509, TU 1354, SL 25.8 mm; (K) PRI 66146, TU 1215, SL 23.9 mm. All are reversed images photographed under UV light. Scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to all images.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g021" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><italic>Conus planiliratus</italic> Sowerby I, 1850 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], p. 44; Guppy, 1866 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], p. 287, pl. 16, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>; Pilsbry, 1921 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], p. 329–330, pl. 20, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g009" ref-type="fig">9</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Conasprelloides planiliratus</italic> (Sowerby I), Tucker and Tenorio, 2009 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], p. 88.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec118">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Syntypes</bold>: NHMUK PI BM GG 20131–20134. <bold>Other specimens</bold>: PRI 66146, PRI 66151, and PRI 67548 (TU station 1215); PRI 66176, PRI 66179, PRI 67502–67509, questionably PRI 67506 (TU station 1354).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec119">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Two noninteracting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern consists of two solid bands: one on the anterior half of the last whorl, the other on the posterior half, but below the shoulder. The secondary pattern consists of about 17–20 spiral rows of dots (which are often square-shaped) or dashes; these sometimes coalesce just below the shoulder to form short axial streaks. The two patterns differ in the color of emitted light. Sutural ramp with radial blotches; some of these appear to be extensions of the secondary pattern (axial streaks) over the shoulder.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec120">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p><italic>Conus planiliratus</italic> can be distinguished from co-occurring fossil species by the presence of spiral ribs over much of its last whorl, the presence of spiral threads on its sutural ramp, and its distinctive coloration pattern. Among extant western Atlantic species, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>planiliratus</italic> bears strong similarity in shell morphology to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cancellatus</italic> Hwass in Bruguière, 1792 and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>stimpsoni</italic> Dall, 1902, both of which were recently characterized and compared by Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. <italic>Conus planiliratus</italic> differs from both of these species in its coloration pattern, which features a heavily pigmented secondary pattern (spiral rows of dots and dashes); this is not present in either of the extant species. Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] placed <italic>C</italic>. <italic>planiliratus</italic> in the genus <italic>Conasprelloides</italic> Tucker and Tenorio, 2009, which Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] considered synonymous with the subgenus <italic>Dauciconus</italic>. Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] placed both <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cancellatus</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>stimpsoni</italic> in the subgenus <italic>Dauciconus</italic> and this assignment is followed here for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>planiliratus</italic>.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>multiliratus</italic> Böse, 1906</bold> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g022" ref-type="fig">Fig. 22</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g022" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g022</object-id>
<label>Fig 22</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>multiliratus</italic> Böse, 1906.</title>
<p>All specimens are from locality station TU 1215 (Gurabo Fm.). (A-C) PRI 67572, SL 20.2 mm; (D) PRI 66147, SL 18.5 mm; (E) PRI 67577, SL 16.7 mm. All are reversed image of specimens photographed under UV light. Scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to all images.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g022" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><italic>Conus agassizi multiliratus</italic> Böse, 1906 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], p. 49–50, pl. 5, Figs. 34–38.</p>
<p><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Leptoconus</italic>) <italic>multiliratus</italic> Marks, 1951 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], p. 139.</p>
<p><italic>Conus gaza</italic> Johnson and Pilsbry, 1911 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], p. 342–343, pl. 23, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>; Maury, 1917 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], p. 210–211, pl. 7, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g012" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Conasprelloides multiliratus</italic> (Böse), Tucker and Tenorio, 2009 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], p. 88.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec121">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p>PRI 66147, PRI 67572–67577 (TU station 1215); PRI 66174 (TU station 1354).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec122">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Probably two noninteracting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern consists of two continuous spiral bands, one at the base of the shell and one near the midpoint of the last whorl; these are lightly pigmented. The secondary pattern (which requires confirmation in specimens with better preserved patterns) seems to consist of spiral rows of dashes associated with the ribs that cover the last whorl. The two patterns differ slightly in the color of emitted light. Sutural ramp with lightly pigmented radial blotches.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec123">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p>The distinctive, heavily-ribbed shell of <italic>Conus multiliratus</italic> cannot be confused with any co-occurring species. Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] assigned <italic>C</italic>. <italic>multiliratus</italic> to the genus <italic>Conasprelloides</italic>, which Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] recognized as a synonym of the subgenus <italic>Dauciconus</italic>. <italic>Conus multiliratus</italic> is similar in shell shape to the extant western Atlantic species <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cancellatus</italic>, which Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] assigned to <italic>Dauciconus</italic> based on phylogenetic evidence [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Additionally, some specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cancellatus</italic> (e.g., [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], pl. 70, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) have two lightly pigmented spiral bands on the last whorl that are similar to those shown here in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>multiliratus</italic>. An important difference between <italic>C</italic>. <italic>multiliratus</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cancellatus</italic>, however, is that the extinct species lacks spiral ornamentation on the sutural ramp, while it is present in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cancellatus</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>karlschmidti</italic>? Maury, 1917</bold> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g023" ref-type="fig">Fig. 23</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g023" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g023</object-id>
<label>Fig 23</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>karlschmidti</italic>? Maury, 1917.</title>
<p>All specimens are from locality station TU 1215 (Gurabo Fm.). (A-C) PRI 67557, SL 19.1 mm; (D-F) PRI 67562, SL 19.5 mm (shell broken); (G) PRI 66138, SL 27.9 mm; (H) PRI 67561, SL 27.9 mm. All are reversed images photographed under UV light. Scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to all images.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g023" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><italic>Conus karlschmidti</italic> Maury, 1917 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], p. 211–212, pl. 7, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g014" ref-type="fig">Fig. 14</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec124">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p>PRI 66138, PRI 67556–67563 (TU station 1215).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec125">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Two noninteracting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern consists of wavy, sometimes branching axial streaks that extend from the base to shoulder. The secondary pattern consists of two spiral bands that cover the anterior and posterior thirds of the last whorl, exposing the primary pattern in-between; in PRI 67562 (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g023" ref-type="fig">Fig. 23D, F</xref>), the primary pattern is weakly visible beneath the secondary pattern. The two patterns differ in the color of emitted light. Sutural ramp with radial blotches that sometimes appear to be extensions of the primary pattern over the shoulder.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec126">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p>Maury’s [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] type specimen of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>karlschmidti</italic> is missing from the collections of the PRI (L. Skibinski, pers. comm.), so could not be compared with the shells considered here. The general shape of Maury’s figured specimen ([<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], pl. 7, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g014" ref-type="fig">Fig. 14</xref>) and her description, however, closely match the shells tentatively referred here to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>karlschmidti</italic>. The coloration pattern of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>karlschmidti</italic> is very similar to that of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>garrisoni</italic> sp. nov. (see below). <italic>Conus karlschmidti</italic> differs from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>garrisoni</italic>, however, in having far fewer tuberculate spire whorls and having a narrower last whorl. Among extant western Atlantic species, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>karlschmidti</italic> is similar in shell shape and coloration pattern to some specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>amphiurgus</italic> Dall, 1889 (e.g., [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], pl. 60, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g008" ref-type="fig">8</xref>), though seems to lack the spiral rows of dots present in some specimens of the modern species. Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] assigned <italic>C</italic>. <italic>amphiurgus</italic> to the subgenus <italic>Dauciconus</italic>, a designation that is followed here for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>karlschmidti</italic>.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>garrisoni</italic> Hendricks sp. nov</bold>.</p>
<p>urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:17820854-5146-45DA-8035-844D1EFC4DAA</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g024" ref-type="fig">Fig. 24</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g024" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g024</object-id>
<label>Fig 24</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>garrisoni</italic> Hendricks sp. nov.</title>
<p>All specimens are from locality station TU 1422 (Cercado Fm.). (A-F) PRI 66166 (holotype), SL 19.8 mm; (G-H) PRI 67197 (paratype), SL 27.2 mm; (I-J) PRI 67194 (paratype), SL 14.2 mm; (K) PRI 67196 (paratype), SL 20.8 mm. (D-K) are reversed images of specimens photographed under UV light. Scale bar to the left of (A) is 1 cm and pertains to (A, D-K); (B, C) scale bars are 2 mm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g024" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec127">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Holotype</bold>: PRI 66166. <bold>Paratypes</bold>: PRI 67194, PRI 67196–67197. All type specimens are from TU station 1422.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec128">
<title>Type locality and horizon</title>
<p>TU station 1422: Arroyo Bellaco, Dominican Republic; upper Miocene Cercado Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec129">
<title>Description</title>
<sec id="sec130">
<title>Shell size</title>
<p>Shell moderately small (largest observed specimen, PRI 67197, is 27.2 mm).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec131">
<title>Last whorl</title>
<p>Conical (RD 0.66–0.67, μ = 0.66; PMD 0.87–0.92, μ = 0.89; n = 3); outline convex, except at anterior third, which is slightly concave. Shoulder angulate to subangulate, nearly smooth in mature specimens. Widest part of shell at or just below shoulder. Aperture uniform in width from base to shoulder. Siphonal notch absent. Fine spiral threads extending from base to shoulder in smaller specimens, restricted to anterior quarter in larger specimens.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec132">
<title>Spire whorls</title>
<p>Spire height moderate (RSH 0.15–0.22; n = 3); outline straight to slightly sigmoidal. Protoconch multispiral, diameter 0.8 mm (based on PRI 66166). Tubercles present on first 6 postnuclear whorls, diminishing thereafter. Sutural ramp slightly sigmoidal in early whorls, convex in later whorls, ornamentation absent. Subsutural flexure symmetrical, depth about equal to width.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec133">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Two noninteracting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern consists of irregularly shaped and sometimes branching axial blotches that span the last whorl. The secondary pattern consists of two broad spiral bands that cover a majority of the last whorl, but not the center region. The two patterns differ in the color of emitted light. Axial markings associated with the primary pattern extend onto the sutural ramp.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec134">
<title>Etymology</title>
<p>Named in honor of American abolitionist and suffragist William Lloyd Garrison (1805–1879).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec135">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p><italic>Conus garrisoni</italic> is not similar to co-occurring fossil species, but is very similar in shell morphology and coloration pattern to the extant, and highly variable (see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]), western Atlantic species <italic>Conus cardinalis</italic> Hwass in Bruguière, 1792. An important difference appears to be the protoconch, which is multispiral in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>garrisoni</italic>, but paucispiral in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cardinalis</italic> (Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] reported <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cardinalis</italic> to have 1.25–2 protoconch whorls). Tucker and Tenorio (2009) assigned <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cardinalis</italic> to the genus <italic>Purpuriconus</italic> da Motta, 1991, which Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] recognized as synonymous with the subgenus <italic>Dauciconus</italic>. While the phylogenetic context of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cardinalis</italic> has not yet been formally explored, the strong similarity between <italic>C</italic>. <italic>garrisoni</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cardinalis</italic> supports the assignment of the fossil species to this subgenus.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>?) <italic>zambaensis</italic> Hendricks sp. nov</bold>.</p>
<p>urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:72CF869C-1094-4C5A-A5D6-270A923DA706</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 25</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g025" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g025</object-id>
<label>Fig 25</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>?) <italic>zambaensis</italic> Hendricks sp. nov.</title>
<p>All specimens are from locality station TU 1354 (Gurabo Fm.). (A-F) PRI 67488 (holotype), SL 34.8 mm; (G-I) PRI 67491 (paratype), SL 32.5 mm; (J) PRI 66173 (paratype), SL 43.1 mm. (B-D, G-J) are reversed images of specimens photographed under UV light. Scale bar to the left of (A) is 1 cm and pertains to images (A-E, G-J); (F) scale bar is 1 mm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g025" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec136">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Holotype</bold>: PRI 67488. <bold>Paratypes</bold>: PRI 66173, PRI 67489–67501. All type specimens are from TU station 1354.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec137">
<title>Type locality and horizon</title>
<p>TU 1354: Cañada de Zamba, Dominican Republic; lower Pliocene Gurabo Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec138">
<title>Description</title>
<sec id="sec139">
<title>Shell size</title>
<p>Shell medium sized (largest observed specimen, PRI 66173, is 43.2 mm).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec140">
<title>Last whorl</title>
<p>Typically conical, but sometimes ventricosely conical (RD 0.56–0.61; μ = 0.59; PMD 0.84–0.88, μ = 0.86; n = 7); outline convex, except at anterior quarter, which may be slightly concave. Shoulder angulate, smooth. Widest part of shell below shoulder. Aperture slightly wider at base than near shoulder. Siphonal notch absent. Spiral threads on anterior half, diminishing towards shoulder.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec141">
<title>Spire whorls</title>
<p>Spire height low (RSH 0.06–0.09; μ = 0.08); outline typically concave to sigmoidal, sometimes convex; whorls may be stepped. Protoconch diameter ca. 0.7 mm (based on PRI 67488), number of whorls unknown. First 2 postnuclear whorls tuberculate, diminishing thereafter. Sutural ramp flat to slightly sigmoidal, several spiral threads present on all but the last couple of whorls in mature specimens. Subsutural flexure nearly symmetrical, depth about 1.2x width.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec142">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Two weakly interacting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern consists of a nearly solid ground pattern, with the exception of thin band near the middle of the last whorl where this pigmentation is discontinuous, resulting in a band of unpigmented, irregularly shaped blotches. The secondary pattern—visible only on a portion of the ventral surface of PRI 67491 (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 25G</xref>)—consists of at least 12 spiral rows of dots; spaces between these are sometimes unpigmented, including when they intersect the primary pattern (these unpigmented spaces are the evidence that a weak interaction between the two patterns is present). The two patterns differ in the color of emitted light. Sutural ramp with blotches that sometimes correspond with the shape of the subsutural flexure.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec143">
<title>Etymology</title>
<p>Named for the type locality, Cañada de Zamba, Dominican Republic.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec144">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p><italic>Conus zambaensis</italic> is somewhat similar in shell morphology to <italic>Conus franklinae</italic> sp. nov.; for differences separating the two species, see remarks for the latter taxon. The shell shape of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>zambaensis</italic>, as well as the presence of spiral threads covering much of the last whorl, are also reminiscent of the extinct species <italic>Conus miamiensis</italic> Petuch, 1986, which is known from the Plio-Pleistocene of Florida. <italic>Conus miamiensis</italic>, however, has a different coloration pattern (see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]). Among extant taxa, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>daucus</italic> has a shape and coloration pattern that resembles <italic>C</italic>. <italic>zambaensis</italic>. All of the morphometric values reported here for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>zambaensis</italic> (RD, PMD, and RSH) are within the ranges given for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>daucus</italic> by Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Furthermore, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>daucus</italic>—as circumscribed by Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]—also exhibits a solid base color that is interrupted by an unpigmented, narrow band in the middle of the last whorl, as well as spiral rows of dots. One difference between <italic>C</italic>. <italic>zambaensis</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>daucus</italic> is that the fossil species has spire whorls that are often stepped, while this is not typical in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>daucus</italic> (see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]). Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] assigned <italic>C</italic>. <italic>daucus</italic> to the subgenus <italic>Dauciconus</italic>, a designation that is tentatively followed here for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>zambaensis</italic>.</p>
<sec id="sec145">
<title>Subgenus <italic>Spuriconus</italic> Petuch, 2003</title>
<p>Type species: <italic>Conus spurius</italic> Gmelin, 1791.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Spuriconus</italic>) <italic>spurius</italic> Gmelin, 1791</bold> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g026" ref-type="fig">Fig. 26A-F,K</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g026" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g026</object-id>
<label>Fig 26</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Spuriconus</italic>) <italic>spurius</italic> Gmelin, 1791 (A-F, K) and <italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Spuriconus</italic>) <italic>humerosus</italic> Pilsbry, 1921 (G-J).</title>
<p>Fossil specimens are from locality stations TU 1422 (Cercado Fm.), TU 1215 (Gurabo Fm.), and TU 1354 (Gurabo Fm.); modern <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> are from Saint Croix Island, United States Virgin Islands (E-F) and offshore of Columbia, near the Venezuelan border (K). (A) PRI 66178, TU 1354, SL 40.6 mm; (B) PRI 67542, TU 1354, SL 40.2 mm; (C) PRI 67543, TU 1354, SL 32.4 mm; (D) PRI 67544, TU 1354, SL 47.1 mm; (E-F) ANSP 313169, SL 63.3 mm (estimated from digital image); (G) PRI 66140, TU 1215, SL 65.3 mm; (H) PRI 67550, TU 1215, SL 46.9 mm; (I) PRI 66154, TU 1422, SL 59.1 mm; (J) PRI 66177, TU 1354, SL 47.9 mm; (K) ANSP 398448, SL 51.5 mm (estimated from digital image). Scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to all images.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g026" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><italic>Conus spurius</italic> Gmelin, 1791 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], p. 3396; Hendricks, 2009 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], p. 19–21, pl. 3, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g014" ref-type="fig">14</xref>, pl. 4, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g014" ref-type="fig">14</xref>; Kohn, 2014 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], p. 345–357, pl. 97, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g012" ref-type="fig">12</xref>, pl. 98, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g016" ref-type="fig">16</xref>, pl. 99, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g016" ref-type="fig">16</xref>, pl. 100, Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.g017" ref-type="fig">17</xref>.</p>
<p><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Lindaconus</italic>) <italic>spurius</italic> Gmelin, Puillandre et al., 2015 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], p. 10.</p>
<p><italic>Spuriconus spurius</italic> (Gmelin), Petuch, 2003 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>], p. 294; Tucker and Tenorio, 2009 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], p. 121–122.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec146">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p>PRI 66178, PRI 67542–67544 (TU station 1354).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec147">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>One pattern present. Pattern consists of at least 4 spiral rows of heavily pigmented blotches that often coalesce to form axial streaks; these are usually visible in regular light. Sutural ramp with blotches. (Note: this color pattern description applies only to the Dominican fossil <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> studied here.)</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec148">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p>In the Dominican Neogene, <italic>Conus spurius</italic>, an extant species [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], can only be confused with <italic>C</italic>. <italic>humerosus</italic> Pilsbry, 1921 (Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g026" ref-type="fig">26G-J</xref>). <italic>Conus humerosus</italic> was originally described by Pilsbry [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] as a subspecies of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>proteus</italic>, which is a name synonymous with <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> (see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]). <italic>Conus humerosus</italic> is tentatively treated here as a species distinct from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic>; while the two species are consistent in most discrete aspects of shell morphology, their coloration patterns consistently differ, including in sympatry (both species occur at TU station 1354). In particular, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>humerosus</italic> has 5–7 spiral rows of square-shaped spots separated by regions lacking pigmentation. Furthermore, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>humerosus</italic> may have two patterns of shell pigmentation, whereas <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> only has one.</p>
<p>As recently documented by Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], modern <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> show a great deal of variation in their pigmentation pattern. The bold, spirally-arranged axial streaks documented here in Dominican fossil <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> are not known from the modern fauna, though modern individuals do sometimes show blotches that have coalesced to form axial streaks (e.g., <xref rid="pone.0120924.g026" ref-type="fig">Fig. 26E,F</xref>). On the other hand, some modern specimens also show spiral rows of square-shaped spots (e.g., <xref rid="pone.0120924.g026" ref-type="fig">Fig. 26K</xref>) that are more similar to the pattern documented here for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>humerosus</italic> than for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> (importantly, though, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>humerosus</italic> has fewer such rows of spots).</p>
<p><italic>Conus spurius</italic> has a substantial fossil record in tropical America [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] and the southeastern United States [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] commented on the fossil record of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> and noted that the species may “hold the distinction as the Recent species with the longest fossil record in the genus” (p. 356). The presence of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> in the lower Pliocene Gurabo Fm. (TU station 1354) sets a minimum age for the species at ca. 4.9 Ma, though it may extend back to the Miocene based on its reported occurrences in Venezuela [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] and Panama [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p>
<p>This taxon was included in the phylogenetic analysis of Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] and was assigned to the subgenus <italic>Lindaconus</italic> Petuch, 2002 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], the type species of which is <italic>Conus lindae</italic> Petuch, 1987 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. This subgeneric assignment is problematic, however, because the recent systematic revision of Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] recognized <italic>C</italic>. <italic>lindae</italic> as a synonym of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>flavescens</italic> Sowerby I, 1834, a species that Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] assigned to the subgenus <italic>Dauciconus</italic>. Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] assigned <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> to the genus <italic>Spuriconus</italic> Petuch, 2003 and this assignment is followed here, albeit at the subgeneric level.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Spuriconus</italic>) <italic>humerosus</italic> Pilsbry, 1921</bold> [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g026" ref-type="fig">Fig. 26G-J</xref></p>
<p><italic>Conus proteus humerosus</italic> Pilsbry, 1921 [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], p. 332, pl. 21, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec149">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Holotype</bold>: ANSP 2548. <bold>Other specimens</bold>: PRI 66154 (TU station 1422); PRI 66140, PRI 67550 (TU station 1215); PRI 66177 (TU station 1354).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec150">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Two weakly interacting patterns possibly present. The primary (base) pattern might consist of a solid, undifferentiated ground pattern that extends over the entire shell. The secondary pattern consists of 5–7 spiral rows of heavily pigmented, square-shaped spots; these are usually visible in regular light. Interaction between the two patterns occurs when the spiral spots intersect the base pattern, resulting in unpigmented spaces between the spiral dots (these unpigmented spaces are the evidence that a solid ground pattern may be present). The two patterns differ in the color of emitted light. Sutural ramp with blotches.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec151">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p>Among Dominican cone snail fossils, <italic>Conus humerosus</italic> can only be confused with <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> Gmelin, 1791; see remarks associated with <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> for a comparison between the two forms. Additional work will be required to determine whether <italic>C</italic>. <italic>humerosus</italic> is truly a distinct species from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> (as suggested here), or whether it is a variation of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> (as suggested first by Pilsbry [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], who described it as a subspecies of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>proteus</italic>, a synonym of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic>). Given its close association with <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>humerosus</italic> is also assigned here to the subgenus <italic>Spuriconus</italic>.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Spuriconus</italic>?) <italic>kaesleri</italic> Hendricks sp. nov</bold>.</p>
<p>urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:11665A29-6D03-440E-82FE-E3515B7D7808</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g027" ref-type="fig">Fig. 27</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g027" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g027</object-id>
<label>Fig 27</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Spuriconus</italic>?) <italic>kaesleri</italic> Hendricks sp. nov.</title>
<p>All specimens are from locality station TU 1354 (Gurabo Fm.). (A-D) PRI 66185 (holotype), SL 22.6 mm; (E) PRI 67668 (paratype), SL 18.8 mm; (F) PRI 67669 (paratype), SL 21.2 mm; (G) PRI 67667 (paratype), SL 28.5 mm; (H-J) PRI 67666 (paratype), SL 38.7 mm; (K) PRI 67670 (paratype), SL 46.5 mm. (B, D-K) are reversed images of specimens photographed under UV light. Scale bar to the left of (A) is 1 cm and pertains to (A-B, D-K); (C) scale bar is 1 cm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g027" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec152">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Holotype</bold>: PRI 66185. <bold>Paratypes</bold>: PRI 67666–67671. All type specimens are from TU station 1354.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec153">
<title>Type locality and horizon</title>
<p>TU 1354: Cañada de Zamba, Dominican Republic; lower Pliocene Gurabo Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec154">
<title>Description</title>
<sec id="sec155">
<title>Shell size</title>
<p>Shell medium sized (largest observed specimen, PRI 67670, is 46.5 mm).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec156">
<title>Last whorl</title>
<p>Typically conical or broadly conical, but sometimes ventricosely conical (RD 0.66–0.72, μ = 0.69; PMD 0.83–0.89, μ = 0.87; n = 5); outline convex, except at anterior quarter, which may be slightly concave. Shoulder subangulate, smooth. Widest part of shell below shoulder. Aperture uniform in width from base to shoulder. Siphonal notch absent. Spiral threads, which are often beaded, on anterior half, diminishing towards shoulder.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec157">
<title>Spire whorls</title>
<p>Spire height low to moderate (RSH 0.09–0.14; μ = 0.11, n = 5); outline concave to slightly sigmoidal. Protoconch unknown. Early postnuclear whorls unknown; tubercles absent from preserved whorls. Sutural ramp sigmoidal, unornamented. Subsutural flexure asymmetrical, depth about 0.9x width.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec158">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>In most specimens, two noninteracting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern consists of 2–4 discontinuous spiral bands. The secondary pattern consists of about 20–40 spiral rows of dots or dashes; spaces between these are sometimes unpigmented. The two patterns differ slightly in the color of emitted light. Sutural ramp with radial blotches that sometimes correspond with the shape of the subsutural flexure. One eroded specimen—PRI 67670—shows a different coloration pattern: its last whorl is covered in a network of small, chevron-shaped markings (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g027" ref-type="fig">Fig. 27K</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec159">
<title>Etymology</title>
<p>Named in honor of University of Kansas paleontologist Roger L. Kaesler (1937–2007).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec160">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p>Among other Neogene cone snail fossils from the Dominican Republic, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>kaesleri</italic> is similar to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>lombardii</italic> sp. nov. (see below) and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> Gmelin, 1791 (see above), which is an extant species. All three species have somewhat similar shell shapes and lack ornamentation on their sutural ramps. The coloration pattern of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic>, however, is very different from either of the newly described species, both of which have numerous spiral rows of dots and dashes on their last whorls. <italic>Conus kaesleri</italic> (which is only known from the Gurabo Fm.) and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>lombardii</italic> (which is only known from the Cercado Fm.) are not known to occur together, but are likely closely related. Several features separate the two species, however. First, the width of the aperture is uniform from the base to the shoulder in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>kaesleri</italic>, but is slightly wider near the base in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>lombardii</italic>. Second, specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>kaesleri</italic> tend to have lower spires (average RSH is 0.11) than specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>lombardii</italic> (average RSH is 0.17). Finally, the coloration patterns vary slightly, as the discontinuous spiral bands present in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>kaesleri</italic> are absent in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>lombardii</italic>. Interestingly, the same networked, chevron-like pattern described above for the eroded specimen PRI 67670 is also present on an eroded specimen of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>lombardii</italic> (PRI 67213). This suggests that both species may have had an additional level of coloration patterning that was not expressed at the surface of the last whorl of the shell.</p>
<p>Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] assigned <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> to the subgenus <italic>Lindaconus</italic>, but it is here assigned to the subgenus <italic>Spuriconus</italic> (see remarks for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic>). Given their strong similarities to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>kaesleri</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>lombardii</italic> are tentatively also assigned to <italic>Spuriconus</italic>.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Spuriconus</italic>?) <italic>lombardii</italic> Hendricks sp. nov</bold>.</p>
<p>urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8BD8086D-09BB-4D38-BD3D-DCADEEDCC9F6</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g028" ref-type="fig">Fig. 28</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g028" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g028</object-id>
<label>Fig 28</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Spuriconus</italic>?) <italic>lombardii</italic> Hendricks sp. nov.</title>
<p>All specimens are from locality station TU 1422 (Cercado Fm.). (A-E) PRI 67207 (holotype), SL 24.7 mm; (F) PRI 66165 (paratype), SL 27.4 mm; (G) PRI 67213 (paratype), SL 23.7 mm; (H-I) PRI 67218 (paratype), SL 20.5 mm; (J-K) PRI 67217 (paratype), SL 17.9 mm. (C-K) are reversed images of specimens photographed under UV light. Scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to all images.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g028" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec161">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Holotype</bold>: PRI 67207. <bold>Paratypes</bold>: PRI 66165, PRI 67189, 67208–67224. All type specimens are from TU station 1422.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec162">
<title>Type locality and horizon</title>
<p>TU 1422: Arroyo Bellaco, Dominican Republic; upper Miocene Cercado Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec163">
<title>Description</title>
<sec id="sec164">
<title>Shell size</title>
<p>Shell moderately small (largest observed specimen, PRI 67215, is 29.5 mm; this specimen is slightly damaged).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec165">
<title>Last whorl</title>
<p>Typically conical, but sometimes ventricosely conical (RD 0.65–0.70, μ = 0.67; PMD 0.83–0.90, μ = 0.88; n = 11); outline slightly convex. Shoulder angulate, smooth. Widest part of shell just below shoulder. Aperture slightly wider at base than near shoulder. Siphonal notch absent. Spiral threads, which are often beaded, on anterior half, diminishing towards shoulder.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec166">
<title>Spire whorls</title>
<p>Spire height moderate (RSH 0.14–0.20, μ = 0.17; n = 11); outline straight to slightly concave. Protoconch unknown. One specimen (PRI 67215) shows possible evidence of one tuberculate postnuclear whorl; tubercles otherwise absent from all spire whorls. Sutural ramp sigmoidal, unornamented. Subsutural flexure asymmetrical; depth about 1.7–2x width.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec167">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>Two noninteracting patterns present. The primary (base) pattern, partially exposed on eroded posterior dorsal surface of last whorl on PRI 67213 (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g028" ref-type="fig">Fig. 28G</xref>), consists of a network of small, chevron-shaped markings. The secondary pattern consists of 27–41 (number increases with shell size) rows of spiral dots or dashes extending from base to shoulder; the dashes are often concentrated, forming several false spiral bands. The two patterns differ in the color of emitted light. Sutural ramp with radial blotches; PRI 67213 suggests that these are extensions over the shoulder of the primary pattern on the last whorl and hence are the only features of the primary pattern that are typically visible on most shells.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec168">
<title>Etymology</title>
<p>Named in honor of Vincent Lombardi (1913–1970), former coach of the Green Bay Packers who led the team to victory in Super Bowl I and II.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec169">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p><italic>Conus lombardii</italic> is similar to two other fossil species from the Neogene of the Dominican Republic: <italic>C</italic>. <italic>kaesleri</italic> sp. nov. and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic> Gmelin, 1791. See remarks associated with <italic>C</italic>. <italic>kaesleri</italic> for important differences that separate these three species, as well as justification for the tentative placement of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>lombardii</italic> in the subgenus <italic>Spuriconus</italic>.</p>
<p><bold>Subgenus <italic>Lautoconus</italic> Monterosato, 1923</bold></p>
<p>Type species: <italic>Conus ventricosus</italic> Gmelin, 1791.</p>
<p><bold><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Lautoconus</italic>?) <italic>carlottae</italic> Hendricks sp. nov</bold>.</p>
<p>urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BD5518E2-C191–4985-A736-AC17AF0243EC</p>
<p><xref rid="pone.0120924.g029" ref-type="fig">Fig. 29</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref></p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g029" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g029</object-id>
<label>Fig 29</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Lautoconus</italic>?) <italic>carlottae</italic> Hendricks sp. nov.</title>
<p>Specimens are from locality stations TU 1422 (Cercado Fm.) and TU 1354 (Gurabo Fm.). (A-E) PRI 66199 (holotype), TU 1354, SL 33.0 mm; (F-G) PRI 67154 (paratype), TU 1354, SL 29.7 mm; (H-I) PRI 66161 (paratype), TU 1422, SL 40.2 mm; (J) PRI 66198 (paratype), TU 1422, SL 27.8 mm. (D-J) are reversed images of specimens photographed under UV light. Scale bar to left of (A) is 1 cm and pertains to images (A-H, J); note that (I) is a magnified view of one of the pigmented spots on (H).</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g029" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec170">
<title>Material examined</title>
<p><bold>Holotype</bold>: PRI 66199 (TU station 1354). <bold>Paratypes</bold>: PRI 66161 and 66198 (TU station 1422); PRI 66200–66201 and PRI 67154–67163 (TU station 1354).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec171">
<title>Type locality and horizon</title>
<p>TU 1354: Cañada de Zamba, Dominican Republic; lower Pliocene Gurabo Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec172">
<title>Other locality and horizon</title>
<p>TU 1422: Arroyo Bellaco, Dominican Republic; upper Miocene Cercado Formation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec173">
<title>Description</title>
<sec id="sec174">
<title>Shell size</title>
<p>Shell medium sized (largest observed specimen, PRI 66161, is 40.2 mm).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec175">
<title>Last whorl</title>
<p>Ventricosely conical (RD 0.65–0.69, μ = 0.66; PMD 0.79–0.84, μ = 0.81; n = 10); outline convex. Shoulder rounded, smooth. Widest part of shell below shoulder. Aperture slightly wider at base than near shoulder. Siphonal notch absent; anterior-most end of lip extends beyond columella. Broad and anteriorly sloping spiral ribs on anterior half that diminish toward the shoulder.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec176">
<title>Spire whorls</title>
<p>Spire height low to moderate (RSH = 0.10–0.18, μ = 0.12; n = 10); outline sigmoidal. Protoconch unknown. Tubercles absent from all spire whorls. Sutural ramp flat in early whorls, convex in later whorls, with several very fine spiral grooves (see PRI 66199); one specimen (PRI 67159) shows evidence of two spiral threads on the earliest postnuclear whorls. In later whorls, the intersection of the sutural ramp with the previous whorl forms a channel along the suture. Subsutural flexure asymmetrical, depth 1–1.5x width.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec177">
<title>Coloration pattern</title>
<p>One pattern present. Pattern consists of round- to teardrop-shaped spots that are situated in a loosely hexagonal packing arrangement over the entirety of the last whorl. The spots are ringed—most prominently on their abaxial sides—by fluorescing regions that differ in emitted wavelength from the enclosed spots (see <xref rid="pone.0120924.g029" ref-type="fig">Fig. 29I</xref>). The last whorl pattern extends over the shoulder onto the sutural ramp.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec178">
<title>Etymology</title>
<p>Named for Carlotta Maury (1874–1938) in honor of her important contributions to paleontology, particularly her work on Neogene mollusks from the Dominican Republic [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. For a biography of Maury’s life, see the recent work by Arnold [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. (Note: Finlay [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] honored Maury with the nomen novum <italic>C</italic>. <italic>mauryi</italic> to replace the occupied name <italic>C</italic>. <italic>ornatus</italic> (Röding, 1798), which Maury [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] applied to a very different species from the Dominican Republic.)</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec179">
<title>Remarks</title>
<p>The distinctive shell coloration pattern exhibited by <italic>C</italic>. <italic>carlottae</italic> is unknown among modern cones snails. In overall shell form, however, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>carlottae</italic> bears resemblance to some of the extant species that Tucker and Tenorio [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] assigned to the genus <italic>Varioconus</italic> da Motta, 1991 and that Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] attributed to the subgenus <italic>Lautoconus</italic> Monterosato, 1923; today these species occur along the west coast of Africa. The extinct species <italic>Conus yaquensis</italic> Gabb, 1873 (e.g., <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://neogeneatlas.org/species/conus-yaquensis-2/" xlink:type="simple">http://neogeneatlas.org/species/conus-yaquensis-2/</ext-link>), known from the upper Pliocene Tamiami Fm. of Florida [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], is somewhat similar in shell morphology, but has the opposite coloration pattern: a net-like reticulated pattern that forms unpigmented dots. The pattern of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>yaquensis</italic> is similar to that of some specimens of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>mercator</italic> Linnaeus, 1758 (e.g., <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.coneshell.net/Pages/c_mercator.htm" xlink:type="simple">http://www.coneshell.net/Pages/c_mercator.htm</ext-link>), an extant species assigned by Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] to the subgenus <italic>Lautoconus</italic>. This subgeneric assignment is tentatively followed here for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>carlottae</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec180">
<title>Additional Forms</title>
<p>While most of the specimens from TU stations 1422, 1215, and 1354 could be assigned to either previously described species or definitively recognized as the new species described herein, 34 specimens remain taxonomically unassigned. In some cases, the poor preservational states of the specimens prevent them from being further studied. Many of the specimens, however, are well preserved and may represent additional undescribed diversity. They were not described here, however, because they are either currently represented by fewer than three known specimens (the threshold used in this study; see above) or could potentially be juvenile forms of taxa that have already been described (Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] also encountered this problem and discussed it on p. 382). Nevertheless, those that have well preserved coloration patterns are figured here (Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120924.g030" ref-type="fig">30</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.g031" ref-type="fig">31</xref>), but are not further described or remarked upon at this time.</p>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g030" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g030</object-id>
<label>Fig 30</label>
<caption>
<title>Unidentified Conidae spp.</title>
<p>Specimens are from locality stations TU 1422 (Cercado Fm.), TU 1215 (Gurabo Fm.), and TU 1354 (Gurabo Fm.). (A) Conidae sp. 1, PRI 66169, TU 1422, SL 30.5 mm; (B-C) Conidae sp. 2, PRI 66186, TU 1354, SL 26.6 mm; (D-E) Conidae sp. 3, PRI 67243, TU 1354, SL 29.2 mm; (F-H) Conidae sp. 4, PRI 67566, TU 1215, SL 16.3 mm; (I-J) Conidae sp. 5, PRI 67234, TU 1422, SL 11.8 mm; (K-L) Conidae sp. 6, PRI 67233, TU 1422, SL 14.1 mm; (M-N) Conidae sp. 7, PRI 66167, TU 1422, SL 11.9 mm; (O) Conidae sp. 8, PRI 67571, TU 1215, SL 14.3 mm; (P-R) Conidae sp. 9, PRI 66149, TU 1215, SL 18.8 mm; (S-U) Conidae sp. 10, PRI 66145, TU 1215, SL 17.4 mm. All are reversed images of specimens photographed under UV light. Scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to all images.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g030" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<fig id="pone.0120924.g031" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g031</object-id>
<label>Fig 31</label>
<caption>
<title>Unidentified Conidae spp.</title>
<p>Specimens are from locality station TU 1354 (Gurabo Fm.). (A-B) Conidae sp. 11, PRI 67253, SL 76.4 mm; (C) Conidae sp. 12, PRI 66172, MD 68.2 mm (only spire is preserved). All are reversed images of specimens photographed under UV light. Scale bar is 1 cm and pertains to all images.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.g031" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec181" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The three coral reef-associated fossil assemblages considered here (TU stations 1422, 1215, and 1354) collectively include a minimum of 28 cone snail species, 13 of which had not been previously described (<xref rid="pone.0120924.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). To put this number in perspective, Kohn’s [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] recent systematic revision of extant cone snails from the southeastern United States and Caribbean recognized a total of 53 valid species (from a pool of 263 available names) and Hendricks [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] recognized 23 total fossil species from the Plio-Pleistocene of the southeastern United States. It is not yet known how many total species of cone snails occur in the Neogene fossil record of the Dominican Republic, but many previously described species were not observed in the three assemblages studied here, suggesting that the total diversity of the fauna—which spans the late Miocene to early Pliocene (6.6-3.5 Ma; McNeill et al., 2012)—may significantly exceed the 28 species documented here (nearly 50 species names have been applied to the fauna in the published literature).</p>
<p>Alan Kohn and his colleagues have extensively studied the community ecology of cone snails on modern Indo-Pacific coral reefs (e.g., [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]). This study allows comparisons to be made between cone snail diversity patterns on modern and fossil coral reef systems for the first time. Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] showed that modern Indo-Pacific reefs support an average of 13.7 cone snail species (range 9–24 species), though a later work [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>] documented 36 co-occurring species at a reef off the coast of Papua New Guinea. The minimum number of species at TU stations 1422, 1215, and 1354 ranged from 14–16 (<xref rid="pone.0120924.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), values that are remarkably consistent with Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. It is worth noting, however, that the fossil reef localities each represent a much greater amount of time (e.g., ca. 0.6 My in the case of TU station 1215), so the number of species that may have been co-existing on each reef during any given period of time may have been less.</p>
<p>All of the 28 species documented from TU stations 1422, 1215, and 1354 include at least one specimen that exhibits a preserved coloration pattern when illuminated by UV light. The great diversity of these revealed coloration patterns—especially the similarities they share with extant species—allow most to be assigned to particular cone snail clades [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], pending their inclusion in an explicit phylogenetic analysis. In total, the 28 species were assigned (or tentatively assigned) to three major clades of cone snails and many subclades: <italic>Profundiconus</italic> (1 species), <italic>Conasprella</italic> (5 species assigned to at least 2 subgenera), and <italic>Conus</italic> (22 species assigned to at least 7 subgenera). The Dominican Neogene cone snail fauna can therefore be considered to be phylogenetically diverse, which has also been demonstrated for the extant western Atlantic fauna [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>].</p>
<p>Presuming that these phylogenetic assignments are correct, they provide useful information about the minimum ages of the clades to which these fossil species may belong and thus have the potential to serve as useful calibration points in future molecular clock-based estimates of the divergence times of different cone snail lineages. As just one example, Duda and Kohn [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] estimated that <italic>Conasprella tornata</italic> diverged from the clade that includes <italic>C</italic>. <italic>mahogani</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>ximenes</italic> about 3 Ma. The newly described fossil species <italic>Conasprella ageri</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0120924.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8A-P</xref>) was likely a close relative of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>tornata</italic> and occurs abundantly at TU station 1354, which is estimated to have an age of ca. 4.9 Ma. If correct, this extends the age of clade (<italic>C</italic>. <italic>tornata</italic>(<italic>C</italic>. <italic>mahogani</italic>,<italic>C</italic>. <italic>ximenes</italic>)) back to at least 4.9 Ma, and perhaps back to at least 6.0 Ma if the two shells from TU station 1422 that are questionably assigned to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>ageri</italic> are indeed that species. <xref rid="pone.0120924.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> summarizes the implied minimum ages of 17 extant species lineages and clades based on the fossil records of DR Neogene cone snails that are hypothesized to be close relatives (see remarks associated with individual fossil species for justification).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0120924.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Minimum ages of clades implied by the fossil record of Dominican Neogene cone snail fossils.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0120924.t002g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dominican Fossil Species</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Similar Extant Species</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum Age of Clade</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Dalliconus</italic>) cf. <italic>sauros</italic> (Garcia, 2006)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C</italic>. <italic>sauros*</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 Ma (TU 1215)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Ximeniconus</italic>) <italic>ageri</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>C</italic>. <italic>tornata</italic>(<italic>C</italic>. <italic>mahogani</italic>,<italic>C</italic>. <italic>ximenes</italic>))</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9 Ma (TU 1354)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conasprella</italic> (<italic>Ximeniconus</italic>) <italic>cercadensis</italic> (Maury, 1917) and <italic>C</italic>. (<italic>X</italic>.) <italic>kitteredgei</italic> (Maury, 1917)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>C</italic>. <italic>perplexa</italic>,<italic>C</italic>. <italic>puncticulata</italic>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 Ma (TU 1422)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conasprella stenostoma</italic> (Sowerby I, 1850)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C</italic>. <italic>delessertii</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 Ma (TU 1215)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> ("<italic>Pyruconus</italic>") <italic>haytensis</italic> Sowerby I, 1850</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C</italic>. <italic>fergusoni</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 Ma (TU 1215)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Atlanticonus</italic>?) <italic>olssoni</italic> Maury, 1917 and <italic>C</italic>. (<italic>A</italic>.?) <italic>franklinae</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C</italic>. <italic>granulatus*</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 Ma (TU 1422)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>?) <italic>zambaensis</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>C</italic>. <italic>richardbinghami</italic>(<italic>C</italic>. <italic>daucus</italic>,<italic>C</italic>. <italic>jacarusoi</italic>))</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9 Ma (TU 1354)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>furvoides</italic> Gabb, 1873</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>C</italic>. <italic>vergatus</italic>,<italic>C</italic>. <italic>recurvus</italic>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9 Ma (TU 1354)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>garrisoni</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C</italic>. <italic>cardinalis*</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 Ma (TU 1422)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>karlschmidti</italic>? Maury, 1917</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>C</italic>. <italic>amphiurgus</italic>,<italic>C</italic>. <italic>villepinii</italic>)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 Ma (TU 1215)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Dauciconus</italic>) <italic>multiliratus</italic> Böse, 1906 and <italic>C</italic>. (<italic>D</italic>.) <italic>planiliratus</italic> Sowerby I, 1850</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C</italic>. <italic>cancellatus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 Ma (TU 1215)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Ductoconus</italic>) <italic>cashi</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C</italic>. <italic>princeps</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 Ma (TU 1422)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Lautoconus</italic>?) <italic>carlottae</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C</italic>. <italic>mercator</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 Ma (TU 1422)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Pyruconus</italic>) <italic>recognitus</italic> Guppy, 1866</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C</italic>. <italic>patricius</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9 Ma (TU 1354)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Spuriconus</italic>) <italic>spurius</italic> Gmelin, 1791, <italic>C</italic>. (<italic>S</italic>.) <italic>humerosus</italic> Pilsbry, 1921, <italic>C</italic>. (<italic>S</italic>.?) <italic>kaesleri</italic> sp. nov., and <italic>C</italic>. (<italic>S</italic>.?) <italic>lombardii</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C</italic>. <italic>spurius</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 Ma (TU 1422)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>gouldi</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>C</italic>. <italic>regius</italic>(<italic>C</italic>. <italic>bartschi</italic>,<italic>C</italic>. <italic>brunneus</italic>))</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 Ma (TU 1422)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus</italic> (<italic>Stephanoconus</italic>) <italic>sewalli</italic> Maury, 1917 and <italic>C</italic>. (<italic>S</italic>.) <italic>bellacoensis</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>C</italic>. <italic>archon</italic>(<italic>C</italic>. <italic>cedonulli</italic>(<italic>C</italic>. <italic>curassaviensis</italic>,<italic>C</italic>. <italic>mappa</italic>)))</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 Ma (TU 1422)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus anningae</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus lyelli</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conus symmetricus</italic> Sowerby I, 1850</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Profundiconus</italic>? <italic>hennigi</italic> sp. nov.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p>See remarks associated with individual fossil species for similarities shared with extant taxa. Parenthetical notation reflects the hypothesis of species relationships published by Puillandre et al. [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]; extant species marked by an asterisk were not included in that study. Clade ages based on minimum ages of the TU locality stations studied here; for listed groups containing more than one fossil species, the oldest taxon was used to set the date (see <xref rid="pone.0120924.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Finally, several of the fossil species provide some interesting biogeographical implications for understanding the regional development of the modern western Atlantic cone snail fauna. Three extant eastern Pacific species, <italic>Conasprella tornata</italic>, <italic>Conus patricius</italic>, and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>princeps</italic> appear much more closely related to three extinct Dominican species than they do to extant western Atlantic species; respectively, these fossil species are <italic>Conasprella ageri</italic>, <italic>Conus recognitus</italic>, and <italic>Conus cashi</italic>. The three extant eastern Pacific species therefore provide clear examples of what Woodring [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] characterized as paciphiles: groups that were once widespread in tropical America, but that now persist only in the eastern Pacific (it should be noted that Woodring [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] himself characterized <italic>Conus patricius</italic> as a paciphilic species). Further study of the fossil records of these three Dominican species may help to resolve the timing of their extinction relative to the final closure of the Central American Seaway about 3 Ma [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], which may have played a role in their demise.</p>
<p>In the introduction to his recent monograph on western Atlantic cone snails, Alan Kohn noted that “the geologic record of the genus [<italic>Conus</italic>] still remains too poorly known to provide useful insights into the evolution of the region’s modern <italic>Conus</italic> fauna” ([<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], p. 1). This statement is, unfortunately, quite true. Our understanding of the phylogenetic contexts of most of the fossil species from this region relative to the modern fauna is nearly non-existent, yet is key to attaining a comprehensive understanding of the evolution of this remarkable clade of gastropods. One way of achieving this goal is through “total evidence” phylogenetic analyses that combine morphological data from extant and fossil species with molecular sequence data from extant species (e.g., [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120924.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]). The revealed coloration patterns documented here provide an additional character suite that will likely be useful for placing fossil cone snails into phylogenies (also see [<xref rid="pone.0120924.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]). This approach—combined with the exceptional Neogene fossil record of the Dominican Republic, as well as other regional fossil deposits—has the potential to provide a detailed understanding of the evolutionary and biogeographic development of the modern western Atlantic cone snail fauna, and more generally illuminate the history of a diverse marine clade and its members’ responses to environmental changes over millions of years.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec182">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0120924.s001" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Specimens observed.</title>
<p>List of PRI specimens observed from locality stations TU 1422, 1215, and 1354.</p>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0120924.s002" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0120924.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Measurement data for newly described species.</title>
<p>SL, shell length; MD, maximum diameter; AH, aperture height; HMD, height of maximum diameter; RD, relative diameter; PMD, position of maximum diameter; and RSH, relative spire height. Asterisk (*) indicates measurement values that are affected by slightly damaged shells.</p>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The following individuals and museums are kindly thanked for providing access to specimens: J. Nagel-Myers, L. Skibinski and G. Dietl, Paleontological Research Institution; J. Slapcinski, Florida Museum of Natural History; W. Etter and O. Schmidt, Naturhistorisches Museum Basel; P. Callomon, Academy of Natural Sciences of Drexel University; J. Todd, Natural History Museum, London; and E. Kools and C. Piotrowski, California Academy of Sciences. Much of this work was completed at Ohio University (OU) during a fall 2014 sabbatical visit; the author thanks the Department of Geology at OU for providing office work space and other resources, as well as E. Hermsen and A. Stigall, who both provided access to laboratory facilities and equipment at OU. Finally, B. Landau, academic editor G. Vermeij, and an anonymous reviewer are thanked for their very helpful comments, which improved the manuscript.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puillandre</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchet</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duda</surname> <given-names>TFJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kauferstein</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name> <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Molecular phylogeny and evolution of the cone snails (Gastropoda, Conoidea)</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>78C</volume>: <fpage>290</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puillandre</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duda</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olivera</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchet</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>One, four or 100 genera? A new classification of the cone snails</article-title>. <source>J Molluscan Stud</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>81</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olivera</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Showers</surname> <given-names>Corneli P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watkins</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fedosov</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biodiversity of cone snails and other venomous marine gastropods: evolutionary success through neuropharmacology</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Anim Biosci</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>487</fpage>–<lpage>513</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev-animal-022513-114124" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev-animal-022513-114124</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25384153</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meinhardt</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The algorithmic beauty of sea shells</chapter-title>. <edition>3rd ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>; <year>2003</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matzke</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ermentrout</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vendetti</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slatkin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Evolution of patterns on <italic>Conus</italic> shells</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>109</volume>: <fpage>E234</fpage>–<lpage>E241</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1119859109" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1119859109</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22219366</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Röckel</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Korn</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Manual of the living Conidae</chapter-title>. Volume <volume>1</volume>: <source>Indo-Pacific Region</source>. <publisher-loc>Grillparzerstr, Germany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Verlag Christa Hemmen</publisher-name>; <year>1995</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The cone shells of Florida: an illustrated key and a review of the recent species</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Wellington, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MdM Publishing</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>. <chapter-title><italic>Conus</italic> of the southeastern United States and Caribbean</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Tempo and mode of evolution in Conidae</article-title>. <source>Malacologia</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendricks</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Portell</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Late Eocene <italic>Conus</italic> (Neogastropoda: Conidae) from Florida, USA</article-title>. <source>Nautilus</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>122</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendricks</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Genus <italic>Conus</italic> (Mollusca: Neogastropoda) in the Plio-Pleistocene of the Southeastern United States</article-title>. <source>Bull Am Paleontol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>375</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>180</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsson</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Some Tertiary mollusks from South Florida and the Caribbean</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Paleontological Research Institution</publisher-name>; <year>1967</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krueger</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name>. <article-title>The use of ultraviolet light in the study of fossil shells</article-title>. <source>Curator</source>. <year>1974</year>;<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vokes</surname> <given-names>HE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vokes</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Variation in the genus <italic>Orthaulax</italic> (Mollusca: Gastropoda)</article-title>. <source>Tulane Stud Geol Paleontol</source>. <year>1968</year>;<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kase</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kitao</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aguilar</surname> <given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kurihara</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pandita</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reconstruction of color markings in Vicarya, a Miocene potamidid gastropod (Mollusca) from SE Asia and Japan</article-title>. <source>Paleontol Res</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>345</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caze</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merle</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pacaud</surname> <given-names>J-M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saint Martin</surname> <given-names>J-P</given-names></name>. <article-title>First systematic study using the variability of the residual colour patterns: the case of the Paleogene Seraphsidae (Mollusca, Gastropoda, Stromboidea)</article-title>. <source>Geodiversitas</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>477</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caze</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merle</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meur</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pacaud</surname> <given-names>J-M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ledon</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saint Martin</surname> <given-names>J-P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Taxonomic implications of the residual colour patterns of ampullinid gastropods and their contribution to the discrimination from naticids</article-title>. <source>Acta Palaeontol Pol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>347</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoerle</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>. <article-title>The genus <italic>Conus</italic> (Mollusca: Gastropoda) from the Alum Bluff Group of northwestern Florida</article-title>. <source>Tulane Stud Geol Paleontol</source>. <year>1976</year>;<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitt</surname> <given-names>WD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pitt</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ultra-violet light as a useful tool for identifying fossil mollusks, with examples from the Gatun Formation, Panama</article-title>. <source>Tulane Stud Geol Paleontol</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caze</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merle</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saint Martin</surname> <given-names>J-P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pacaud</surname> <given-names>J-M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Contribution of residual colour patterns to the species characterization of Caenozoic molluscs (Gastropoda, Bivalvia)</article-title>. <source>Comptes Rendus Palevol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landau</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harzhauser</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Islamoglu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marques da Silva</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Systematics and palaeobiogeography of the gastropods of the middle Miocene (Serravallian) Karaman Basin</article-title>. <source>Cainozoic Res</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>11–13</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>584</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Comfort</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The pigmentation of molluscan shells</article-title>. <source>Biol Rev Camb Philos Soc</source>. <year>1951</year>;<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>285</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedegaard</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bardeau</surname> <given-names>J-F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chateigner</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molluscan shell pigments: an in situ resonance Raman study</article-title>. <source>J Molluscan Stud</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Biju-Duval</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Neogene paleontology in the northern Dominican Republic: 1. Field surveys, lithology, environment, and age</article-title>. <source>Bull Am Paleontol</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>89</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nehm</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Budd</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Palaeobiological research in the Cibao Valley of the Northern Dominican Republic</chapter-title>. <name name-style="western"><surname>Nehm</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Budd</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Evolutionary Stasis and Change in the Dominican Republic Neogene</source>. <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>. pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McNeill</surname> <given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klaus</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Budd</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname> <given-names>BP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishman</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Late Neogene chronology and sequence stratigraphy of mixed carbonate-siliciclastic deposits of the Cibao Basin, Dominican Republic</article-title>. <source>Geol Soc Am Bull</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>124</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vokes</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Neogene paleontology in the northern Dominican Republic 8. The family Muricidae (Mollusca: Gastropoda)</article-title>. <source>Bull Am Paleontol</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>97</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klaus</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Budd</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Comparison of Caribbean coral reef communities before and after Plio-Pleistocene faunal turnover: analyses of two Dominican Republic reef sequences</article-title>. <source>Palaios</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waller</surname> <given-names>TR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Neogene paleontology of the northern Dominican Republic. 24. Propeamussiidae and Pectinidae (Mollusca: Bivalvia: Pectinoidea) of the Cibao Valley</article-title>. <source>Bull Am Paleontol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>381</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allmon</surname> <given-names>WD</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Studying species in the fossil record: a review and recommendations for a more unified approach</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Allmon</surname> <given-names>WD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yacobucci</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Species and speciation in fossil animals</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>; in press.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duda</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names> <suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bolin</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Hidden diversity in a hyperdiverse gastropod genus: Discovery of previously unidentified members of a <italic>Conus</italic> species complex</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>867</fpage>–<lpage>876</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2008.08.009" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ympev.2008.08.009</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18783734</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duda</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matheny</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cryptic species differentiated in <italic>Conus ebraeus</italic>, a widespread tropical marine gastropod</article-title>. <source>Biol Bull</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>217</volume>: <fpage>292</fpage>–<lpage>305</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20040753</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozminsky</surname> <given-names>EV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lezin</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Distribution of pigments in the shell of the gastropod <italic>Littorina obtusata</italic> (Linnaeus, 1758)</article-title>. <source>Russ J Mar Biol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>238</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tenorio</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Systematic classification of recent and fossil Conoidean gastropods, with keys to the genera of cone shells</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Hackenheim, Germany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ConchBooks</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendricks</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saupe</surname> <given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hermsen</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allmon</surname> <given-names>WD</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Generification of the Fossil Record</article-title>. <source>Paleobiology</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>511</fpage>–<lpage>528</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holt</surname> <given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jønsson</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reconciling hierarchical taxonomy with molecular phylogenies</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>1010</fpage>–<lpage>1017</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syu061" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/sysbio/syu061</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25139888</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sowerby</surname> <given-names>I GB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Descriptions of new species of fossil shells found by J. S. Heniker, Esq</article-title>. <source>Q J Geol Soc London</source>. <year>1850</year>;<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guppy</surname> <given-names>RJL</given-names></name>. <article-title>On the Tertiary Mollusca of Jamaica</article-title>. <source>Q J Geol Soc London</source>. <year>1866</year>;<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>295</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pilsbry</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Revision of W. M. Gabb’s Tertiary Mollusca of Santo Domingo</article-title>. <source>Proc Acad Nat Sci Phila</source>. <year>1921</year>;<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>435</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maury</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Santo Domingo type sections and fossils, part 1</article-title>. <source>Bull Am Paleontol</source>. <year>1917</year>;<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname> <given-names>EF</given-names></name>. <article-title><italic>Conus sauros</italic>, a new <italic>Conus</italic> species (Gastropoda: Conidae) from the Gulf of Mexico</article-title>. <source>Novapex</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodring</surname> <given-names>WP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Geology and paleontology of Canal Zone and adjoining parts of Panama. Description of Tertiary mollusks (gastropods: Eulimidae, Marginellidae to Helminthoglyptidae)</article-title>. <source>U S Geol Surv Prof Pap</source>. <year>1970</year>;<volume>306-D</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ager</surname> <given-names>DV</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The nature of the stratigraphical record</chapter-title>, <edition>second edition</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Halsted Press</publisher-name>; <year>1981</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodring</surname> <given-names>WP</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Miocene Mollusks from Bowden, Jamaica, Part II: Gastropods and Discussion of Results</chapter-title>. <source>Contributions to the Geology and Paleontology of the West Indies</source>. <publisher-name>Carnegie Institution of Washington</publisher-name>; <year>1928</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pflug</surname> <given-names>HD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mollusken aus dem Tertiär von St. Domingo</article-title>. <source>Acta Humboldtiana, Ser Geol et Palaeontol</source>. <year>1961</year>;<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petuch</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>New Caribbean molluscan faunas</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Charlottesville, Virginia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Coastal Education &amp; Research Foundation</publisher-name>; <year>1987</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Guppy RJL. On the Tertiary fossils of the West Indies with especial reference to the classification of the Kainozoic rocks of Trinidad (Paper No. 4). Proc Sci Assoc Trinidad. 1867;Pt 3: 145–176.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodring</surname> <given-names>WP</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Panama land bridge as a sea barrier</article-title>. <source>Proc Am Philos Soc</source>. <year>1966</year>; <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>425</fpage>–<lpage>433</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gabb WM. On the topography and geology of Santo Domingo. Trans Am Philos Soc. 1873; 49–259.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Böse</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sobre algunas faunas Terciarias de México</article-title>. <source>Bol Inst Geol México</source>. <year>1906</year>;<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marks</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Miocene stratigraphy and paleontology of southwestern Ecuador</article-title>. <source>Bull Am Paleontol</source>. <year>1951</year>;<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pilsbry</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fauna of the Gatun Formation, Isthmus of Panama</article-title>. <source>Proc Acad Nat Sci Phila</source>.<year>1911</year>;<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>336</fpage>–<lpage>373</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gmelin</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Systema naturae per regna tria naturae</chapter-title>, <edition>13th edition</edition>. Vol <volume>1</volume>, pt <issue>6</issue>. <publisher-loc>Leipzig, Germany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>G. E. Beer</publisher-name>; <year>1791</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petuch</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Cenozoic seas: the view from eastern North America</chapter-title>. <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>; <year>2003</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landau</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vermeij</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Southern Caribbean Neogene palaeobiogeography revisited. New data from the Pliocene of Cubagua, Venezuela</article-title>. <source>Palaeogeogr Palaeoclimatol Palaeoecol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>257</volume>: <fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>461</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname> <given-names>LB</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Education and Career of Carlotta J. Maury: Part 1</article-title>. <source>Earth Sci Hist</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname> <given-names>LB</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Education and Career of Carlotta J. Maury: Part 2</article-title>. <source>Earth Sci Hist</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>52</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Finlay HJ. New specific names for Austral Mollusca. Trans Proc N Z Inst. 1927:488–533.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nybakken</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ecology of <italic>Conus</italic> on eastern Indian Ocean fringing reefs: diversity of species and resource utilization</article-title>. <source>Mar Biol</source>. <year>1975</year>;<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Environmental complexity and species diversity in the gastropod genus <italic>Conus</italic> on Indo-West Pacific reef platforms</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source>. <year>1967</year>;<volume>101</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>259</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Microhabitat factors affecting abundance and diversity of <italic>Conus</italic> on coral reefs</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>60</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Maximal species richness in <italic>Conus</italic>: diversity, diet and habitat on reefs of northeast Papua New Guinea</article-title>. <source>Coral Reefs</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duda</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names> <suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Species-level phylogeography and evolutionary history of the hyperdiverse marine gastropod genus <italic>Conus</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>272</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15619440</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname> <given-names>JBC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Dea</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Timing of the oceanographic and biological isolation of the Caribbean Sea from the tropical eastern Pacific Ocean</article-title>. <source>Bull Mar Sci</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>89</volume>: <fpage>779</fpage>–<lpage>800</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hermsen</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hendricks</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>. <article-title>W(h)ither fossils? Studying morphological character evolution in the age of molecular sequences</article-title>. <source>Ann Mo Bot Gard</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>95</volume>: <fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0120924.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>UE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hendricks</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Geometric morphometric character suites as phylogenetic data: extracting phylogenetic signal from Gastropod shells</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>366</fpage>–<lpage>385</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syt002" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/sysbio/syt002</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23325808</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>