<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">pmed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="flc">plme</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosmed</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1549-1277</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1549-1676</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030445</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">06-PLME-ED-0689</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Editorial</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Infectious Diseases</subject>
          <subject>Science Policy</subject>
          <subject>Public Health and Epidemiology</subject>
          <subject>Non-Clinical Medicine/Health Economics</subject>
          <subject>Non-Clinical Medicine/Health Policy</subject>
          <subject>Infectious Diseases/HIV Infection and AIDS</subject>
          <subject>Non-Clinical Medicine/Medical Education</subject>
          <subject>Non-Clinical Medicine/Bioethics</subject>
          <subject>Non-Clinical Medicine/History of Medicine</subject>
          <subject>Non-Clinical Medicine/Medical Law</subject>
          <subject>Public Health and Epidemiology/Environmental Health</subject>
          <subject>Women's Health</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy">
          <subject>Socioeconomic determinants of health</subject>
          <subject>Public Health</subject>
          <subject>Health Policy</subject>
          <subject>History</subject>
          <subject>Health education (including prevention and promotion)</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Social Medicine in the Twenty-First Century</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Editorial</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Stonington</surname>
            <given-names>Scott</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Holmes</surname>
            <given-names>Seth M</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <collab xlink:type="simple">The <italic>PLoS Medicine</italic> Editors</collab>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="current-aff" id="n1">
          <p><bold>E-mail:</bold> <email xlink:type="simple">medicine_editors@plos.org</email></p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>24</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e445</elocation-id><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2006</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The PLoS Medicine Editors et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article page="e294" related-article-type="companion" vol="3" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030294" xlink:title="Essay" xlink:type="simple">
				<article-title>Anthropology in the Clinic: The Problem of Cultural Competency and How to Fix It</article-title>
			</related-article><related-article page="e439" related-article-type="companion" vol="3" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030439" xlink:title="Essay" xlink:type="simple">
				<article-title>Is There a Global Bioethics? End-of-Life in Thailand and the Case for Local Difference </article-title>
			</related-article><related-article page="e421" related-article-type="companion" vol="3" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030421" xlink:title="Research Article" xlink:type="simple">
				<article-title>Indigenous Health and Socioeconomic Status in India</article-title>
			</related-article><related-article page="e419" related-article-type="companion" vol="3" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030419" xlink:title="Essay" xlink:type="simple">
				<article-title>Health Is Still Social: Contemporary Examples in the Age of the Genome </article-title>
			</related-article><related-article page="e399" related-article-type="companion" vol="3" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030399" xlink:title="Essay" xlink:type="simple">
				<article-title>How Did Social Medicine Evolve, and Where Is It Heading? </article-title>
			</related-article><related-article page="e405" related-article-type="companion" vol="3" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030405" xlink:title="Essay" xlink:type="simple">
				<article-title>Ethnic Disparities in Health: The Public's Role in Working for Equality </article-title>
			</related-article><related-article page="e199" related-article-type="companion" vol="3" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030199" xlink:title="Student Forum" xlink:type="simple">
				<article-title>Why Should Medical Students Care About Health Policy?</article-title>
			</related-article><related-article page="e449" related-article-type="companion" vol="3" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030449" xlink:title="Policy Forum" xlink:type="simple">
				<article-title>Structural Violence and Clinical Medicine</article-title>
			</related-article><related-article page="e349" related-article-type="companion" vol="3" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030349" xlink:title="The PLoS Medicine Debate" xlink:type="simple">
				<article-title>Is It Ethical for Patients with Renal Disease to Purchase Kidneys from the World's Poor? </article-title>
			</related-article><related-article page="e423" related-article-type="companion" vol="3" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030423" xlink:title="Essay" xlink:type="simple">
				<article-title>"Anecdotal Evidence": Why Narratives Matter to Medical Practice </article-title>
			</related-article><related-article page="e383" related-article-type="companion" vol="3" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030383" xlink:title="Research Article" xlink:type="simple">
				<article-title>Reconstructing Tuberculosis Services after Major Conflict: Experiences and Lessons Learned in East Timor </article-title>
			</related-article><related-article page="e342" related-article-type="companion" vol="3" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030342" xlink:title="Research Article" xlink:type="simple">
				<article-title>Insights into the Management of Emerging Infections: Regulating Variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease Transfusion Risk in the UK and the US</article-title>
			</related-article><related-article page="e452" related-article-type="companion" vol="3" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030452" xlink:title="Research Article" xlink:type="simple">
				<article-title>Reinterpreting Ethnic Patterns among White and African American Men Who Inject Heroin: A Social Science of Medicine Approach </article-title>
			</related-article><related-article page="e448" related-article-type="companion" vol="3" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030448" xlink:title="Research Article" xlink:type="simple">
				<article-title>An Ethnographic Study of the Social Context of Migrant Health in the United States</article-title>
			</related-article><related-article page="e394" related-article-type="companion" vol="3" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030394" xlink:title="Policy Forum" xlink:type="simple">
				<article-title>Time to Regenerate: Ecosystems and Health Promotion</article-title>
			</related-article><abstract abstract-type="toc">
        <p>The<italic>PLoS Medicine</italic> editors, and Guest Editors Scott Stonington and Seth Holmes, introduce a special collection of articles examining the social structures that contribute to illness and health.</p>
      </abstract><counts>
        <page-count count="2"/>
      </counts><!--===== Restructure custom-meta-wrap to custom-meta-group =====--><custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>citation</meta-name>
          <meta-value>The <italic>PLoS Medicine</italic> Editors, Stonington S, Holmes SM (2006) Social medicine in the twenty-first century. PLoS Med 3(10): e445. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030445" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030445</ext-link></meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>
      <graphic mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030445.social_logo" xlink:type="simple"/>
    </p>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title/>
      <p>In its launch issue in October 2004, <italic>PLoS Medicine</italic> signaled a strong interest in creating a journal that went beyond a biological view of health to incorporate socioeconomic, ethical, and cultural dimensions. For example, that first issue contained a policy paper on how the health community should respond to violent political conflict [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030445-b001">1</xref>], a debate on whether health workers should screen all women for domestic violence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030445-b002">2</xref>], and a study on the global distribution of risk factors for disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030445-b003">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>Two years on, our October 2006 issue takes our interest even further. It contains a special collection of ten magazine articles and five research papers devoted entirely to social medicine. We are delighted that the collection features many of the leaders in the field, including the renowned medical anthropologists Paul Farmer and Arthur Kleinman, the former United States Surgeon General David Satcher, and the Harvard professor of social medicine and psychiatry Leon Eisenberg.</p>
      <p>Most of our readers have welcomed our inclusive view of what a medical journal should highlight. Some, however, have been critical, suggesting that we should publish “less soft stuff” and more “hard science.” These critics might argue that in this era of stem cell research and the human genome project, of molecular medicine and DNA microarray technology, the notion of social medicine seems irrelevant and outmoded.</p>
      <p>But the ultimate role of a medical journal is surely to contribute to health improvement, and that means looking not just at molecules but at the social structures that contribute to illness. The stark fact is that most disease on the planet is attributable to the social conditions in which people live and work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030445-b004">4</xref>]. The socially disadvantaged have less access to health services, and get sicker and die earlier than the privileged. Despite impressive technological advances in medicine, global health inequalities are worsening.</p>
      <p>“All medicine is inescapably social,” said Leon Eisenberg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030445-b005">5</xref>], and we entirely agree. Take, for example, the announcement of the sequencing of the human genome, which the BBC predicted would mean we could “banish inherited disorders, screen people for their vulnerability to diseases, tailor treatment to an individual's genetic make-up, create thousands of new drugs and extend human lifespan” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030445-b006">6</xref>]. In time, perhaps these predictions will be partly or fully realized. What is certain, though, is that the human genome project has also opened up an immediate Pandora's Box of complex ethical, legal, and social issues. These issues include ensuring equity in patients' access to the fruits of the project and balancing the benefits, risks, and economic costs of genetic screening. Even the human genome is “inescapably social.”</p>
      <p>And so, to complement the papers on molecular medicine that we have published over the last two years—such as papers on genetic mutations that confer resistance to cancer drugs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030445-b007">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030445-b008">8</xref>] or on differentiation of insulin-producing cells from human neural progenitor cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030445-b009">9</xref>]—we have also dedicated space in the journal to considering the large-scale social forces that give rise to human disease and affect its distribution around the globe. These include economics, politics, legal institutions, and power structures.</p>
      <p>Throughout our special collection, one pioneer in understanding these large-scale social forces is repeatedly acknowledged—Rudolf Virchow. In his 1848 medical report of an outbreak of typhus in Silesia, Virchow concluded that poverty and living conditions, not biology, were the prime causes of the epidemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030445-b010">10</xref>]. While an understanding of these large-scale forces remains social medicine's base and one of its most important tasks, this special collection shows the ways in which finer-grained social forces have an equally important effect on health. The different levels at which social forces operate can be considered as four primary domains, beginning in the clinical encounter and opening outward to society and the globe.</p>
      <p>The first domain, then, is made up of the cultural and social aspects of the relationship between patients and health professionals. This relationship is a social negotiation affected by beliefs, practices, interests, and power dynamics. Communication within this relationship can have a powerful impact upon health outcomes. The influence of this relationship upon health is not limited to Western, allopathic, biomedical systems but is equally as important in other medical systems throughout the world [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030445-b011">11</xref>].</p>
      <p>The second domain involves patients' beliefs, practices, and experiences. Patients' experiences of and responses to suffering are not confined to the clinical encounter and vary dramatically among different populations. Understanding the specifics of people's everyday lives is essential to engaging with them and their illnesses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030445-b012">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030445-b013">13</xref>].</p>
      <p>The third domain is the culture of medicine itself. Health professionals and institutions have their own cultures that also go beyond clinical interactions. Health systems and health research both contain agendas, prejudices, and beliefs that can lead to certain perspectives being favored as the most legitimate. Understanding the culture of medicine is essential to understanding health professionals' attitudes toward illness, patients, and treatments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030445-b014">14–16</xref>].</p>
      <p>The final domain brings us, full circle, back to Virchow and the large-scale forces that shape health, which have become known as the social determinants of disease. The 15 papers in the special collection each relate to at least one of these four domains, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0030445-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p>
      <table-wrap content-type="3col" id="pmed-0030445-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030445.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
          <title>The Four Domains of Social Medicine in the Special Collection</title>
        </caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030445.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col id="tb1col1" align="left"/><col id="tb1col2" align="left"/><col id="tb1col3" align="left"/></colgroup><tbody><tr><td><bold>Domain of Social Medicine</bold></td><td><bold>Authors</bold></td><td><bold>Title and Reference</bold></td></tr><tr><td><bold>Relationship between patients and health professionals</bold></td><td>Arthur Kleinman and Peter Benson</td><td>Anthropology in the clinic: The problem of cultural competency and how to fix it. PLoS Med 3(10): e294.</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Patients' beliefs, practices, and experiences</bold></td><td>Philippe Bourgois, Alexis Martinez, Alex Kral, Brian R. Edlin, Jeff Schonberg, and Dan Ciccarone</td><td>Reinterpreting ethnic patterns among white and African American men who inject heroin: A social science of medicine approach. PLoS Med 3(10): e452.</td></tr><tr><td>&nbsp;</td><td>Tarif Bakdash and Nancy Scheper-Hughes</td><td>Is it ethical for patients with renal disease to purchase kidneys from the world's poor? PLoS Med 3(10): e349.</td></tr><tr><td><bold>The culture of medicine</bold></td><td>Dorothy Porter</td><td>How did social medicine evolve, and where is it heading? PLoS Med 3(10): e399.</td></tr><tr><td>&nbsp;</td><td>Scott Stonington and Pinit Ratanakul</td><td>Is there a global bioethics? End-of life in Thailand and the case for local difference. PLoS Med 3(10): e439.</td></tr><tr><td>&nbsp;</td><td>Maya L. Ponte</td><td>Insights into the management of emerging infections: Regulating variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease transfusion risk in the UK and US. PLoS Med 3(10): e342.</td></tr><tr><td>&nbsp;</td><td>Rafael Campo</td><td>&ldquo;Anecdotal evidence&rdquo;: Why narratives matter to medical practice. PLoS Med 3(10): e423.</td></tr><tr><td>&nbsp;</td><td>Rajesh Gupta</td><td>Why should medical students care about health policy? PLoS Med 3(10): e199.</td></tr><tr><td>&nbsp;</td><td>Nelson Martins, Paul M. Kelly, Jocelyn A. Grace, and Anthony B. Zwi</td><td>Reconstructing tuberculosis services after major conflict: Experiences and lessons learned in East Timor. PLoS Med 3(10): e383.</td></tr><tr><td><bold>The social determinants of disease</bold></td><td>Timothy H. Holtz, Seth M. Holmes, Scott Stonington, and Leon Eisenberg</td><td>Health is still social: Contemporary examples in the age of the genome. PLoS Med 3(10): e419.</td></tr><tr><td>&nbsp;</td><td>David Satcher</td><td>Ethnic disparities in health: The public's role in working for equality. PLoS Med 3(10): e405.</td></tr><tr><td>&nbsp;</td><td>Paul E. Farmer, Bruce Nizeye, Sara Stulac, and Salmaan Keshavjee</td><td>Structural violence and clinical medicine. PLoS Med 3(10): e449.</td></tr><tr><td>&nbsp;</td><td>Seth M. Holmes</td><td>An ethnographic study of the social context of migrant health in the United States. PLoS Med 3(10): e448.</td></tr><tr><td>&nbsp;</td><td>Colin Butler and Sharon Friel</td><td>Time to regenerate: Ecosystems and health promotion. PLoS Med 3(10): e394.</td></tr><tr><td>&nbsp;</td><td>S. V. Subramanian, George Davey Smith, and Malavika Subramanyam</td><td>Indigenous health and socioeconomic status in India. PLoS Med 3(10): e421.</td></tr></tbody></table> --></table-wrap>
      <p>In their compelling policy paper for this special collection, Paul Farmer and colleagues argue that while the search for the molecular basis of disease has been enormously fruitful, there has at the same time been a “desocialization” of scientific inquiry. In other words, they say, there has been “a tendency to ask only biological questions about what are in fact <italic>biosocial</italic> phenomena” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030445-b017">17</xref>]. We hope that our special collection helps to “resocialize” our understanding of disease distributions and outcomes.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We'd like to thank Philip R. Lee and Alan Brandt for their guidance in commissioning articles for the special collection.</p>
      <p>
        <italic>Seth M. Holmes and Scott Stonington are in the Department of Anthropology, History and Social Medicine, School of Medicine, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, California, United States of America. They acted as Guest Editors of this special collection on social medicine.</italic>
      </p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b001">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zwi</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>How should the health community respond to violent political conflict?</article-title>
					<source>PLoS Med</source>
					<volume>1</volume>
					<fpage>e14</fpage>
					<comment>DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0010014" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0010014</ext-link></comment>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b002">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Taket</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wathen</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacMillan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>Should health professionals screen all women for domestic violence?</article-title>
					<source>PLoS Med</source>
					<volume>1</volume>
					<fpage>e4</fpage>
					<comment>DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0010004" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0010004</ext-link></comment>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b003">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ezzati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vander Hoorn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>Distribution of major health risks: Findings from the Global Burden of Disease study.</article-title>
					<source>PLoS Med</source>
					<volume>1</volume>
					<fpage>e27</fpage>
					<comment>DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0010027" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0010027</ext-link></comment>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b004">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valentine</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loewenson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solar</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2006</year>
					<article-title>The Commission on Social Determinants of Health: Tackling the social roots of health inequities.</article-title>
					<source>PLoS Med</source>
					<volume>3</volume>
					<fpage>e106</fpage>
					<comment>DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030106" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030106</ext-link></comment>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b005">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1999</year>
					<article-title>Does social medicine still matter in an era of molecular medicine?</article-title>
					<source>J Urban Health</source>
					<volume>76</volume>
					<fpage>164</fpage>
					<lpage>175</lpage>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b006">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
					<collab xlink:type="simple">European Commission</collab>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>Ethical, legal and social aspects of genetic testing: Research, development and clinical applications.</article-title>
					<publisher-loc>Luxembourg</publisher-loc>
					<publisher-name>Office for Official Publications of the European Communities</publisher-name>
					<comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/research/conferences/2004/genetic/pdf/report_en.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://ec.europa.eu/research/conferences/2004/genetic/pdf/report_en.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 22 September 2006.</comment>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b007">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riely</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2005</year>
					<article-title>KRAS mutations and primary resistance of lung adenocarcinomas to gefitinib or erlotinib.</article-title>
					<source>PLoS Med</source>
					<volume>2</volume>
					<fpage>e17</fpage>
					<comment>DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0020017" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0020017</ext-link></comment>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b008">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Politi</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riely</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somwar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2005</year>
					<article-title>Acquired resistance of lung adenocarcinomas to gefitinib or erlotinib is associated with a second mutation in the EGFR kinase domain.</article-title>
					<source>PLoS Med</source>
					<volume>2</volume>
					<fpage>e73</fpage>
					<comment>DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0020073" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0020073</ext-link></comment>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b009">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2005</year>
					<article-title>Differentiation of insulin-producing cells from human neural progenitor cells.</article-title>
					<source>PLoS Med</source>
					<volume>2</volume>
					<fpage>e103</fpage>
					<comment>DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0020103" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0020103</ext-link></comment>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b010">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Virchow</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1879 [1985]</year>
					<article-title>Report on the typhus epidemic in Upper Silesia (1848).</article-title>
					<comment>In:</comment>
					<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rather</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group>
					<comment>editor</comment>
					<comment>Rudolf Virchow: Collected essays on public health and epidemiology</comment>
					<publisher-loc>Canton (MA)</publisher-loc>
					<publisher-name>Science History</publisher-name>
					<fpage>205</fpage>
					<lpage>319</lpage>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b011">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleinman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1981</year>
					<article-title>Patients and healers in the context of culture.</article-title>
					<publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>
					<publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>
					<fpage>427</fpage>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b012">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fadiman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1998</year>
					<article-title>The spirit catches you and you fall down: A Hmong child, her American doctors, and the collision of two cultures.</article-title>
					<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
					<publisher-name>Noonday Press</publisher-name>
					<fpage>341</fpage>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b013">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleinman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1988</year>
					<article-title>The illness narratives: Suffering, healing, and the human condition.</article-title>
					<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
					<publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>
					<fpage>284</fpage>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b014">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2002</year>
					<article-title>Randomized controlled crime: Post-colonial sciences in alternative medicine research.</article-title>
					<source>Soc Stud Sci</source>
					<volume>32</volume>
					<fpage>659</fpage>
					<lpage>690</lpage>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b015">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paci</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1997</year>
					<article-title>Disclosure practices and cultural narratives: Understanding concealment and silence around cancer in Tuscany, Italy.</article-title>
					<source>Soc Sci Med</source>
					<volume>44</volume>
					<fpage>1433</fpage>
					<lpage>1452</lpage>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b016">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pigg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2001</year>
					<article-title>Languages of sex and AIDS in Nepal: Notes on the social production of commensurability.</article-title>
					<source>Cult Anthropol</source>
					<volume>16</volume>
					<fpage>481</fpage>
					<lpage>541</lpage>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030445-b017">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nizeye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stulac</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keshavjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2006</year>
					<article-title>Structural violence and clinical medicine.</article-title>
					<source>PLoS Med</source>
					<volume>3</volume>
					<fpage>e449</fpage>
					<comment>DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030449" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030449</ext-link></comment>
				</element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>