<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
    <front>
        <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PLoS</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosmed</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1549-1676</issn><publisher>
                <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
            </publisher></journal-meta>
        <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PLME-RA-6208R3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000431</article-id><article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                    <subject>Research Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
                    <subject>Evidence-Based Healthcare/Health Services Research and
                        Economics</subject>
                    <subject>Public Health and Epidemiology/Health Policy</subject>
                </subj-group>
            </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Strategies and Practices in Off-Label Marketing of Pharmaceuticals: A Retrospective Analysis of Whistleblower Complaints</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Off-Label Marketing of
                    Pharmaceuticals</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Kesselheim</surname>
                        <given-names>Aaron S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                        <sup>2</sup>
                    </xref>
                    <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
                        <sup>*</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Mello</surname>
                        <given-names>Michelle M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                        <sup>3</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Studdert</surname>
                        <given-names>David M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
                        <sup>4</sup>
                    </xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
                        <sup>5</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
                <label>1</label>
                <addr-line>Division of Pharmacoepidemiology and Pharmacoeconomics, Department of
                    Medicine, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Boston, Massachusetts, United
                    States of America</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff2">
                <label>2</label>
                <addr-line>Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of
                    America</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff3">
                <label>3</label>
                <addr-line>Department of Health Policy and Management, Harvard School of Public
                    Health, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff4">
                <label>4</label>
                <addr-line>School of Law, University of Melbourne, Melbourne, Australia</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff5">
                <label>5</label>
                <addr-line>School of Population Health, University of Melbourne, Melbourne,
                    Australia</addr-line>
            </aff><contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Ross</surname>
                        <given-names>Joseph S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <role>Academic Editor</role>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Yale University School of Medicine, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">akesselheim@partners.org</email></corresp>
                <fn fn-type="con">
                    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.icmje.org/" xlink:type="simple">ICMJE</ext-link> criteria for authorship read and met: ASK MMM DMS.
                        Agree with the manuscript's results and conclusions: ASK MMM DMS.
                        Designed the experiments/the study: ASK DMS. Analyzed the data: ASK DMS.
                        Collected data/did experiments for the study: ASK DMS. Wrote the first draft
                        of the paper: ASK. Contributed to the writing of the paper: ASK MMM DMS.
                        Contributed to the design of the study: MMM.</p>
                </fn>
            <fn fn-type="conflict">
                <p>ASK reports consulting for the Alosa Foundation, a nonprofit organization that
                    runs the Independent Drug Information Service and is not affiliated in any way
                    with any pharmaceutical company. From 2008–2009, ASK served as an expert
                    witness for the state of Texas in a lawsuit against Merck related to improper
                    promotion of rofecoxib (Vioxx). From 2007–2008, ASK helped develop an
                    educational program to encourage evidence-based prescribing, with funding from a
                    grant derived from the settlement of a fraud case regarding improper promotion
                    of gabapentin (Neurontin).</p>
            </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>5</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e1000431</elocation-id><history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>10</day>
                    <month>9</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>25</day>
                    <month>2</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kesselheim et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under
                the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted
                use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and
                source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="toc">
                <p>Aaron Kesselheim and colleagues analyzed unsealed whistleblower complaints
                    against pharmaceutical companies filed in US federal fraud cases that contained
                    allegations of off-label marketing, and develop a taxonomy of the various
                    off-label practices.</p>
            </abstract><abstract>
                <sec>
                    <title>Background</title>
                    <p>Despite regulatory restrictions, off-label marketing of pharmaceutical
                        products has been common in the US. However, the scope of off-label
                        marketing remains poorly characterized. We developed a typology for the
                        strategies and practices that constitute off-label marketing.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                    <title>Methods and Findings</title>
                    <p>We obtained unsealed whistleblower complaints against pharmaceutical
                        companies filed in US federal fraud cases that contained allegations of
                        off-label marketing (January 1996–October 2010) and conducted
                        structured reviews of them. We coded and analyzed the strategic goals of
                        each off-label marketing scheme and the practices used to achieve those
                        goals, as reported by the whistleblowers. We identified 41 complaints
                        arising from 18 unique cases for our analytic sample (leading to
                        US$7.9 billion in recoveries). The off-label marketing schemes
                        described in the complaints had three non–mutually exclusive goals:
                        expansions to unapproved diseases (35/41, 85%), unapproved disease
                        subtypes (22/41, 54%), and unapproved drug doses (14/41, 34%).
                        Manufacturers were alleged to have pursued these goals using four
                        non–mutually exclusive types of marketing practices:
                        prescriber-related (41/41, 100%), business-related (37/41,
                        90%), payer-related (23/41, 56%), and consumer-related (18/41,
                        44%). Prescriber-related practices, the centerpiece of company
                        strategies, included self-serving presentations of the literature (31/41,
                        76%), free samples (8/41, 20%), direct financial incentives to
                        physicians (35/41, 85%), and teaching (22/41, 54%) and
                        research activities (8/41, 20%).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                    <title>Conclusions</title>
                    <p>Off-label marketing practices appear to extend to many areas of the health
                        care system. Unfortunately, the most common alleged off-label marketing
                        practices also appear to be the most difficult to control through external
                        regulatory approaches.</p>
                    <p>
                        <italic>Please see later in the article for the Editors' Summary</italic>
                    </p>
                </sec>
            </abstract><abstract abstract-type="editor">
                <title>Editors' Summary</title>
                <sec id="s5a1">
                    <title>Background</title>
                    <p>Before a pharmaceutical company can market a new prescription drug in the US,
                        the drug has to go through a long approval process. After extensive studies
                        in the laboratory and in animals, the pharmaceutical company must test the
                        drug's safety and efficacy in a series of clinical trials in which
                        groups of patients with specific diseases are given the drug according to
                        strict protocols. The results of these trials are reviewed by Federal Drug
                        Administration (FDA, the body that regulates drugs in the US) and, when the
                        FDA is satisfied that the drug is safe and effective for the conditions in
                        which it is tested, it approves the drug for sale. An important part of the
                        approval process is the creation of the “drug label,” a detailed
                        report that specifies the exact diseases and patient groups in which the
                        drug can be used and the approved doses of the drug.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s5a2">
                    <title>Why Was This Study Done?</title>
                    <p>Physicians can, however, legally use FDA-approved drugs
                        “off-label.” That is, they can prescribe drugs for a different
                        disease, in a different group of patients, or at a different dose to that
                        specified in the drug's label. However, because drugs'
                        manufacturers stand to benefit financially from off-label use through
                        increased drugs sales, the FDA prohibits them from directly promoting
                        unapproved uses. The fear is that such marketing would encourage the
                        widespread use of drugs in settings where their efficacy and safety has not
                        been rigorously tested, exposing patients to uncertain benefits and possible
                        adverse effects. Despite the regulatory restrictions, off-label marketing
                        seems to be common. In 2010, for example, at least six pharmaceutical
                        companies settled US government investigations into alleged off-label
                        marketing programs. Unfortunately, the tactics used by pharmaceutical
                        companies for off-label marketing have been poorly understood in the medical
                        community, in part because pharmaceutical industry insiders
                        (“whistleblowers”) are the only ones who can present in-depth
                        knowledge of these tactics. In recent years, as more whistleblowers have
                        come forward to allege off-label marketing, developing a more complete
                        picture of the practice is now possible. In this study, the researchers
                        attempt to systematically classify the strategies and practices used in
                        off-labeling marketing by examining complaints filed by whistleblowers in
                        federal enforcement actions where off-label marketing by pharmaceutical
                        companies has been alleged.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s5a3">
                    <title>What Did the Researchers Do and Find?</title>
                    <p>In their analysis of 41 whistleblower complaints relating to 18 alleged cases
                        of off-label marketing in federal fraud cases unsealed between January 1996
                        and October 2010, the researchers identified three non–mutually
                        exclusive goals of off-label marketing schemes. The commonest goal
                        (85% of cases) was expansion of drug use to unapproved diseases (for
                        example, gabapentin, which is approved for the treatment of specific types
                        of epilepsy, was allegedly promoted as a therapy for patients with
                        psychiatric diseases such as depression). The other goals were expansion to
                        unapproved disease subtypes (for example, some antidepressant drugs approved
                        for adults were allegedly promoted to pediatricians for use in children) and
                        expansion to unapproved drug dosing strategies, typically higher doses. The
                        researchers also identified four non–mutually exclusive types of
                        marketing practices designed to achieve these goals. All of the
                        whistleblowers alleged prescriber-related practices (including providing
                        financial incentives and free samples to physicians), and most alleged
                        internal practices intended to bolster off-label marketing, such as sales
                        quotas that could only be met if the manufacturer's sales
                        representatives promoted off-label drug use. Payer-related practices (for
                        example, discussions with prescribers about ways to ensure insurance
                        reimbursement for off-label prescriptions) and consumer-related practices
                        (most commonly, the review of confidential patient charts to identify
                        consumers who could be off-label users) were also alleged.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s5a4">
                    <title>What Do These Findings Mean?</title>
                    <p>These findings suggest that off-labeling marketing practices extend to many
                        parts of the health care delivery system. Because these practices were
                        alleged by whistleblowers and were not the subject of testimony in a full
                        trial, some of the practices identified by the researchers were not
                        confirmed. Conversely, because most of the whistleblowers were US-based
                        sales representatives, there may be other goals and strategies that this
                        study has not identified. Nevertheless, these findings provide a useful
                        snapshot of off-label marketing strategies and practices allegedly employed
                        in the US over the past 15 years, which can now be used to develop new
                        regulatory strategies aimed at effective oversight of off-label marketing.
                        Importantly, however, these findings suggest that no regulatory strategy
                        will be complete and effective unless physicians themselves fully understand
                        the range of off-label marketing practices and their consequences for public
                        health and act as a bulwark against continued efforts to engage in off-label
                        promotion.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s5a5">
                    <title>Additional Information</title>
                    <p>Please access these Web sites via the online version of this summary at
                            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000431" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000431</ext-link>.</p>
                    <list list-type="bullet">
                        <list-item>
                            <p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/" xlink:type="simple">US
                                    Food and Drug Administration</ext-link> provides detailed
                                information about <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/Drugs/default.htm" xlink:type="simple">drug approval
                                    in the US</ext-link> for consumers and for health professionals;
                                its <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/Drugs/GuidanceComplianceRegulatoryInformation/Surveillance/DrugMarketingAdvertisingandCommunications/ucm209384.htm" xlink:type="simple">Bad Ad Program</ext-link> aims to educate health care providers
                                about the role they can play in ensuring that prescription drug
                                advertising and promotion is truthful and not misleading.</p>
                        </list-item>
                        <list-item>
                            <p>The American Cancer Society has a page about <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cancer.org/Treatment/TreatmentsandSideEffects/TreatmentTypes/Chemotherapy/off-label-drug-use" xlink:type="simple">off-label drug use</ext-link></p>
                        </list-item>
                        <list-item>
                            <p>Wikipedia has pages on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prescription_drug" xlink:type="simple">prescription drugs</ext-link>, on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pharmaceutical_marketing" xlink:type="simple">pharmaceutical marketing</ext-link>, and on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Off-label_use" xlink:type="simple">off-label drug use</ext-link> (note that Wikipedia is a free
                                online encyclopedia that anyone can edit; available in several
                                languages)</p>
                        </list-item>
                        <list-item>
                            <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.taf.org/" xlink:type="simple">Taxpayers Against Fraud</ext-link> is a nonprofit organization
                                dedicated to helping whistleblowers, and it presents up-to-date
                                information about False Claims Act cases</p>
                        </list-item>
                        <list-item>
                            <p>The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.whistleblower.org/" xlink:type="simple">Government
                                    Accountability Project</ext-link> is a nonprofit organization
                                that seeks to promote corporate and government accountability by
                                protecting whistleblowers, advancing occupational free speech, and
                                empowering citizen activists</p>
                        </list-item>
                        <list-item>
                            <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.healthyskepticism.org/global/" xlink:type="simple">Healthy
                                    Skepticism</ext-link> is an international nonprofit membership
                                association that aims to improve health by reducing harm from
                                misleading health information</p>
                        </list-item>
                    </list>
                </sec>
            </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>ASK is supported by a career development award from the Agency for Healthcare
                    Research &amp; Quality (K08HS18465-01), and a Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
                    Investigator Award in Health Policy Research. MMM is supported by the Greenwall
                    Faculty Scholars Program in Bioethics. DMS is supported by a Federation
                    Fellowship from the Australian Research Council. The funders had no role in
                    study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation
                    of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
                <page-count count="9"/>
            </counts></article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec id="s1">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>In the US, a setting dominated by aggressive advertising of prescription drugs to
                patients and physicians, off-label marketing has been a controversial subject area.
                Physicians are permitted to prescribe drugs “off label”—that is,
                for purposes and patient populations outside of those formally approved by the US
                Food and Drug Administration (FDA). However, the FDA prohibits pharmaceutical
                companies from engaging in direct promotion of those unapproved uses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-KefauverHarris1">[1]</xref>. The
                rationale is that such marketing can lead to widespread uses of a drug that are not
                based on evidence of efficacy and safety, expose patients to uncertain benefits and
                the prospect of adverse effects, and undermine incentives for manufacturers to
                conduct clinical trials necessary to achieve FDA approval for new uses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-FughBerman1">[2]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Kesselheim1">[5]</xref>.</p>
            <p>Despite regulatory restrictions on off-label marketing, the practice appears to have
                flourished <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Kesselheim2">[6]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Almashat1">[7]</xref>. In 2009, Pfizer paid US$2.3 billion to settle
                allegations that it marketed its drugs illegally to physicians—the largest
                federal health care fraud settlement in US history <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Harris1">[8]</xref>. In 2010, at least six other
                manufacturers settled charges pertaining to off-label marketing, and more were under
                investigation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Department1">[9]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Sandburg1">[15]</xref>. The widely publicized litigation over the
                anti-inflammatory drug rofecoxib (Vioxx) also exposed marketing practices, such as
                seeding trials and ghost-writing of medical journal articles, that could promote
                off-label uses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Hill1">[16]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Ross1">[17]</xref>. What is known about off-label marketing practices comes
                largely in this form—namely, episodic reporting of high-profile prosecutions
                in the popular media <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Spielmans1">[18]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Steinman2">[20]</xref>, or personal testimony or congressional investigations
                arising from these same cases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-FughBerman2">[21]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Waxman1">[22]</xref>. There has been no systematic collection and analysis of
                these cases, which makes it difficult to identify larger themes and draw conclusions
                about the favored tactics.</p>
            <p>An accumulating number of these cases over the last decade makes such an analysis
                feasible. Moreover, the data available to conduct this type of analysis are
                remarkably rich because virtually all of the major cases have been instigated by
                “whistleblowers” whose complaints provide detailed, firsthand knowledge
                of the practices at issue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Kesselheim3">[23]</xref>. Because off-label marketing activities are secretive and
                difficult to detect and examine through other means <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Mello1">[24]</xref>, reports from these insiders
                provide a uniquely illuminating perspective on the range and nature of practices
                pursued.</p>
            <p>We analyzed whistleblower-initiated legal complaints filed in off-label marketing
                cases over the last 15 y to shed more light on this widely discussed but poorly
                understood challenge for health regulation. We aimed to create a typology for
                understanding these cases and a coherent thematic model for mapping pharmaceutical
                companies' fraudulent promotional behaviors and strategies. Improved
                understanding in this area has the potential to contribute to the development of
                strategies for better detection and enforcement.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
            <title>Methods</title>
            <sec id="s2a">
                <title>Design Overview</title>
                <p>The primary data for this study consisted of complaints filed by whistleblowers
                    in “qui tam” cases brought under the US federal False Claims Act
                    (FCA). In brief, the FCA prohibits the submission of false claims to the
                    government for reimbursement. Private citizens who notice potential violations
                    of the FCA can file a sealed complaint in federal court; those who do nearly
                    always retain a personal attorney to represent them and help them write their
                    complaint. The allegations in the complaint are then investigated by the US
                    Department of Justice (DOJ)-Civil Division, which, depending on the strength of
                    the evidence, may elect to intervene and take over the enforcement action,
                    essentially inserting the government as the lead party in the case. At this
                    point, the original whistleblower's complaint is usually unsealed. Multiple
                    complaints may be filed against the same company, but the DOJ intervenes only on
                    the first complaint brought to its attention or subsequent complaints that
                    provide new information (other nonintervened complaints against the same company
                    are usually dismissed and remain sealed). Because of this screening process and
                    the clout of the DOJ, nearly all complaints in which the DOJ intervenes lead to
                    a settlement or judgment against the defendant company. This study focused on
                    cases against pharmaceutical manufacturers for off-label marketing of
                    prescription drugs in which the DOJ intervened.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2b">
                <title>Setting and Participants</title>
                <p>Officials in the DOJ-Civil Division provided us with a full list of
                    pharmaceutical-related federal qui tam cases in which the DOJ intervened and
                    that were settled between January 1996 and 2005. We updated the list to include
                    all DOJ-intervened cases through October 2010 by conducting a search of DOJ
                    press releases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-United1">[25]</xref> and electronic media reports in Lexis-Nexis. We
                    cross-checked the final list with data compiled by Taxpayers Against Fraud, a
                    nongovernmental organization that tracks federal fraud actions. We then obtained
                    the unsealed complaints in these cases from the DOJ, on-line searches of
                    archives of US federal court filings <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-United2">[26]</xref>, and direct approaches to
                    lawyers involved in the litigation.</p>
                <p>Complaints are written documents that generally consist of a summary of the
                    allegations, a description of the whistleblower(s) and defendants, and a
                    detailed account of the allegations and the evidence supporting them. They may
                    be amended during the course of the investigation. We used the most recent
                    versions of the whistleblower-filed complaints available and accessible at the
                    extraction date (6 November 2010). We searched the summaries of the allegations
                    to determine which made allegations about unlawful off-label marketing by the
                    defendant company; 41 complaints in 18 cases did. These complaints formed our
                    analytical sample. Copies of the complaints can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/education/primarydocs.php" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/education/primarydocs.php</ext-link>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2c">
                <title>Qualitative Analysis</title>
                <p>We designed a structured instrument for abstracting information from the
                    complaints. An initial typology was generated using a standard coding
                    methodology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Glaser1">[27]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Constas1">[28]</xref>. Two investigators (ASK and DMS) acting independently
                    conducted a preliminary review of 20% of the complaints. After comparing
                    and discussing results of these reviews, we identified two major descriptive
                    domains for further analysis: the strategic goal of the off-label marketing
                    scheme and the specific practices manufacturers used to achieve that goal. We
                    also identified categories and subcategories within each of those domains. One
                    of us (ASK) then read each complaint and coded the details provided into the
                    prespecified categories and subcategories in each domain.</p>
                <p>It is important to note that the range of off-label marketing strategies and
                    behaviors we identified and report below are drawn from across the sample of
                    cases as a whole; no manufacturer was accused of all of them.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3">
            <title>Results</title>
            <p>A total of 41 complaints arose from 55 whistleblowers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-1000431-t001">Table 1</xref>). At the time of the alleged fraud, the
                whistleblowers worked as pharmaceutical sales representatives (39/55, 71%),
                sales or accounting managers (11/55, 20%), and unaffiliated physicians (5/55,
                9%). The cases were brought against 18 manufacturers, including both large
                companies with diverse drug portfolios (e.g., Pfizer, Eli Lilly) and smaller
                companies selling a relatively narrow range of products (e.g., Orphan Medical,
                Medicis). At the time of analysis, settlements had occurred in 16 of the 18 cases
                and totaled US$7.9 billion in damages.</p>
            <table-wrap id="pmed-1000431-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000431.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
                    <title>Pharmaceutical fraud cases related to off-label marketing, January
                        1996–October 2010.</title>
                </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pmed-1000431-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000431.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
                    <colgroup span="1">
                        <col align="left" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Company Name</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Complaints</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Complainants</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Drug(s)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case Status</td>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Parke-Davis/Warner-Lambert</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medical marketing liaison</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gabapentin (Neurontin)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Settled in 2004 (US$430 million)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Serono</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sales representatives, marketing managers, unaffiliated
                                nonprofit organization</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Somatropin (Serostim)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Settled in 2005 (US$704 million)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">InterMune</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sales representative</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Interferon gamma 1b (Actimmune)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Settled in 2006 (US$37 million)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bristol Myers-Squibb</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Business manager</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pravastatin (Pravachol), Metformin (Glucophage),
                                others</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Settled in 2007 (US$515 million)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cell Therapeutics</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sales representative</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arsenic trioxide (Trisenox)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Settled in 2007 (US$11 million)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orphan Medical</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sales representative</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sodium oxybate (Xyrem)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Settled in 2007 (US$20 million)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medicis</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sales representatives</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ciclopirox gel (Loprox)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Settled in 2007 (US$10 million)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cephalon</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sales representatives, sales manager, unaffiliated
                                physician</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Modafinil (Provigil), Tiagabine (Gabitril), Fentanyl
                                buccal (Actiq)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Settled in 2008 (US$425 million)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Eli Lilly</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sales representatives</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Olanzapine (Zyprexa), others</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Settled in 2009 (US$1.4 billion)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pfizer</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sales representatives, sales managers, unaffiliated
                                physician</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Valdecoxib (Bextra), Ziprasidone (Geodon), Pregabalin
                                (Lyrica), others</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Settled in 2009 (US$2.3 billion)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AstraZeneca</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sales representative</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Quetiapine (Seroquel)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Settled in 2010 (US$520 million)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ortho-McNeil-Janssen</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sales representatives, unaffiliated physician</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Topiramate (Topamax)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Settled in 2010 (US$81 million)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Novartis</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Marketing managers</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tobramycin (TOBI)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Settled in 2010 (US$72.5 million)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Forest</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sales representative, unaffiliated physician</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Citalopram (Celexa) and Escitalopram (Lexapro)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Settled in 2010 (US$313 million)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Allergan</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sales representative, managers, unaffiliated
                                physician</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OnabotulinumtoxinA (Botox)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Settled in 2010 (US$600 million)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Novartis</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sales representatives</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oxcarbazepine (Trileptal), others</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Settled in 2010 (US$422.5 million)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scios</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sales directors</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nesiritide (Natrecor)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Complaints unsealed (2009)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wyeth</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sales representatives</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sirolimus (Rapamune)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Complaint unsealed (2010)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                <bold/>
                            </td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                <bold>41</bold>
                            </td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                <bold>US$7.9 billion</bold>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table></alternatives></table-wrap>
            <sec id="s3a">
                <title>Off-Label Marketing Strategies</title>
                <p>According to the complaints, manufacturers aimed to increase use of their
                    products through off-label marketing schemes in three non–mutually
                    exclusive ways. They sought to expand uses to different disease entities, to
                    variations on the approved indication, and to alternatives to the approved
                    dosing schedule (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-1000431-t002">Table
                    2</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap id="pmed-1000431-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000431.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
                        <title>Frequency of off-label marketing strategies and practices reported in
                            whistleblower complaints.</title>
                    </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pmed-1000431-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000431.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
                        <colgroup span="1">
                            <col align="left" span="1"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        </colgroup>
                        <thead>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Descriptor</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>n</italic>/<italic>N</italic>, Percent</td>
                            </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <bold>
                                        <italic>Off-label marketing strategies</italic>
                                    </bold>
                                </td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <bold>Expansion to different disease entity</bold>
                                </td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <bold>35/41, 85%</bold>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Similar symptoms, different disease</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17/35, 49%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <bold>Expansion to variation of approved indication</bold>
                                </td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <bold>22/41, 54%</bold>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Different patient subgroup</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10/22, 45%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <bold>Expansion to variation of approved dosing schedule</bold>
                                </td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <bold>14/41, 34%</bold>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <bold>
                                        <italic>Off-label marketing practices</italic>
                                    </bold>
                                </td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <bold>Prescriber-related</bold>
                                </td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <bold>41/41, 100%</bold>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Direct financial incentives</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35/41, 85%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Distorted presentation of supporting
                                    evidence</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31/41, 76%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Influence on continuing medical education
                                    programs</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22/41, 54%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Influence on peer-reviewed literature,
                                    including ghost-writing</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20/41, 49%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Recruitment as clinical trial
                                    investigators</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8/41, 20%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Free samples</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8/41, 20%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <bold>Internal practices</bold>
                                </td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <bold>37/41, 90%</bold>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Intramural meetings</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27/37, 73%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Internal documents, brochures</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17/37, 46%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Use of company-based physicians and
                                    scientists</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19/37, 51%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Cloaking strategies</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25/37, 68%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Sham warnings from legal counsel</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 16/25, 64%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Direct orders to conceal
                                    activities</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 12/25, 48%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Financial incentives to employees</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15/37, 41%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <bold>Payer-related</bold>
                                </td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <bold>23/41, 56%</bold>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Discussions with prescribers about how to
                                    ensure reimbursement</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18/23, 78%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Development of billing systems that
                                    circumvent restrictions</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 13/18, 72%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Falsification of billing codes</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 11/18, 61%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Direct approaches to payers to ensure
                                    presence on formulary</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8/23, 35%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <bold>Consumer-related</bold>
                                </td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <bold>18/41, 44%</bold>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Direct identification of/approaches to
                                    consumers through physician office or pharmacy</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10/18, 56%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Funding of consumer organizations</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3/18, 17%</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table></alternatives></table-wrap>
                <sec id="s3a1">
                    <title>Expansion to unapproved disease entities</title>
                    <p>The most prevalent strategy involved expanding use on the basis of
                        diagnosis—that is, seeking off-label uses for disease entities
                        distinct from those approved by the FDA (35/41, 85%). For example,
                        gabapentin (Neurontin), approved as adjunctive treatment for certain types
                        of epilepsy, was also allegedly promoted as therapy for patients with
                        psychiatric disease such as bipolar disorder or depression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US1">[29]</xref>. Another
                        case involved Pfizer's alleged promotion of sildenafil (Viagra) to
                        treat low libido and to “restore and increase orgasmic
                        sensations” in women <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US2">[30]</xref>.</p>
                    <p>In some cases, a reported rationale for pursuing this type of expansion was
                        that limiting sales to the FDA-approved indication could not sustain needed
                        levels of revenue. One whistleblower from a small, single drug-focused
                        company stated that she was told “that management wanted to sell the
                        company, and that in order to make it a more attractive acquisition target,
                        it was necessary to show increased sales revenue” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US11">[31]</xref>.</p>
                    <p>In many examples of this marketing strategy, the drug was promoted for
                        treatment of similar symptoms across disease classes (17/35, 49%).
                        For example, modafinil (Provigil), initially approved for narcolepsy-related
                        sleepiness, was allegedly promoted for many types of sleepiness in
                        non-narcoleptic patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US12">[32]</xref>. Another example related to the anti-inflammatory
                        drug valdecoxib (Bextra), which was approved for a limited number of
                        pain-related indications and then allegedly promoted by Pfizer for pain
                        relief more broadly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US3">[33]</xref>.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3a2">
                    <title>Expansion to unapproved indications</title>
                    <p>The second most common strategy for off-label promotion was to expand the
                        product's use to different variations of the same condition (22/41,
                        54%). In some cases, the off-label disease was closely related to the
                        approved one—for example, when a product was specifically approved for
                        a severe manifestation of a condition but then promoted for milder forms. In
                        the case of nesiritide (Natrecor), the drug was approved for “acutely
                        decompensated heart failure” and was allegedly promoted in patients
                        with chronic stable heart failure as a preventative measure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US31">[34]</xref>. Although
                        both groups of patients had heart failure, they were quite different
                        manifestations of the disease.</p>
                    <p>One prominent subcategory of this type of off-label promotion focused on
                        patient subgroups different from those contemplated in the FDA approval
                        (10/22, 45%). For example, ciclopirox gel (Loprox) was approved for
                        fungal dermatoses in patients over age 10, but allegedly promoted by its
                        manufacturer to manage diaper-related fungal dermatitis in babies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US4">[35]</xref>. In some of
                        the antidepressant drugs in our sample, the product was approved for adult
                        use, but allegedly promoted to pediatricians and family practice physicians
                        specifically for young patients who demonstrated signs of depression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US2">[30]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US5">[36]</xref>. In the
                        case of citalopram (Celexa), studies that had shown dangers with using the
                        drug in pediatric populations were allegedly withheld from physicians as
                        part of the marketing campaign <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US5">[36]</xref>.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3a3">
                    <title>Expansion to unapproved dosing strategies</title>
                    <p>The final, and least common, variety of off-label expansion was off-label
                        prescribing based on different dosing regimens than that approved by the FDA
                        (14/41, 34%). Typically, manufacturers promoted higher doses to
                        enhance revenues by encouraging sale of more units of the product. For
                        example, the manufacturer of oxcarbazepine (Trileptal) allegedly promoted
                        use of the antiepileptic drug “as monotherapy for seizures using
                        extremely high dosages” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US6">[37]</xref>. By contrast, the manufacturer of sirolimus
                        (Rapamune), which was approved for transplant patients in combination with
                        cyclosporine and corticosteroids, allegedly trained its staff to encourage
                        its use in combination with “any drug or combination of drugs that a
                        physician could be convinced to prescribe” to enhance its market
                        possibilities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US7">[38]</xref>.</p>
                </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3b">
                <title>Off-Label Marketing Practices</title>
                <p>The marketing practices manufacturers allegedly employed to achieve these
                    strategic goals for off-label use fell into four non–mutually exclusive
                    categories: internal practices, payer-related practices, prescriber-related
                    practices, and consumer-related practices. We defined internal practices as
                    incentives and other aspects of the employment environment at the defendant
                    manufacturer that encouraged employees to promote off-label uses. Payer-related
                    practices were strategies aimed at encouraging insurers to pay for off-label
                    prescriptions. Prescriber-related and consumer-related practices involved direct
                    promotion of off-label drug use to prescription writers and consumers,
                    respectively.</p>
                <sec id="s3b1">
                    <title>Prescriber-related practices</title>
                    <p>All of the complaints we analyzed detailed off-label promotion to
                        prescribers; this was generally the centerpiece of the whistleblowers'
                        complaints. Though manufacturers are not supposed to discuss off-label uses
                        unless a physician inquires, many were accused of either flouting that rule
                        or designing their representatives' presentations in such a way as to
                        guarantee that discussion would inevitably lead to off-label uses.</p>
                    <p>According to the complaints, off-label use was frequently encouraged through
                        self-serving presentations of the scientific literature through which
                        physicians were given false or unbalanced study data supporting the
                        unapproved use (31/41, 76%). A common example was selective
                        presentation of favorable studies, where dangers from the off-label uses
                        allegedly being promoted were not mentioned <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US41">[39]</xref>. Other examples included
                        presenting one drug as being superior to another when no head-to-head
                        studies had been conducted <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US8">[40]</xref> and characterizing reports of individual cases or
                        poorly designed studies as definitive evidence supporting an off-label use
                            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US9">[41]</xref>.</p>
                    <p>A number of whistleblowers alleged that free samples had been provided (8/41,
                        20%) as a way to promote off-label use. The whistleblowers in this
                        group reported that these samples were intended to encourage physicians to
                        use a product on the basis of convenience, even though it might not be
                        approved for a certain use. In addition, many described how free samples
                        were intended to introduce unapproved patient populations to the
                        manufacturer's product with the intention of stimulating their
                        continued use.</p>
                    <p>Complaints alleged that manufacturers also encouraged off-label use through
                        direct financial incentives to physicians. Lavish gifts or honoraria were
                        mentioned in most complaints (35/41, 85%), with many whistleblowers
                        reporting strategies to target these gifts to physicians who were high
                        off-label prescribers (18/41, 44%). In some cases, physicians might
                        be invited to serve in focus groups or as consultants to the manufacturer,
                        although it was alleged that the association was intended not to obtain
                        expert advice, but to provide money to prescribers to positively reinforce
                        off-label use (15/41, 37%).</p>
                    <p>Finally, off-label use was encouraged among prescribers through teaching and
                        research activities. In over half the cases, Continuing Medical Education
                        (CME) seminars were organized with speakers known to promote off-label uses
                        (22/41, 54%). In a few cases, whistleblowers reported that CME
                        activities were organized by shell corporations to impart an appearance of
                        scientific neutrality <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US31">[34]</xref>. Nearly half of whistleblowers also alleged that
                        manufacturers sought to promote off-label drug use through journal
                        publications (20/41, 49%). These practices included falsely reporting
                        outcomes from patients in manufacturer-sponsored studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US51">[42]</xref> and
                        publishing “ghostwritten” articles supporting an unapproved use
                        written by the manufacturer under the name of a respected scientist <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US61">[43]</xref>. Finally,
                        a minority of whistleblowers alleged that manufacturers recruited physicians
                        to conduct clinical trials for them with the intent of encouraging off-label
                        use (“seeding trials”), rather than for any useful scientific or
                        information-gathering reasons (8/41, 20%).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3b2">
                    <title>Internal practices</title>
                    <p>Thirty-seven of the whistleblower (90%) complaints detailed particular
                        internal manufacturer practices intended to bolster the off-label marketing
                        (two of the four complaints where these were not mentioned were filed solely
                        by whistleblowers positioned outside the companies). All of the practices
                        described were reported to be company-wide, rather than the work of an
                        individual manager or group of managers. In 73% (27/37) of these
                        cases, the off-label marketing strategy was implemented through intramural
                        meetings and seminars in which marketing practices were discussed; in
                        46% (17/37) of them, it was also implemented through development of
                        brochures and other materials for dissemination; in 51% (19/37),
                        employees other than the sales representatives, such as internal physicians
                        and scientists, were involved.</p>
                    <p>Many of the complaints describing internal practices (25/37, 68%)
                        pointed to specific efforts by drug manufacturers to conceal off-label
                        marketing activities. Some described warnings from legal teams to avoid
                        off-label marketing (16/25, 64%). These were generally understood by
                        employees as providing “plausible deniability” to the company
                            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US3">[33]</xref>, and
                        were widely undermined through strategies such as verbal orders diverging
                        from what was declared in their company policies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US11">[31]</xref>. For example, one
                        whistleblower reported that his company purposefully designed “do not
                        detail” labels on materials related to off-label uses that could
                        easily be removed by a sales representative <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US2">[30]</xref>. A third of complaints
                        included reports of direct orders to conceal, such as “cleaning”
                        internal reports and memoranda of all mentions of off-label marketing
                        (12/25, 48%).</p>
                    <p>The complaints frequently described use of financial incentives for employees
                        to engage in off-label marketing. Forty-one percent (15/37) of the reports
                        of internal strategies described incentives or other aspects of
                        employees' compensation plans that were directly tied to effectively
                        implementing an off-label prescription strategy. In one case involving a
                        drug approved by the FDA for a rare indication, a whistleblower reported
                        that the company imposed sales quotas on representatives that could only be
                        met through expanding use beyond the limited approved indication <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US11">[31]</xref>. Other
                        examples included an internal sales “contest” for employees who
                        could demonstrate greatest compliance with marketing programs encouraging
                        off-label use <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US71">[44]</xref> and direct payments to employees to encourage
                        them not to report off-label marketing practices <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US4">[35]</xref>.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3b3">
                    <title>Payer-related practices</title>
                    <p>Payer-related promotional practices were reported in just over half of the
                        complaints (23/41, 56%) and fell into two categories: discussions
                        with prescribers about ways to ensure insurance reimbursement for their
                        off-label prescriptions (18/23, 78%) and direct discussions with
                        payers themselves (8/23, 35%) (three complaints described both). The
                        reports of discussions with prescribers in complaints described efforts to
                        educate them about how to manage the billing system to ensure that off-label
                        prescriptions were reimbursed, including advice on ways to bypass
                        insurers' restrictions on prescriptions of the product (13/18,
                        72%). For example, one whistleblower reported being taught to
                        overcome a requirement that patients receive a trial of a competitor's
                        drug first by instructing physicians to issue two different prescriptions at
                        the same time: one for the competitor's drug that the patient could
                        ignore, the other for the company's drug <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US81">[45]</xref>. The other strategy
                        commonly reported was to encourage providers to falsify billing codes
                        (11/18, 61%).</p>
                    <p>Seven complaints reported that manufacturers interacted with payers to
                        encourage off-label drug use by ensuring drugs were on a formulary for
                        off-label uses (four reports) or developing organizational protocols that
                        included the off-label use (four reports; one reported both). One
                        whistleblower described a bolder tactic for ensuring formulary coverage for
                        off-label use of a product: directing “their sales representatives to
                        garnish physician and patient letters of support to encourage
                        reimbursement” by Medicare intermediaries <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US91">[46]</xref>.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3b4">
                    <title>Consumer-related practices</title>
                    <p>Nearly half the complaints described off-label marketing practices focused
                        directly on consumers (18/41, 44%). The most common example involved
                        identifying consumers who could be off-label users (10/18,
                        56%)—for instance, by conducting chart reviews in
                        physicians' offices. The next step was bringing those patients eligible
                        for an off-label use to the physician's attention, thereby fusing a
                        consumer-focused practice with a prescriber-focused one. Other practices
                        intended to directly encourage off-label use among consumers allegedly
                        included promotion of consumer demand for off-label uses through payments to
                        nonprofit, consumer-focused disease management organizations in exchange for
                        their support of the off-label use <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US61">[43]</xref>. Another complaint
                        described on-line resources presented by a “noncommercial public
                        interest organization” that were intended to promote off-label use of
                        the product, but which were developed by a marketing firm linked to the
                        defendant company <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US10">[47]</xref>. In a third case, the whistleblowers alleged that
                        the company provided indigent patients with “gift certificates, phone
                        cards, and bus tokens” as inducements to seek out prescriptions of a
                        drug for an off-label purpose <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-US13">[48]</xref>.</p>
                </sec>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>Through a comprehensive review of whistleblower complaints, to our knowledge the
                first of its kind, we found descriptions of a range of marketing practices related
                to off-label promotion of prescription drugs. All of the strategies and behaviors we
                outlined were alleged by whistleblowers with special knowledge of company practices,
                although none of the complaints was subject to full trial and evaluation by a judge
                or jury. The study provides a basic empirical snapshot of the extent to which each
                of these strategies and practices have been employed, at least among cases exposed
                in qui tam litigation.</p>
            <p>Our findings show that off-label marketing practices have a broad reach. Similar
                behaviors and strategies were linked to manufacturers of varying sizes across drugs
                in virtually all therapeutic classes; they extended to many aspects of the health
                care system; they affected a multitude of players (prescribers, pharmacies, disease
                advocacy groups, CME organizations, consumers); and were pursued through virtually
                every facet of physician-industry relationships (paid consultancies, preceptorships,
                and collaboration in clinical trials and research publications). The alleged tactics
                in our analytic sample ranged from subtly encouraging physicians to ask for
                information about off-label uses to providing strong financial rewards for
                encouraging off-label uses; they also included targeting multiple links in the
                prescription production chain, from company scientists and sales representatives to
                prescribers.</p>
            <p>Some of the practices we identified have been highlighted in anecdotal reports and
                are relatively well known. Others have received little or no attention, such as
                pharmaceutical marketing representatives working directly with physicians and their
                office managers to circumvent reimbursement restrictions set by government payers
                and other insurers. Nearly a quarter of the whistleblowers alleged that
                pharmaceutical sales representatives were given access to patients'
                confidential medical records at physicians' offices for the purposes of
                trolling for prospective targets for illegal direct-to-consumer promotion of
                off-label uses. Despite the remarkable prevalence of this practice among the
                complaints we analyzed, media coverage has tended to center on other, more
                institutionally focused aspects of fraud.</p>
            <p>New regulatory strategies, both public and private, aimed in part at preventing
                off-label marketing, have proliferated in recent years. Medical journals have
                changed their authorship standards to foil ghostwriting <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Drazen1">[49]</xref>; following the example of
                several states, the federal health care reform legislation requires disclosure of
                pharmaceutical industry payments to physicians <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Physician1">[50]</xref>; the leading pharmaceutical
                manufacturers' association, PhRMA, has adopted a Code of Ethics that prohibits
                certain types of gifts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-PhRMA1">[51]</xref>; and a handful of academic medical centers have
                restricted or prohibited visits by pharmaceutical sales representatives <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Pollack1">[52]</xref>. Our findings
                support the need for these measures to combat gifts to physicians, which we
                identified as the single most prevalent modality of off-label promotion reported by
                whistleblowers.</p>
            <p>However, our results also suggest that additional steps will likely be necessary to
                curb off-label marketing. For example, interventions seeking to insulate physician
                education from industry influence have largely been limited to programs in which the
                manufacturer controls the content, but the reports in this study suggest that even
                so-called “unrestricted” educational grants from industry may be
                deployed to effect off-label marketing. A better policy solution would be fully
                independent programs of continuing medical education, an approach that has received
                limited support in a few states and has been proposed (but not enacted) in US
                Congress. Another potential solution is a central repository, independent from any
                physician or health care organization, where manufacturers can donate money that is
                then distributed for educational purposes.</p>
            <p>Some experts have suggested that fraudulent off-label marketing might be prevented
                through more substantial fines for manufacturers under investigation or other
                penalties for company managers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Edney1">[53]</xref>. Criminal prosecutions of executives are rare <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Wilson1">[54]</xref>, but the DOJ
                has signaled increasing interest in using this approach <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Edney1">[53]</xref>. While seeking to fortify
                deterrence through such tactics might address some behaviors, our findings suggest
                that some common off-label marketing practices may be difficult to control through
                external regulatory approaches because of their deep-seated nature. Whistleblowers
                in most of the cases we reviewed reported that private conversations between sales
                representatives and prescribers were a leading strategy for off-label promotion. The
                opportunity to prompt and answer physicians' questions about off-label uses,
                address their individual concerns, and provide a digest of empirical evidence that
                can be slanted as needed likely makes these conversations a particularly effective
                form of marketing. The fact that so many of the communications are oral and take
                place in private offices makes them very difficult for regulators to monitor and
                sanction. It is impossible to conceive of how anyone other than a company insider or
                a physician could bring many of these marketing practices to light (indeed, this
                underlines the distinctive strength of our data source). The move by a few prominent
                academic medical centers to ban sales representatives from the premises is a bold
                and powerful one, but it has not, as yet, been followed by many hospitals or
                physician practices.</p>
            <p>Changes in the PhRMA Code are a positive sign that the industry is responsive to
                public concerns about inappropriate marketing practices. In some news reports,
                manufacturers have described new corporate cultures that avowedly reject the illegal
                tactics described in the whistleblower complaints <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000431-Kindler1">[55]</xref>. However, in many of the cases
                we studied, manufacturers were reported to demonstrate awareness of existing
                regulations and engage in strategic behaviors to work around them (e.g., by giving
                employees lectures about the regulatory environment that were understood to be a
                smokescreen) or to mask their violations of the law (e.g., by encouraging employees
                to not enter off-label marketing calls in their logs).</p>
            <p>Our approach has limitations. First, although the DOJ conducted thorough
                investigations of each complaint in the study sample, the settled cases concluded
                without a full trial, which would have included formal fact-finding by a judge or
                jury. Thus, some allegations may be false and, for nearly all complaints, internal
                company documents that might have corroborated the complainants' specific
                reports remained confidential. Second, our analyses were conducted mainly at the
                complaint level, but nine of the 18 cases involved more than one complaint (the DOJ
                permits multiple complaints when each brings new information to bear on the case);
                the clustering of complaints in some cases may have inflated the reported prevalence
                of certain behaviors. Third, most whistleblowers were US-based sales representatives
                with a particular field of vision in relation to their companies' off-label
                marketing practices. It is possible that other behaviors and strategies exist that
                the whistleblower did not observe and the government investigations did bring to
                light. Our reliance on the text of the complaints means that we would have missed
                these. Finally, the complaints were composed to support claims of fraud under
                certain specific legislation, including the False Claims Act.</p>
            <sec id="s4a">
                <title>Conclusion</title>
                <p>Off-label marketing has been ubiquitous in the health care system and features
                    some behaviors and strategies that may be resistant to external regulatory
                    approaches. Our findings suggest that no regulatory strategy will be complete
                    and effective without physicians themselves serving as a bulwark against
                    off-label promotion. Aside from sales representatives and other company
                    insiders, who play important roles as whistleblowers, physicians are alone in
                    having a full view of many of the most insidious forms of illegal marketing
                    outlined in the complaints we reviewed. As physicians' understanding of
                    these practices and the consequences of inappropriate off-label promotion for
                    public health evolves, so may their enthusiasm for shutting them down.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <p>We would like to thank Joy Lee for her research assistance.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-KefauverHarris1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">Kefauver-Harris Drug Amendments</collab>
                    <year>1962</year>
                    <comment>Public Law 87-781 (codified as amended at 21 U.S.C. § 352
                        (n))</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-FughBerman1">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Fugh-Berman</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Melnick</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Off-label promotion, on-target sales.</article-title>
                    <source>PLoS Med</source>
                    <volume>5</volume>
                    <fpage>e210</fpage>
                    <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050210" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0050210</ext-link></comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Psaty1">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Psaty</surname>
                            <given-names>BM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ray</surname>
                            <given-names>W</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>FDA guidance on off-label promotion and the state of the
                        literature from sponsors.</article-title>
                    <source>J Amer Med Assn</source>
                    <volume>299</volume>
                    <fpage>1949</fpage>
                    <lpage>1951</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Henney1">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Henney</surname>
                            <given-names>JE</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Safeguarding patient welfare: who's in
                        charge?</article-title>
                    <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
                    <volume>145</volume>
                    <fpage>305</fpage>
                    <lpage>307</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Kesselheim1">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kesselheim</surname>
                            <given-names>AS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Avorn</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Pharmaceutical promotion to physicians and First Amendment
                        rights.</article-title>
                    <source>New Engl J Med</source>
                    <volume>358</volume>
                    <fpage>1727</fpage>
                    <lpage>1732</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Kesselheim2">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kesselheim</surname>
                            <given-names>AS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Studdert</surname>
                            <given-names>DM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Whistleblower-initiated enforcement actions against health care
                        fraud and abuse in the United States, 1996 to 2005.</article-title>
                    <source>Ann Int Med</source>
                    <volume>149</volume>
                    <fpage>342</fpage>
                    <lpage>349</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Almashat1">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Almashat</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Preston</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Waterman</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wolfe</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <month>December</month>
                    <day>16</day>
                    <article-title>Rapidly increasing criminal and civil monetary penalties against
                        the pharmaceutical industry: 1991 to 2010.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.citizen.org/hrg1924" xlink:type="simple">http://www.citizen.org/hrg1924</ext-link>. Accessed 10 February
                        2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Harris1">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Harris</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <month>September</month>
                    <day>2</day>
                    <article-title>Pfizer pays $2.3 billion to settle marketing
                        case.</article-title>
                    <comment>NY Times B4</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Department1">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">Department of Justice</collab>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <month>April</month>
                    <day>29</day>
                    <article-title>Two Johnson &amp; Johnson subsidiaries to pay over $81
                        million to resolve allegations of off-label promotion of
                        Topamax.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/2010/April/10-civ-500.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/2010/April/10-civ-500.html</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Department2">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">Department of Justice</collab>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <month>April</month>
                    <day>27</day>
                    <article-title>Pharmaceutical giant AstraZeneca to pay $520 million for
                        off-label drug marketing.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/2010/April/10-civ-487.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/2010/April/10-civ-487.html</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Department3">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">Department of Justice</collab>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <month>May</month>
                    <day>4</day>
                    <article-title>Novartis vaccines &amp; diagnostics to pay more than $72
                        million to resolve False Claims Act allegations concerning
                        TOBI.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/2010/May/10-civ-522.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/2010/May/10-civ-522.html</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Department4">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">Department of Justice</collab>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <month>September</month>
                    <day>15</day>
                    <article-title>Drug maker Forest pleads guilty; to pay more than $313
                        million to resolve criminal charges and False Claims Act
                        allegations.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/2010/September/10-civ-1028.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/2010/September/10-civ-1028.html</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Department5">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">Department of Justice</collab>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <month>September</month>
                    <day>30</day>
                    <article-title>Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corp. to pay more than $420
                        million to resolve off-label promotion and kickback allegations. 30 Sept
                        2010.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/2010/September/10-civ-1102.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/2010/September/10-civ-1102.html</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Department6">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">Department of Justice</collab>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <month>September</month>
                    <day>1</day>
                    <article-title>Allergan agrees to plead guilty and pay $600 million to
                        resolve allegations of off-label promotion of Botox®.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/2010/September/10-civ-988.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/2010/September/10-civ-988.html</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Sandburg1">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sandburg</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>Health care fraud investigations bedevil Pharma industry: if
                        you're not under investigation, it's only because you've
                        recently settled.</article-title>
                    <source>Pink Sheet</source>
                    <volume>71</volume>
                    <fpage>21</fpage>
                    <lpage>24</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Hill1">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hill</surname>
                            <given-names>KP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ross</surname>
                            <given-names>JS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Egilman</surname>
                            <given-names>DS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Krumholz</surname>
                            <given-names>HM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>The ADVANTAGE seeding trial: a review of internal
                        documents.</article-title>
                    <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
                    <volume>149</volume>
                    <fpage>251</fpage>
                    <lpage>258</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Ross1">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ross</surname>
                            <given-names>JS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hill</surname>
                            <given-names>KP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Egilman</surname>
                            <given-names>DS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Krumholz</surname>
                            <given-names>HM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Guest authorship and ghostwriting in publications related to
                        rofecoxib: a case study of industry documents from rofecoxib
                        litigation.</article-title>
                    <source>J Amer Med Assn</source>
                    <volume>299</volume>
                    <fpage>1800</fpage>
                    <lpage>1812</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Spielmans1">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Spielmans</surname>
                            <given-names>GI</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>The promotion of olanzapine in primary care: an examination of
                        internal industry documents.</article-title>
                    <source>Soc Sci Med</source>
                    <volume>69</volume>
                    <fpage>14</fpage>
                    <lpage>20</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Steinman1">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Steinman</surname>
                            <given-names>MA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Harper</surname>
                            <given-names>GM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Chren</surname>
                            <given-names>MM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Landefeld</surname>
                            <given-names>CS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bero</surname>
                            <given-names>LA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Characteristics and impact of drug detailing for
                        gabapentin.</article-title>
                    <source>PLoS Med</source>
                    <volume>4</volume>
                    <fpage>e134</fpage>
                    <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0040134" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0040134</ext-link></comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Steinman2">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Steinman</surname>
                            <given-names>MA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bero</surname>
                            <given-names>LA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Chren</surname>
                            <given-names>MM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Landefeld</surname>
                            <given-names>CS</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Narrative review: the promotion of gabapentin: an analysis of
                        internal industry documents.</article-title>
                    <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
                    <volume>145</volume>
                    <fpage>284</fpage>
                    <lpage>293</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-FughBerman2">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Fugh-Berman</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ahari</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Following the script: how drug reps make friends and influence
                        doctors.</article-title>
                    <source>PLoS Med</source>
                    <volume>4</volume>
                    <fpage>e150</fpage>
                    <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0040150" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0040150</ext-link></comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Waxman1">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Waxman</surname>
                            <given-names>HA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <month>May</month>
                    <day>5</day>
                    <article-title>Memorandum re: marketing of Vioxx to physicians.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://oversight.house.gov/documents/20050505114932-41272.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://oversight.house.gov/documents/20050505114932-41272.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Kesselheim3">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kesselheim</surname>
                            <given-names>AS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Studdert</surname>
                            <given-names>DM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mello</surname>
                            <given-names>MM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <article-title>Experiences of whistle-blowers in major fraud litigation against
                        pharmaceutical companies.</article-title>
                    <source>New Engl J Med</source>
                    <volume>362</volume>
                    <fpage>1832</fpage>
                    <lpage>1839</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Mello1">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mello</surname>
                            <given-names>MM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Studdert</surname>
                            <given-names>DM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Brennan</surname>
                            <given-names>TA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>Shifting terrain in the regulation of off-label promotion of
                        pharmaceuticals.</article-title>
                    <source>New Engl J Med</source>
                    <volume>360</volume>
                    <fpage>1557</fpage>
                    <lpage>1566</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-United1">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">United States Department of Justice</collab>
                    <year>2011</year>
                    <article-title>Office of Public Affairs Press Releases.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.usdoj.gov/03press/03_1_1.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.usdoj.gov/03press/03_1_1.html</ext-link>. Accessed 10
                        February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-United2">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">United States Judiciary</collab>
                    <year>2011</year>
                    <article-title>Public Access to Court Electronic Records.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pacer.psc.uscourts.gov/" xlink:type="simple">http://pacer.psc.uscourts.gov/</ext-link>. Accessed 10 February
                        2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Glaser1">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Glaser</surname>
                            <given-names>BG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Strauss</surname>
                            <given-names>AL</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1967</year>
                    <source>The discovery of grounded theory: strategies for qualitative
                        research</source>
                    <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Aldine De Gruyter Press</publisher-name>
                    <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">274</size>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Constas1">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Constas</surname>
                            <given-names>MA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1992</year>
                    <article-title>Qualitative data analysis as a public event: the documentation of
                        category development procedures.</article-title>
                    <source>American Educational Research Journal</source>
                    <volume>29</volume>
                    <fpage>253</fpage>
                    <lpage>266</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US1">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US ex rel. Franklin v. Parke-Davis, Division of Warner-Lambert
                        Company</collab>
                    <year>1996 August 13</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 1:96-CV-11651-PBS.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/WarnerLambert_Complaint1.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/WarnerLambert_Complaint1.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US2">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US ex rel. Collins, et al. v. Pfizer, Inc</collab>
                    <year>2007 August 13</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 1:04-CV-11780-DPW.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Pfizer_Complaint8.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Pfizer_Complaint8.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US11">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US, et al. ex rel. Lauterbach v. Orphan Medical Inc., Jazz
                        Pharmaceuticals Inc., and Dr. Peter Gleason</collab>
                    <year>2006 February 17</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 05-CV-0387-SJF-KAM.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/OrphanMedical_Complaint1.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/OrphanMedical_Complaint1.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US12">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US, et al. ex rel. Boise v. Cephalon, Inc</collab>
                    <year>2008 January 3</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 2:04-CV-04401-TON.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Cephalon_Complaint4.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Cephalon_Complaint4.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US3">
                <label>33</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US ex rel. Kopchinski v. Pfizer, Inc. and Pharmacia Corp</collab>
                    <year>2005 October 24</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 1:05-CV-12115-DPW.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Pfizer_Complaint7.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Pfizer_Complaint7.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US31">
                <label>34</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US, et al. ex rel. Stromv. Scios, Inc. and Johnson &amp; Johnson,
                        Inc</collab>
                    <year>2005 July 22</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 3:05-CV-03004-CRB.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Scios_Complaint2.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Scios_Complaint2.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US4">
                <label>35</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US, et al. ex rel. Mulqueen, et al. v. Medicis Pharmaceutical
                        Corp</collab>
                    <year>2007 April 5</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 2:04-CV-02389-KHV-GLR.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Medicis_Complaint1.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Medicis_Complaint1.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US5">
                <label>36</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US, et al. ex rel. Gobble v. Forest Laboratories Inc., Forest
                        Pharmaceuticals, Inc</collab>
                    <year>2010 January 8</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 03-10395-NMG.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Forest_Complaint1.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Forest_Complaint1.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US6">
                <label>37</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US, et al. ex rel. Copeland v. Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corp</collab>
                    <year>2010 August 26</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 2:06-CV-01630-LDD.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/NovartisCase2_Complaint1.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/NovartisCase2_Complaint1.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US7">
                <label>38</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US, et al. ex rel. Sandler and Paris v. Wyeth Pharmaceuticals, Inc. and
                        Pfizer Inc</collab>
                    <year>2010 May 24</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 2:05-CV-06609-JP.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Wyeth_Complaint1.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Wyeth_Complaint1.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US41">
                <label>39</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US ex rel. Marchese v. Cell Therapeutics, Inc., et al</collab>
                    <year>2007 August 24</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 2:06-CV-00168-MJP.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/CellTherapeutics_Complaint1.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/CellTherapeutics_Complaint1.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US8">
                <label>40</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US, et al. ex rel. Kruszewski v. Pfizer, Inc</collab>
                    <year>2009 August 21</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 2:07-CV-04106-JCJ.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Pfizer_Complaint5.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Pfizer_Complaint5.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US9">
                <label>41</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US, et al. ex rel. Wetta v. AstraZeneca Corporation</collab>
                    <year>2008 August 1</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 2:04-CV-03479-BMS.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/AstraZeneca_Complaint1.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/AstraZeneca_Complaint1.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US51">
                <label>42</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US ex rel. Gallagher v. Intermune, Inc</collab>
                    <year>2004 July 9</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 04:CV-4323.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Intermune_Complaint1.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Intermune_Complaint1.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US61">
                <label>43</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US ex rel. Westlock v. Pfizer, Inc., et al</collab>
                    <year>2008 August 1</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 1:08-CV-11318-DPW.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Pfizer_Complaint2.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Pfizer_Complaint2.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US71">
                <label>44</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US ex rel. Liter v. Pfizer, Inc</collab>
                    <year>2007 November 21</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 2:06-CV-00176-WOB.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Pfizer_Complaint1.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Pfizer_Complaint1.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US81">
                <label>45</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US ex rel. Farber and Schildhauer v. Pfizer, Inc</collab>
                    <year>2007 June 12</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 1:07-CV-10304-DPW.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Pfizer_Complaint6.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Pfizer_Complaint6.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US91">
                <label>46</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US ex rel. Smith v. Scios, Inc., et al</collab>
                    <year>2005 October 7</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 3:05-CV-04055-CRB.</article-title>
                    <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Scios_Complaint1.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Scios_Complaint1.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US10">
                <label>47</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US ex rel. Lang and Rushin v. Allergan, Inc</collab>
                    <year>2007 June 5</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 1:07-CV-01288-WSD.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Allergan_Complaint2.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Allergan_Complaint2.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-US13">
                <label>48</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">US, et al. ex rel. Garcia and Driscoll v. Serono, Inc</collab>
                    <year>2003 October 6</year>
                    <article-title>Civil Action 03-CV-11892-GAO.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Serono_Complaint1.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.drugepi.org/downloads/downloads/Serono_Complaint1.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Drazen1">
                <label>49</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Drazen</surname>
                            <given-names>JM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>de Leeuw</surname>
                            <given-names>PW</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Laine</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mulrow</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>DeAngelis</surname>
                            <given-names>CD</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <article-title>Toward more uniform conflict disclosures—the updated ICMJE
                        conflict of interest reporting form.</article-title>
                    <source>New Engl J Med</source>
                    <volume>363</volume>
                    <fpage>188</fpage>
                    <lpage>189</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Physician1">
                <label>50</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">Physician Payments Sunshine Act</collab>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <comment>H.R. 3590 § 6002</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-PhRMA1">
                <label>51</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">PhRMA</collab>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Code on interactions with health care
                        professionals.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phrma.org/files/attachments/PhRMA%20Marketing%20Code%202008.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.phrma.org/files/attachments/PhRMA%20Marketing%20Code%202008.pdf</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Pollack1">
                <label>52</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pollack</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006 September 12</year>
                    <article-title>Stanford to ban drug makers' gifts to doctors, even
                        pens.</article-title>
                    <comment>NY Times C2</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Edney1">
                <label>53</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Edney</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2010 October 15</year>
                    <article-title>Drugmaker CEOs may be targets for U.S. FDA in off-label cases,
                        lawyer says.</article-title>
                    <comment>Bloomberg News. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2010-10-14/drugmaker-executives-may-become-targets-of-fda-for-off-label-promotions.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2010-10-14/drugmaker-executives-may-become-targets-of-fda-for-off-label-promotions.html</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Wilson1">
                <label>54</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wilson</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2010 November 9</year>
                    <article-title>Ex-Glaxo executive is charged in drug fraud.</article-title>
                    <comment>NY Times B2</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000431-Kindler1">
                <label>55</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kindler</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2010 March 17</year>
                    <article-title>Business must change to earn back the public's
                        trust.</article-title>
                    <comment>Reuters. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blogs.reuters.com/great-debate/2010/03/17/business-must-change-to-earn-back-the-publics-trust/" xlink:type="simple">http://blogs.reuters.com/great-debate/2010/03/17/business-must-change-to-earn-back-the-publics-trust/</ext-link>.
                        Accessed 10 February 2011</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
        <glossary>
            <title>Abbreviations</title>
            <def-list>
                <def-item>
                    <term>DOJ</term>
                    <def>
                        <p>US Department of Justice</p>
                    </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                    <term>FDA</term>
                    <def>
                        <p>US Food and Drug Administration</p>
                    </def>
                </def-item>
            </def-list>
        </glossary>
        
    </back>
</article>